Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

About Our Project

Research Question
Background
Methods
Acknowledgements
Sources and Links

Research Question

At the beginning of the semester, we set out to explore translation differences between a well-known English text and its Japanese counterpart. We settles on Alice's Adventures in Wonderland, and asked: how are literary elements translated when their main purpose is to convey a sense of whimsy in a document?

Top

Background

Alice Translations in History

Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland was written by Lewis Carroll (a pseudonym created by Charles Lutwidge Dodgson) and was originally published in 1865. Carroll published three other Alice-related works: Through the Looking Glass and What Alice Found There (1871), Alice’s Adventure’s Under Ground (1886), and The Nursery ‘Alice’ (1890).

The first Japanese translation of one of Carroll’s works was of Through the Looking Glass published in 1899. Since this initial translation, there have been 1,271 editions of Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland and 321 editions of Through the Looking Glass translated into Japanese over the course of 119 years (it should be noted that the only other language with translations in the thousands is Spanish with 1,223 editions; the third most popular language, German, has less than half of this) (Lindseth 741). Titles often differ across translations, but the most commonly used title is Fushigi no Kuni no Arisu (「不思議の国のアリス」).

Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland continues to be translated, adapted, and used as inspiration for new works throughout Japan today. There is even a Lewis Carroll Society of Japan, which has two publications in both Japanese and English.

Project Background

The translation of Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland used for this project is titled Arisu wa Fushigi no Kuni de (「アリスはふしぎの国で」) and was translated by Yu Okubo (大久保ゆう訳) in 2014. There are several reasons why this edition was chosen. This edition, unlike many other translations, is out of copyright. One of the goals of this project is to allow the reader to view both the Japanese and English texts side-by-side, to truly be able to compare the original with its translation. The recent date of publication for this translation also made it appealing, as the language and referenced used would likely be more current, and any unknown features of the text would be easier to look up. Even the title of this work made it appealing; the deviation of the title from the accepted standard title used in the Japanese translation community indicated that there might be a larger amount of interesting linguistical features embedded within the text.

The texts used in this project can be found on the text pages, as well as on their respective original sources. The edition of the Japanese text can be found at Aozora Bunko, and the English text can be found at Project Gutenberg.

Translational Features

When translating a work from one language into another, differences between languages can cause difficulties in producing a target text from the original. Alice is well known for the difficulties it poses to translators.

Rhyme in particular is a feature that appears with some degree of frequency in English songs and poems, but that is almost nonexistent in Japanese. End-rhyme is a feature that is much easier to use in English than in Japanese due to word order; Japanese typically follows a subject-object-verb (SOV) pattern, whereas English word order is subject-verb-object (SVO). For end-rhyme to be present in Japanese poetry, one would have to rhyme verb endings and sentence-final particles, which vary based on several factors, including tense, formality, tone, and gender. Rhyme is also more common in poems that are metrical and contain parallelism (Brooks). English poems have strong focus on meter and parallelism, especially in couplets, whereas Japanese poems tend to embrace asymmetrical structures with few instances of strong stresses.

When translation occurs from Japanese into English, translators tend to not only change the asymmetrical structure and syllabic patterns of Japanese verse, but also that end-rhyme is placed in the English translations where it did not occur before. A Japanese tanka might be translated into a rhyming English quatrain (Brooks).

Idioms can be difficult to translate from one text to the next, as most languages do not have exact equivalents of the lexical properties of idiomatic phrases with the connotations. Idioms are usually translated in one of several ways: by using an idiom with a similar meaning (with either the same types of lexical items or different lexical items), by paraphrasing the meaning without an idiom, or by omitting the idiom completely (Takacs).

Similarly, Carroll’s use of word play makes for interesting translation techniques. Carroll’s use of puns can offer the same kinds of struggles as idioms do; translators must find a set of play on words that not only matches Carroll’s original meaning, but that also convey these puns within their own language (Lindseth). These problems are often tackled in a similar manner to idioms as well; some translators find ingenious ways to convey the similar meaning, while tweaking the play on words to make sense in their own language. Although most translators of Alice attempt to find a word play equivalent in their own texts, occasionally phrases or entire sections of chapter will be omitted due to the difficulty of translation.

Carroll’s use of phonetic and letter-based wordplay often requires translators to find similar sounds within their own languages. In cases of alliteration, consonance, and similar literary devices, it can sometimes be difficult for translators find a series of words with the same sound, especially if the attempt is to keep the same sound that Carroll used in his work.

Top

Methods

Linguistic Methods

Two kinds of words were looked for within the texts; nonsense words and incorrect word usage. Nonsense words (“ns”) are words that were coined or made up by Carroll or Okubo. Incorrect word usage (“iu”) was used as an umbrella term for words that are accepted by the dictionary, but that were used in the improper context.

The translation of play on words (“pow”) was also looked for when analyzing the texts. The types of word play focused on were idioms and syntactic play, lexical play, and phonetic and phonemic play. Each kind of word play occurs under the same tag. Word play that was based on structure or typography were not marked; this kind of word play was not as common. The English and this edition of the Japanese are also very similar in structure, with the same number of paragraphs per chapter and same basic structure to poems and songs.

Within the text, play on words often occurred in a specific format; a character would make a statement that would be misinterpreted by another character, who would respond, creating a sense of verbal irony for the reader. These exchanges would often occur over multiple paragraphs, which could make tagging while maintaining well-formedness difficult. For ease of tagging play on words within the structure of the text, only the second part of the play on words phrase would be tagged. For example:

Onomatopoeia (“onomatopoeia”) was added later to the project. Japanese uses a larger quantity of onomatopoeia than English does, but onomatopoeia is still present within the English text.

Within the original XML files, distinctions were made between words and phrases when marking up the text; however, these distinctions have not been included in the XHTML. Both <word> and <phrase> tags contained an attribute that was allowed the same specifications. Because of this, and because the differences between “words” and “phrases” were determined to be insignificant for this project, the XHTML includes only the attribute specifications in a <span> without distinguishing whether the text is a word or a phrase.

Not all attribute specifications were included in the final markup on this site; originally the texts were also marked up for uncommon word usage (“uc”) and Japanese text that ‘matched’ a marked phrase in the English, but that contained no device itself (“match”). Uncommon usage was originally placed on the English words and phrases that had were considered out-of-date, but they were later left out for several reasons. The Japanese translation of Alice used in this project was published in 2014, and likely contains modern Japanese in most cases. The other reason lies in the proficiency of Japanese of the researchers; as neither Dana nor Emily are native Japanese speakers, it would have been difficult to know for certain which Japanese was out-of-date. For this reason, the Japanese text contains no “uc” tags. Match, however, was left out of the HTML when it was decided that the two texts did not to mirror each other in their entirety when rendered on the site.

Computational Methods

We were able to use a variety of languages and systems to fully annotate Alice and come out with the data we wanted. As mentioned above, we started out using XML, simply by tagging unique features in the text with their own tags. We used a Relax NG schema to validate our manuscripts and make sure they had been tagged and organized properly. Our website was built using the host obdurodon, the program Fetch, and XHTML. We also created several CSS stylesheets in order to properly configure our website's aesthetics.

As the semester went on, we began using XSLT to convert our XML files to XHTML that we could put on our website. XSLT also helped us to create visualizations of our data, made by turning our XML into SVG files.

Top

Acknowledgements

Thank you to Dr. Birnbaum, our instructor, and Gabi Keane, our project advisor, for their advice, teaching, and support.

Thank you to the other students in our class for providing other perspectives to problems we encountered and helping us to look at things in a different way.

Thank you to Hiroyuki Good, for his help in locating crucial texts for this project.

Top

About Us

Emily Byron is a freshman (Class of 2021) at the University of Pittsburgh, main campus, majoring in linguistics and Japanese.

Dana Kaufhold is also a member of the Class of 2021 at Pitt, and is majoring in linguistics and political science.

Neither of us have had prior coding experience, but we highly recommend this class to anyone majoring in Humanities or Social Sciences. You don't need experience - you just need enthusiasm.

Top

Sources and Links

References

Brooks, E Bruce. “Nine Maxims on Translation.” Lectures: On Translation. 5 Dec. 2002, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Amherst, University of Massachusetts, www.umass.edu.
Carroll, Lewis. Alice's Adventures Under Ground. British Library, 26 Nov. 1864, www.bl.uk.
Lindseth, Jon A., and Alan Tannenbaum. Alice in a World of Wonderlands: the Translations of Lewis Carroll's Masterpiece. First ed., vol. 1 3, Oak Knoll Press, 2015.
Takacs, Csilla. “The Fascination of Translating Idioms.” Bulletin of the Transilvania Univ. of Braşov, no. 2, 2015, pp. 41–54. IV, www.ceeol.com.
Weaver, Warren. Alice in Many Tongues. Univ. of Wisconsin Pr., 1964.

Other Links

Our project's Github.
Our course's webpage.
Project Gutenberg, an online source for English texts that are out of copyright.
Aozora Bunko, an online source for Japanese texts that are out of copyright.

Top

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1
Chapter 2
Chapter 3
Chapter 4
Chapter 5
Chapter 6
Chapter 7
Chapter 8
Chapter 9
Chapter 10
Chapter 11
Chapter 12

Chapter 1

Click a checkbox to toggle a feature on or off in the text.

Cultural

Incorrect Word Usage

Nonsense Words

Onomatopoeia

Play on Words

Repetition

Down the Rabbit-Hole

Alice was beginning to get very tired of sitting by her sister on the bank, and of having nothing to do: once or twice she had peeped into the book her sister was reading, but it had no pictures or conversations in it, ‘and what is the use of a book,’ thought Alice ‘without pictures or conversations?’

So she was considering in her own mind (as well as she could, for the hot day made her feel very sleepy and stupid), whether the pleasure of making a daisy-chain would be worth the trouble of getting up and picking the daisies, when suddenly a White Rabbit with pink eyes ran close by her.

There was nothing so VERY remarkable in that; nor did Alice think it so VERY much out of the way to hear the Rabbit say to itself, ‘Oh dear! Oh dear! I shall be late!’ (when she thought it over afterwards, it occurred to her that she ought to have wondered at this, but at the time it all seemed quite natural); but when the Rabbit actually TOOK A WATCH OUT OF ITS WAISTCOAT-POCKET, and looked at it, and then hurried on, Alice started to her feet, for it flashed across her mind that she had never before seen a rabbit with either a waistcoat-pocket, or a watch to take out of it, and burning with curiosity, she ran across the field after it, and fortunately was just in time to see it pop down a large rabbit-hole under the hedge.

In another moment down went Alice after it, never once considering how in the world she was to get out again.

The rabbit-hole went straight on like a tunnel for some way, and then dipped suddenly down, so suddenly that Alice had not a moment to think about stopping herself before she found herself falling down a very deep well.

Either the well was very deep, or she fell very slowly, for she had plenty of time as she went down to look about her and to wonder what was going to happen next. First, she tried to look down and make out what she was coming to, but it was too dark to see anything; then she looked at the sides of the well, and noticed that they were filled with cupboards and book-shelves; here and there she saw maps and pictures hung upon pegs. She took down a jar from one of the shelves as she passed; it was labelled ORANGE MARMALADE, but to her great disappointment it was empty: she did not like to drop the jar for fear of killing somebody, so managed to put it into one of the cupboards as she fell past it.

‘Well!’ thought Alice to herself, ‘after such a fall as this, I shall think nothing of tumbling down stairs! How brave they’ll all think me at home! Why, I wouldn’t say anything about it, even if I fell off the top of the house!’ (Which was very likely true.)

Down, down, down. Would the fall NEVER come to an end! ‘I wonder how many miles I’ve fallen by this time?’ she said aloud. ‘I must be getting somewhere near the centre of the earth. Let me see: that would be four thousand miles down, I think--’ (for, you see, Alice had learnt several things of this sort in her lessons in the schoolroom, and though this was not a VERY good opportunity for showing off her knowledge, as there was no one to listen to her, still it was good practice to say it over) ‘--yes, that’s about the right distance--but then I wonder what Latitude or Longitude I’ve got to?’ (Alice had no idea what Latitude was, or Longitude either, but thought they were nice grand words to say.)

Presently she began again. ‘I wonder if I shall fall right THROUGH the earth! How funny it’ll seem to come out among the people that walk with their heads downward! The Antipathies, I think--’ (she was rather glad there WAS no one listening, this time, as it didn’t sound at all the right word) ‘--but I shall have to ask them what the name of the country is, you know. Please, Ma’am, is this New Zealand or Australia?’ (and she tried to curtsey as she spoke--fancy CURTSEYING as you’re falling through the air! Do you think you could manage it?) ‘And what an ignorant little girl she’ll think me for asking! No, it’ll never do to ask: perhaps I shall see it written up somewhere.’

Down, down, down. There was nothing else to do, so Alice soon began talking again. ‘Dinah’ll miss me very much to-night, I should think!’ (Dinah was the cat.) ‘I hope they’ll remember her saucer of milk at tea-time. Dinah my dear! I wish you were down here with me! There are no mice in the air, I’m afraid, but you might catch a bat, and that’s very like a mouse, you know. But do cats eat bats, I wonder?’ And here Alice began to get rather sleepy, and went on saying to herself, in a dreamy sort of way, ‘Do cats eat bats? Do cats eat bats?’ and sometimes, ‘Do bats eat cats?’ for, you see, as she couldn’t answer either question, it didn’t much matter which way she put it. She felt that she was dozing off, and had just begun to dream that she was walking hand in hand with Dinah, and saying to her very earnestly, ‘Now, Dinah, tell me the truth: did you ever eat a bat?’ when suddenly, thump! thump! down she came upon a heap of sticks and dry leaves, and the fall was over.

Alice was not a bit hurt, and she jumped up on to her feet in a moment: she looked up, but it was all dark overhead; before her was another long passage, and the White Rabbit was still in sight, hurrying down it. There was not a moment to be lost: away went Alice like the wind, and was just in time to hear it say, as it turned a corner, ‘Oh my ears and whiskers, how late it’s getting!’ She was close behind it when she turned the corner, but the Rabbit was no longer to be seen: she found herself in a long, low hall, which was lit up by a row of lamps hanging from the roof.

There were doors all round the hall, but they were all locked; and when Alice had been all the way down one side and up the other, trying every door, she walked sadly down the middle, wondering how she was ever to get out again.

Suddenly she came upon a little three-legged table, all made of solid glass; there was nothing on it except a tiny golden key, and Alice’s first thought was that it might belong to one of the doors of the hall; but, alas! either the locks were too large, or the key was too small, but at any rate it would not open any of them. However, on the second time round, she came upon a low curtain she had not noticed before, and behind it was a little door about fifteen inches high: she tried the little golden key in the lock, and to her great delight it fitted!

Alice opened the door and found that it led into a small passage, not much larger than a rat-hole: she knelt down and looked along the passage into the loveliest garden you ever saw. How she longed to get out of that dark hall, and wander about among those beds of bright flowers and those cool fountains, but she could not even get her head through the doorway; ‘and even if my head would go through,’ thought poor Alice, ‘it would be of very little use without my shoulders. Oh, how I wish I could shut up like a telescope! I think I could, if I only knew how to begin.’ For, you see, so many out-of-the-way things had happened lately, that Alice had begun to think that very few things indeed were really impossible.

There seemed to be no use in waiting by the little door, so she went back to the table, half hoping she might find another key on it, or at any rate a book of rules for shutting people up like telescopes: this time she found a little bottle on it, (‘which certainly was not here before,’ said Alice,) and round the neck of the bottle was a paper label, with the words ‘DRINK ME’ beautifully printed on it in large letters.

It was all very well to say ‘Drink me,’ but the wise little Alice was not going to do THAT in a hurry. ‘No, I’ll look first,’ she said, ‘and see whether it’s marked “poison” or not’; for she had read several nice little histories about children who had got burnt, and eaten up by wild beasts and other unpleasant things, all because they WOULD not remember the simple rules their friends had taught them: such as, that a red-hot poker will burn you if you hold it too long; and that if you cut your finger VERY deeply with a knife, it usually bleeds; and she had never forgotten that, if you drink much from a bottle marked ‘poison,’ it is almost certain to disagree with you, sooner or later.

However, this bottle was NOT marked ‘poison,’ so Alice ventured to taste it, and finding it very nice, (it had, in fact, a sort of mixed flavour of cherry-tart, custard, pine-apple, roast turkey, toffee, and hot buttered toast,) she very soon finished it off.

‘What a curious feeling!’ said Alice; ‘I must be shutting up like a telescope.’

* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * *

And so it was indeed: she was now only ten inches high, and her face brightened up at the thought that she was now the right size for going through the little door into that lovely garden. First, however, she waited for a few minutes to see if she was going to shrink any further: she felt a little nervous about this; ‘for it might end, you know,’ said Alice to herself, ‘in my going out altogether, like a candle. I wonder what I should be like then?’ And she tried to fancy what the flame of a candle is like after the candle is blown out, for she could not remember ever having seen such a thing.

After a while, finding that nothing more happened, she decided on going into the garden at once; but, alas for poor Alice! when she got to the door, she found she had forgotten the little golden key, and when she went back to the table for it, she found she could not possibly reach it: she could see it quite plainly through the glass, and she tried her best to climb up one of the legs of the table, but it was too slippery; and when she had tired herself out with trying, the poor little thing sat down and cried.

‘Come, there’s no use in crying like that!’ said Alice to herself, rather sharply; ‘I advise you to leave off this minute!’ She generally gave herself very good advice, (though she very seldom followed it), and sometimes she scolded herself so severely as to bring tears into her eyes; and once she remembered trying to box her own ears for having cheated herself in a game of croquet she was playing against herself, for this curious child was very fond of pretending to be two people. ‘But it’s no use now,’ thought poor Alice, ‘to pretend to be two people! Why, there’s hardly enough of me left to make ONE respectable person!’

Soon her eye fell on a little glass box that was lying under the table: she opened it, and found in it a very small cake, on which the words ‘EAT ME’ were beautifully marked in currants. ‘Well, I’ll eat it,’ said Alice, ‘and if it makes me grow larger, I can reach the key; and if it makes me grow smaller, I can creep under the door; so either way I’ll get into the garden, and I don’t care which happens!’

She ate a little bit, and said anxiously to herself, ‘Which way? Which way?’, holding her hand on the top of her head to feel which way it was growing, and she was quite surprised to find that she remained the same size: to be sure, this generally happens when one eats cake, but Alice had got so much into the way of expecting nothing but out-of-the-way things to happen, that it seemed quite dull and stupid for life to go on in the common way.

So she set to work, and very soon finished off the cake.

* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * *

ひゅうんとウサギ穴へ

アリスはあっきあきしてきた、木かげで、お姉さまのそばですわってるのも、何もしないでいるのも――ちらちらお姉さまの読んでる本をのぞいてみても、さし絵もかけ合いもない、「なら本のねうちって何、」とアリスは思う、「さし絵もかけ合いもないなんて。」

だから物思いにふけるばっかり（といってもそれなり、だって日ざしぽかぽかだとぼんやりねむくなってくるし）、デイジーの花輪作りはわざわざ立ち上がって花をつむほど楽しいものなのかしら――そこへふといきなり赤い目の白ウサギが１羽そばをかけぬける。

たいして目を引くようなところもないから、アリスにしてもさほどとんでもないとも感じないまま、聞こえてくるウサギのひとりごと。「およよ！　およよ！　ちこくでおじゃる！」（あとになって思い返すと、ここでふしぎがってしかるべきという気もするけど、そのときはみんな自然きわまると思えてね）その次にウサギがチョッキのぽっけから時計を取り出し、まじまじしてからかけ出したから、アリスもとびあがる、だってむねがはっとした、これまでそんなウサギ見たことない、チョッキにぽっけがあったり、時計を取り出したり、そこでわくわく気になる、野原を走って追っていくと、さいわいちょうど目の前でそいつはかき根の下、大きなウサギ穴にぴょんと入って。

たちまち飛びこみアリスは後を追う、またもどってこられるかなんて、ちっとも考えもせずに。

そのウサギ穴はまっすぐ続いて、まるでどこかトンネルみたい、そのあといきなり下り坂、いきなりすぎてふみとどまろうと思うまもなく気づいたらかなり深いふきぬけみたいなところに落っこちていて。

穴がすごく深いのか、落ちるのがすごくゆるやかなのか、どうにもひまがありすぎて、落ちるあいだにあたりは見られる、次にはどうなるのって思いもできる。まず下を見てみると、ゆく先はわかるけれども、暗すぎて何がなんだか。そのあと穴のぐるりを見ると、目にとまるのはぎっしりならんだ戸だなに本だな。あちらこちらに見える画びょうでとまった地図に絵。通りがかりにたなのひとつからびんを取り下ろすと、オレンジ・マーマレードとはられてあるのに、とてもがっかり、中身はから。とはいえ、びんを放るのはしのびない、だって下のだれかが死ぬといけないから、うまく戸だなのひとつへ通りすがりに置いておいた。

「ふふ！」とアリスは考えごと。「こうやって落ちておけば、もう 階段 転げ落ちるのなんてわけなくてよ！　おうちに帰ったら、あたくしみんなの 英雄 ね！　ええ、お 屋敷 の屋根から落ちたって、何も声をあげたりしないんだから！」（そりゃあまあそうだよね。）

ひゅうん、うん、うん。 いつになったら落ちきるのかな。「これまでのところで、どれくらい落ちたのかしら。」と声に出してみる。「地球のまんなかあたりには来てるはずね。ええと、６４００キロの深さだったかしら――」（だって、ほら、アリスはお 勉強 の時間にこういったことはそれなりにかじっていたからね、今ここでひけらかしたところで、聞いてくれる人もいないからどうしようもないけど、そらんじるけいこにはなったかな。）「――うん、それでだいたい深さは合ってるけど――あと今いるはずのイドとケイドは何かしら？」（アリスは 緯度 も 経度 もさっぱりだけど、今言うと 格好 がつくかなと思っただけ。）

やがてまた始めて。「まさかこのまま地球をまっすぐつきぬけて？　面白いっ、行きつく先の方々は頭を下にして歩いてるってわけね！　たんはい人ね、たぶん――」（聞いてる人がいなくてちょうどよかったかも、このとき、言葉づかいがまちがっていたからね）「――でもちゃんとお国のお名前何ですかっておうかがいしないと、ねえ。どうも、おくさま、ここはニュージーランド、それともオーストラリア？」（と言いながら左足を引いてひざを曲げようとしたんだけど――空中でこんなふうにスカートつまむところ思いえがける？　できると思う？）「そうしたら物をたずねたあたくしが、なんて物知らずの小娘って思われてよ！　だめ、聞けない。でももしかしたらどこかに書いてあるのが見つかるかも。」

ぴゅうん、うん、うん。ほかにやることもなくて、またすぐにアリスはしゃべりだす。「ダイナ、あたくしがいなくて、 今晩 はきっとさみしがっていてよ！」（ダイナはネコのこと。）「みんなお茶の時間にミルク出すのわすれてないといいけれど。ダイナちゃん！　いっしょに落ちてくれたらよかったのに！　空中にネズミはいなさそうだけど、コウモリならとれるかも、だってほら似ててよ、ネズミと。でもネコってコウモリ食べるのかしら。」ここでアリスはちょっとねむたくなってきて、うつらうつらしながらそのままひとりごと。「ネーコってコーモリ食べる？　ネーコって、コーモリ、食べる？」そのうちどっちがどっち食べるのかわからなくなって。まあほらどちらにしても答えはわからないから、どっちになっても大して変わりないけど。うとうと気分になると、ちょうど始まるゆめのなかではダイナと手をつないでおさんぽの場面、そこでにらんで言うんだ、「いいこと、ダイナ、はっきりお言い。あなたコウモリ食べたことあって？」そのときいきなり、どさっ！　どささっ！　とつっこんだのが枝にかれ葉の山で、落っこちるのおしまい。

アリスにけがはちっともなくて、ぴょいとすぐさままっすぐ立てる。見上げてみても、頭の上はまっくらやみ。前にはまた長い道があって、白ウサギがまだ見えるところにいて、かけ足で進んでいく。ぐずぐずしてるひまなんてない。走り出すアリスは風のよう、ちょうどぎりぎり向こうが角を曲がるところでこんな声が。「おおぴょんぬるかな、もう大ちこくでおじゃる！」すぐあとに続いてこっちも角を回ったはずなのに、ウサギのすがたはもうあたりになくて。気づけば天井低めの大広間、その天井からずらりとぶらさがったランプで照らされてて。

まわりにぐるりとドアがならんでいたのに、どれもみんな 鍵 がかかってて、だからアリスはえんえんあっちにこっちに、ぜんぶドアを試したあと、とぼとぼとまんなかに歩いていってね、どうやったらまたお外に出られるんだろうって。

するとそこでふと出くわした３本足の小さなテーブル、ぜんぶまるまるガラスでできていて、なんとその上にはただひとつ、ちっちゃな金の鍵、そこでアリスがまずひらめいたのが、この広間のドアのどれかに合うんじゃないかってこと。なのに何たること！　穴が大きすぎるか鍵が小さすぎるか、とにかく何にも開かない。ところがもう１度回ってみると、前には気付かなかったけれど、ちんまりカーテンのかかっているところにばったり、そのうらには高さ４０センチくらいのドアが。で、ちっちゃな金の鍵で合わないか試してみると、とってもうれしいことにぴったり！

アリスがドアを開けるとネズミ穴と同じくらいの小さな通り口が続いていて、しゃがんでのぞいてみると、向こうには見たこともないきれいなお庭が。もうその暗い広間から飛び出して、明るいお花畑とひんやり泉いずみのあたりを歩き回りたくてしかたがないのに、そのドアは頭も通らなくって。「頭だけが向こうに出ても結局、」とかわいそうにアリスは考えごと。「 肩 がぬけなくちゃどうしようもなくてよ。はあ、 望遠鏡 みたく身体をたためればどんなにいいか！　始め方さえわかれば、たぶんできるのに。」というのも、ほら、ここずっととんでもないことばかり起こってたから、アリスはほんとにできないことなんて、もう実はほとんどないじゃないかって気になってきてたんだ。

ドアの前でぼーとしててもしかたないみたいだから、テーブルのところに引き返して、もうひとつ鍵でも、いやせめて身体のたたみ方の本でも見つからないかなと思ってたんだけど、今度見るとテーブルには小びんが（「さっきまでぜったいなかったのに」ってアリスは言って）びんの首にはくるっと紙切れ、そこに〈ノンデ〉って文字がカタカナできれいに 印刷 してあって。

「ノンデ」っていうのはたいへんけっこう、でもお利口さんのアリスはあわててそんなことしたりしません。「だめ、まずたしかめること。」って言う、「そのびんに〈毒〉の 印 があるかないか見てみないと。」だってそういう小話をそれなりに読んだことがあって、そこでは子どもがやけどしたり、けだものに食べられたり、そのほかひどい目に合うのだけど、どれもお友だちの教えてくれた 簡単 な決まりをわすれたせいでそうなったわけ。たとえば、赤くてちんちんの火かきをずっと持ってるとやけどするよ、ナイフで指を深く切ったらふつうは血が出るよ、とか。で、ちゃんと覚えていたのが、〈毒〉の印のあるびんをぐびぐび飲むと、おそかれ早かれほぼまちがいなく毒に当たるよ、というもの。

とはいえ、このびんには〈毒〉の印はなかったので、アリスが思い切って味見してみると、とってもおいしくて（なんと風味はサクランボのタルトにカスタード、パイナップルから ローストチキンとキャラメル、あつあつのバタートーストまでがいっしょになったみたいで）あっというまに飲みきっちゃった。

＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊ 　　＊　　　＊　　　＊ ＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊

「とってもへんてこな気持ち！」とアリス。「望遠鏡みたく身体がたたまれてるのね。」

うん、その通り。今や背せたけはたった２５センチ、そして顔がぱっとあかるくなったのは、あの小さいドアからすてきなお庭に出るのに、今の大きさならちょうどいいって思ったから。とはいえ、まずはしばらくじっとしてたしかめる、もうちぢまないかなって、ちょっぴりどきどきしていたんだ。「だってほら、おしまいに、」とアリスはひとりごと。「ロウソクみたく、ぜんぶいなくなっちゃうのかも。あたくしそうしたらどうなっちゃうのかしら。」そこでロウソクがふっと吹き消されたあと火がどうなるのか思いうかべてみようとしたんだ、そんなの見たことなかったからね。

しばらくして、もう何も起こらないってわかったから、すぐにでもお庭へ出ることにしたんだ。でも、あああかわいそうにアリス！　ドアのところで、ちっちゃな金の鍵をわすれたことに気がついて、取ろうとテーブルに引き返してみると、今度は上にぜんぜんとどかない。ガラスの向こうにもうはっきりと見えるのに、せいいっぱいテーブルの足からのぼろうとしても、すべるすべる。しまいにはくたびれて、かわいそうにかわい子ちゃんはへたりこんで大泣き。

「ほら、そんなふうに泣いたってどうしようもなくてよ！」とアリスは自分に言い聞かせる。「あなた、今すぐにおやめなさい！」いつもご自分へのおいさめはとてもご立派りっぱ（あんまり言うこと聞かないけど）、時にはご自分へのおしかりがきびしくてなみだをためることもある。あるときなんか自分対自分のクローケーの試合でずるっこしたからってわすれずご自分の耳をおはたきになろうとするくらい。このへんてこな子は１人２役するのが大好きだったんだ。「でも今、」とかわいそうなアリスの考えでは「１人２役してもしかたなくてよ！　もう、あたくし、ちゃんとひとり分にも足りてないんだもの！」

ふと目を落とすと、テーブルの下に置かれたガラスの小箱。開けると中に小ぶりの焼菓子やきがしが見つかって、そこにはほしブドウで、〈タベテ〉って文字をきれいにならべてあって。「なら、いただきます。」とアリス。「身体が大きくなれば鍵にもとどくし、身体が小さくなってもドア下をくぐりぬけられる。いずれにしても庭には出られるから、どっちになってもかまわなくてよ！」

ちょびっとかじって、そわそわとひとりごと。「どちらの方？　どちらなの？」とどっちになるかわかるように、頭のてっぺんを手でおさえていたらびっくりびっくり、気づくと同じ背たけのまま。たしかに、焼菓子を食べただけじゃ、こういうふうになるのがふつうなんだけど、アリスはとんでもないことが起こるってほんとにそれだけを考えるようになってたから、まっとうな人生ががすごくつまらなくばかげたことに思えてね。

だからむきになって、たちまちぺろりと焼菓子をたいらげたんだ。

＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊ 　　＊　　　＊　　　＊ ＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1
Chapter 2
Chapter 3
Chapter 4
Chapter 5
Chapter 6
Chapter 7
Chapter 8
Chapter 9
Chapter 10
Chapter 11
Chapter 12

Chapter 2

The Pool of Tears

‘Curiouser and curiouser!’ cried Alice (she was so much surprised, that for the moment she quite forgot how to speak good English); ‘now I’m opening out like the largest telescope that ever was! Good-bye, feet!’ (for when she looked down at her feet, they seemed to be almost out of sight, they were getting so far off). ‘Oh, my poor little feet, I wonder who will put on your shoes and stockings for you now, dears? I’m sure I shan’t be able! I shall be a great deal too far off to trouble myself about you: you must manage the best way you can;--but I must be kind to them,’ thought Alice, ‘or perhaps they won’t walk the way I want to go! Let me see: I’ll give them a new pair of boots every Christmas.’

And she went on planning to herself how she would manage it. ‘They must go by the carrier,’ she thought; ‘and how funny it’ll seem, sending presents to one’s own feet! And how odd the directions will look! ALICE’S RIGHT FOOT, ESQ. HEARTHRUG, NEAR THE FENDER, (WITH ALICE’S LOVE). Oh dear, what nonsense I’m talking!’

Just then her head struck against the roof of the hall: in fact she was now more than nine feet high, and she at once took up the little golden key and hurried off to the garden door.

Poor Alice! It was as much as she could do, lying down on one side, to look through into the garden with one eye; but to get through was more hopeless than ever: she sat down and began to cry again.

‘You ought to be ashamed of yourself,’ said Alice, ‘a great girl like you,’ (she might well say this), ‘to go on crying in this way! Stop this moment, I tell you!’ But she went on all the same, shedding gallons of tears, until there was a large pool all round her, about four inches deep and reaching half down the hall.

After a time she heard a little pattering of feet in the distance, and she hastily dried her eyes to see what was coming. It was the White Rabbit returning, splendidly dressed, with a pair of white kid gloves in one hand and a large fan in the other: he came trotting along in a great hurry, muttering to himself as he came, ‘Oh! the Duchess, the Duchess! Oh! won’t she be savage if I’ve kept her waiting!’ Alice felt so desperate that she was ready to ask help of any one; so, when the Rabbit came near her, she began, in a low, timid voice, ‘If you please, sir--’ The Rabbit started violently, dropped the white kid gloves and the fan, and skurried away into the darkness as hard as he could go.

Alice took up the fan and gloves, and, as the hall was very hot, she kept fanning herself all the time she went on talking: ‘Dear, dear! How queer everything is to-day! And yesterday things went on just as usual. I wonder if I’ve been changed in the night? Let me think: was I the same when I got up this morning? I almost think I can remember feeling a little different. But if I’m not the same, the next question is, Who in the world am I? Ah, THAT’S the great puzzle!’ And she began thinking over all the children she knew that were of the same age as herself, to see if she could have been changed for any of them.

‘I’m sure I’m not Ada,’ she said, ‘for her hair goes in such long ringlets, and mine doesn’t go in ringlets at all; and I’m sure I can’t be Mabel, for I know all sorts of things, and she, oh! she knows such a very little! Besides, SHE’S she, and I’m I, and--oh dear, how puzzling it all is! I’ll try if I know all the things I used to know. Let me see: four times five is twelve, and four times six is thirteen, and four times seven is--oh dear! I shall never get to twenty at that rate! However, the Multiplication Table doesn’t signify: let’s try Geography. London is the capital of Paris, and Paris is the capital of Rome, and Rome--no, THAT’S all wrong, I’m certain! I must have been changed for Mabel! I’ll try and say “How doth the little--“’ and she crossed her hands on her lap as if she were saying lessons, and began to repeat it, but her voice sounded hoarse and strange, and the words did not come the same as they used to do:--

‘How doth the little crocodile
Improve his shining tail,
And pour the waters of the Nile
On every golden scale!

‘How cheerfully he seems to grin,
How neatly spread his claws,
And welcome little fishes in
With gently smiling jaws!’

‘I’m sure those are not the right words,’ said poor Alice, and her eyes filled with tears again as she went on, ‘I must be Mabel after all, and I shall have to go and live in that poky little house, and have next to no toys to play with, and oh! ever so many lessons to learn! No, I’ve made up my mind about it; if I’m Mabel, I’ll stay down here! It’ll be no use their putting their heads down and saying “Come up again, dear!” I shall only look up and say “Who am I then? Tell me that first, and then, if I like being that person, I’ll come up: if not, I’ll stay down here till I’m somebody else”--but, oh dear!’ cried Alice, with a sudden burst of tears, ‘I do wish they WOULD put their heads down! I am so VERY tired of being all alone here!’

As she said this she looked down at her hands, and was surprised to see that she had put on one of the Rabbit’s little white kid gloves while she was talking. ‘How CAN I have done that?’ she thought. ‘I must be growing small again.’ She got up and went to the table to measure herself by it, and found that, as nearly as she could guess, she was now about two feet high, and was going on shrinking rapidly: she soon found out that the cause of this was the fan she was holding, and she dropped it hastily, just in time to avoid shrinking away altogether.

‘That WAS a narrow escape!’ said Alice, a good deal frightened at the sudden change, but very glad to find herself still in existence; ‘and now for the garden!’ and she ran with all speed back to the little door: but, alas! the little door was shut again, and the little golden key was lying on the glass table as before, ‘and things are worse than ever,’ thought the poor child, ‘for I never was so small as this before, never! And I declare it’s too bad, that it is!’

As she said these words her foot slipped, and in another moment, splash! she was up to her chin in salt water. Her first idea was that she had somehow fallen into the sea, ‘and in that case I can go back by railway,’ she said to herself. (Alice had been to the seaside once in her life, and had come to the general conclusion, that wherever you go to on the English coast you find a number of bathing machines in the sea, some children digging in the sand with wooden spades, then a row of lodging houses, and behind them a railway station.) However, she soon made out that she was in the pool of tears which she had wept when she was nine feet high.

‘I wish I hadn’t cried so much!’ said Alice, as she swam about, trying to find her way out. ‘I shall be punished for it now, I suppose, by being drowned in my own tears! That WILL be a queer thing, to be sure! However, everything is queer to-day.’

Just then she heard something splashing about in the pool a little way off, and she swam nearer to make out what it was: at first she thought it must be a walrus or hippopotamus, but then she remembered how small she was now, and she soon made out that it was only a mouse that had slipped in like herself.

‘Would it be of any use, now,’ thought Alice, ‘to speak to this mouse? Everything is so out-of-the-way down here, that I should think very likely it can talk: at any rate, there’s no harm in trying.’ So she began: ‘O Mouse, do you know the way out of this pool? I am very tired of swimming about here, O Mouse!’ (Alice thought this must be the right way of speaking to a mouse: she had never done such a thing before, but she remembered having seen in her brother’s Latin Grammar, ‘A mouse--of a mouse--to a mouse--a mouse--O mouse!’) The Mouse looked at her rather inquisitively, and seemed to her to wink with one of its little eyes, but it said nothing.

‘Perhaps it doesn’t understand English,’ thought Alice; ‘I daresay it’s a French mouse, come over with William the Conqueror.’ (For, with all her knowledge of history, Alice had no very clear notion how long ago anything had happened.) So she began again: ‘Ou est ma chatte?’ which was the first sentence in her French lesson-book. The Mouse gave a sudden leap out of the water, and seemed to quiver all over with fright. ‘Oh, I beg your pardon!’ cried Alice hastily, afraid that she had hurt the poor animal’s feelings. ‘I quite forgot you didn’t like cats.’

‘Not like cats!’ cried the Mouse, in a shrill, passionate voice. ‘Would YOU like cats if you were me?’

‘Well, perhaps not,’ said Alice in a soothing tone: ‘don’t be angry about it. And yet I wish I could show you our cat Dinah: I think you’d take a fancy to cats if you could only see her. She is such a dear quiet thing,’ Alice went on, half to herself, as she swam lazily about in the pool, ‘and she sits purring so nicely by the fire, licking her paws and washing her face--and she is such a nice soft thing to nurse--and she’s such a capital one for catching mice--oh, I beg your pardon!’ cried Alice again, for this time the Mouse was bristling all over, and she felt certain it must be really offended. ‘We won’t talk about her any more if you’d rather not.’

‘We indeed!’ cried the Mouse, who was trembling down to the end of his tail. ‘As if I would talk on such a subject! Our family always HATED cats: nasty, low, vulgar things! Don’t let me hear the name again!’

‘I won’t indeed!’ said Alice, in a great hurry to change the subject of conversation. ‘Are you--are you fond--of--of dogs?’ The Mouse did not answer, so Alice went on eagerly: ‘There is such a nice little dog near our house I should like to show you! A little bright-eyed terrier, you know, with oh, such long curly brown hair! And it’ll fetch things when you throw them, and it’ll sit up and beg for its dinner, and all sorts of things--I can’t remember half of them--and it belongs to a farmer, you know, and he says it’s so useful, it’s worth a hundred pounds! He says it kills all the rats and--oh dear!’ cried Alice in a sorrowful tone, ‘I’m afraid I’ve offended it again!’ For the Mouse was swimming away from her as hard as it could go, and making quite a commotion in the pool as it went.

So she called softly after it, ‘Mouse dear! Do come back again, and we won’t talk about cats or dogs either, if you don’t like them!’ When the Mouse heard this, it turned round and swam slowly back to her: its face was quite pale (with passion, Alice thought), and it said in a low trembling voice, ‘Let us get to the shore, and then I’ll tell you my history, and you’ll understand why it is I hate cats and dogs.’

It was high time to go, for the pool was getting quite crowded with the birds and animals that had fallen into it: there were a Duck and a Dodo, a Lory and an Eaglet, and several other curious creatures. Alice led the way, and the whole party swam to the shore.

なみだまり

「てんへこりん、てんへこりん！」と声をあげるアリス（もうびっくりのあまり、 一時 ちゃんとした言葉づかいをどわすれしてね）。「今度は身体が広げられてる、世界最大の望遠鏡をのばしてるみたい！　ごきげんよう、あんよちゃん！」（だって足元を見下ろすと、どんどん遠ざかって、ほとんど見えなくなりそうで。）「ああ、おいたわしや、あんよちゃん、こうなったらどなたにくつやくつ下をはかせてもらおうかしら、ねえ？　ぜったいあたくしには無理だからっ！　あんまりにもはなれすぎて、こっちからめんどう見切れなくてよ。できるだけご自分で何とかなさることね――でも気づかいはしてあげないと。」とアリスは思って、「でないと行きたい方に歩いてくれないかも！　そうね、クリスマスごとに新しいブーツをさし上げてよ。」

頭のなかであれこれ、どうしようかとめぐらせ続けてね。「ひとに運んでもらわないと。」と考えて、「って、もうふきだしそう、自分のあんよにプレゼントだなんて！　あて名だっておかしなものになってよ だんろ前の しきものにお住まいの 　 アリスの右足さまへ 　　　 アリスから 愛 をこめて まったく！　あたくしの話もすっからかんね！」

ちょうどそこで、頭が広間の天井にごつん。なんとただいま背たけは２メートル７５をややこえたあたり、たちまちちっちゃな金の鍵を取り上げて、お庭のドアへあわてて向かう。

ふびんなアリス！　がんばってもできるのは、横向きにねそべって片目でお庭をのぞくだけ、向こうへ行く望みなんて、これまで以上にありえない。へたりこんでまた大泣きのはじまり。

「あなた 恥 をお知りなさい。」とアリス。「あなたみたいな気高い娘が」（たしかにお高い）「こんな泣きに泣いて！　ただちにおやめ、いいこと！」けれどもやっぱりそのまま、流すなみだはたっぷり 大量 、しまいにぐるりと大きな池になって、深さおよそ１０センチ、広間も半分ひたってしまう。

しばらくして聞こえてくる遠くのぱたぱたという足音、あわててなみだをぬぐって近づくものに目をやると、そう、あの白ウサギがまた帰ってきたんだ、おめかしして、白ヤギの手ぶくろを片手に、大きなせんすをもう片手に持っていてね。大わらわでどたばたやってきて、ぶつぶつ言いながらこっちへ来るんだ。「およよ！　 御前 さま、御前さま！　およよ！　お待ちさせたらかんかん、そんなのいやでおじゃる！」まさにアリスはすがる思いで、だれか助けてと言いたいところだったから、近くを通りがかったウサギにおずおずと弱々しげに声をかけてみる。「もし、よろしくて――」びくっとしたウサギは、はたと白手ぶくろとせんすを落として、全速力でぴゅーっと暗がりに消え去っちゃった。

せんすと手ぶくろを拾い上げたアリス、その部屋が暑苦しいので、ずーっと自分をあおぎながらひとりごとの続き――「もう、もう！　今日はけったいなことばかり！　でも昨日はずっといつも通りだったのに。もしや夜中のうちにあたくしの身に何か。待って。今朝起きたときのあたくしはちゃんとあたくし？　どうも少しちがっていた気がしないでもなくてよ。でもあたくしでないのなら気になるのは、『今のあたくしはいったいどなた』ってこと。んもう、まったくややこしい！」そこで同い年の知り合いの子のことをみんな思いうかべていって、自分がそのうちのだれかになっていないかたしかめたんだ。

「あたくしがエイダでないことはたしかね。」とつぶやく。「だってあの子の 髪 はあんなに長いまき毛、あたくしはちっともまきがなくてよ――それときっとメイベルでもないはず、だってあたくしは物知りっていうのに、あの子、ふん！　知らないにもほどがあってよ！　それにあの子はあの子、あたくしはあたくし、だから――ああ、もう！　なんてややこしいの！　どうかしら、ちゃんと覚えてたこと覚えてる？　ええと４×５＝１２、４×６＝１３、４×７――ああ、もう！　そんな調子じゃいつまでも２０にならなくてよ！　とはいえ九九なんて大したことないんだから。地理を試すの。ロンドンはパリの 都 、パリはローマの都、それからローマは――ちがう、そんなのまちがいに決まってる！　メイベルになっちゃったにちがいなくてよ！　だったら『がんばるぞミツバチ』のお歌はどう？」そこでおけいこごとみたく、ひざ前に手を重ねて、そらんじてみたんだけど、声ががらがらでとっぴで、それに歌詞かしもいつも通りでなくって。

びっくりだ　わあにさん
しっぽがね　ぴかーん
ナイルがわ　ざあぶざぶ
うろこにね　びしゃーん！

キバだして　にいんやり
ツメひろげ　じゃきーん
おいでませ　さかなちゃん
にこにこ……がぶりっ！

「ぜんぜん歌詞がちがってよ。」とかわいそうにアリスはまた目になみだをいっぱいにためながら、言葉を続けた。「やっぱりあたくしメイベルにちがいないのね、だったらあたくしあのせせこましい小屋にうつり住まなきゃいけないことになって、しかも遊ぶおもちゃもろくにないの、うわあん！　お勉強も山もりよ！　いやあ！　あたくし心に決めた、あたくしがメイベルなら、ここでじっとしててやるんだから！　どなたかがのぞいて『お上がりなさい！』なんて言ってもむだなんだから！　あたくし上目で申しあげてよ、『ところであたくし何者？　まずそれにお答えになって。それから、それがあたくしのなりたい方なら上がりますけど、ちがうようでしたらほかのどなたかになるまで、ここでじっとしております。』――でも、ああもう！」とアリスはいきなりわっと泣き出して、「そののぞいてくれるどなたかが、いてくださったらどんなにいいか！　もうもううんざりよ、こんなところでひとりぼっちだなんて！」

こう言いつつ自分の手に目を落としてみるとびっくり、見るとしゃべっているあいだにウサギさんの白手ぶくろをはめていたんだ。「どうしてこんなことができてるの？」と思ってね、「また小さくなってるにちがいないわ。」起きあがってテーブルまで行ってそれで背たけをはかってみると、だいたいしかわからないながらも、今はおよそ６０センチで、大いそぎでちぢみつつあってね。わけはすぐにわかった、持っているせんすのせいなんだ。あわてて手放すと、まさにそのときからちぢみはすっかりおさまって。

「まったく、命からがらね！」と言うアリスはいきなり変わったことにびくびくものだったんだけど、自分がまだちゃんとあるってわかってほっとしてね。「さて今こそお庭よ！」といちもくさんにあの小さなドアへもどったんだけど、なのに、ああ！　小さなドアはまたしまっていて、ちっちゃな金の鍵も前と同じでガラスのテーブルの上、だから「もう今までで最悪」とかわいそうにその子は思うしかない。「だってこんなちっちゃくなったの初めてなのよ、初めて！　正直ひどすぎてよ、ひどすぎ！」

と口に出したとたん、足をすべらせ、たちまちぼちゃん！　しょっぱい水に首までつかって。初めのうちは海か何かに落ちたと思ってね。「たしかこういう場合は、線路から引き返せばよくてよ。」とひとりごと。（アリスは生まれてこのかた１度だけ海辺に行ったことがあったから、ふつうにこう考えたんだ。イギリスでは海に行くと、かならず砂はまにたくさん 車輪 のついた箱がたの着がえ部屋があってね、子どもたちは木のくま手で砂をほじっていて、あとはずらり海の家にその後ろが線路の駅。）でもすぐにはっとした、いるのは自分が３メートル近いときに泣いて作ったなみだまりなんだって。

「あんなに泣くんじゃなかった！」と言いながらアリスは水をかいて前に進もうとしてね。「 罰 が当たろうとしてるのよきっと、自分のなみだでおぼれろってね！　そんなのけったいだわ、ぜったい！　それにしても今日はけったいなことばっかり。」

ふとそのときすぐそばあたりで何かがばしゃんと池に落ちる音、水をかいて近くで見きわめようとする。とりあえずセイウチかカバかと思ったものの、今の自分がとっても小さいことを思い出して、たちまちはっとした、ただのハツカネズミが自分と同じようにすべり落ちただけだって。

「このネズミに声をかけて、」とアリスは考えごと。「何かになって？　ここへ落ちてきてからというもの、もうとんでもないことだらけなんだから、どうもあれも話せそうな気がしてよ。とりあえずだめもとでやってみようかしら。」で、やってみた。「そこなネズミよ、ごぞんじ？　この池の出口。このあたりを泳ぎまわってへとへとなの、そこなネズミよ！」（アリスにはネズミにちゃんと正しく呼びかけなきゃいけないという頭があったので、１度もそんなことしたことなかったけど、そういえばお兄さんの古文の学習帳にあってね、『ネズミが――ネズミの――ネズミに――ネズミを――ネズミよ！』って。）そのネズミはどこか問いたげにその子を見つめて、小さなひとみで目くばせしてくれたみたいなんだけど、一言もなくって。

「こっちの言葉がわからないのかも。」とアリスは考えごと。「たぶん外国ネズミなのね、ウィリアムせいふく王についてわたってきた。」（その子の知ってるかぎりでは、何年前に何が起こったのかはうろ覚えだから、こんなことに。）で、またやってみる。「 吾猫兮何在 ？」これは外国語のドリルにある初めの文。ネズミは水からいきなりとび出し、そりゃもうびくびくとふるえだしてね。「あら、ごめんあそばせ！」あわてて声を上げるアリス、このあわれな動物の気をそこねたかと気がかりで。「ネコお好きでないことうっかりしててよ！」

「お好きでねえよ！」とネズミのかん高く気持ちのこもった声。「こっちの身になりゃわかんだろ！」

「ええ、おっしゃる通りね。」とアリスの声は相手をなだめるよう。「そうお 怒 りにならないで。でもうちのネコのダイナに引き合わせられたらなあ、あの子をひと目見たならきっとネコさんのこともお気にめしてよ。かわいくておとなしいんだから。」と続けるアリスはひとりごと半分で、池をゆったりとお泳ぎに。「でね、だんろのそばにすわって、すてきにのどを鳴らして、お手々をぺろぺろ顔をごしごし――だっこするとほんとふわふわなんだから――それにつかまえるのも上手いのよ、ネズミを……あらごめんあそばせ！」とアリスはまた大声、だってそのときにはネズミも毛を全身逆立てていたから、ぜったい 怒 らせたなと思ってね、「おいやなら、このやりとりはもうひかえますけど。」

「やりとりだと？」と声をはるネズミは、しっぽの先までふるえていてね、「こっちが話に乗ったみてえな言いぐさじゃねえか！　うちは代々ずうっとネコが大きれえなんだ、いじわるで下品な 乱暴 ものめ！　もうその名をおれの前で出すんじゃねえ！」

「いたしませんとも！」とアリスはあわてて話の中身を変えようとする。「あなた――あなた、あれはお好き――その――犬は？」ネズミの返事がないので、アリスはこれはいいと続けてね、「お屋敷のそばのかわいい子犬、この子をお引き合わせしたくてよ！　すんだ目のちっちゃなテリアで、ほら、あるのよ！　もう長々とした茶色の巻き毛！　それに物を投げるとひろってくるの、あとちんちんしてごはんをおねだりしたり、もう色々――半分も思い出せなくてよ――そう、かい主は地主さんで、ほらお話でははたらき者で、 金貨 １００まい分のねうちものなの！　それにお話ではみんなやっつけるって、畑のネズミを――ああっ！」と大声をあげたアリス、やっちゃったというふうで。「またお気を悪くされたかしら。」だってもう全力で泳いではなれていくネズミ、進むほどに池はばしゃばしゃと波打つ。

それで後ろからやさしく声をかけたんだ、「ネズミさん！　おもどりになって、犬ネコどっちのお話もしないから、お好きでないなら！」するとそれを聞いたネズミは、くるっと回ってゆるゆる泳ぎもどってくる。顔は真っ青（ 怒 ってるんだなとアリス）、それからかすかに声をふるわせながら、「岸辺へ出んぞ、それからおれの昔話でもしてやっから、あんたもこっちがどうして犬ネコがきらいかわかるってもんだ。」

そろそろいい 頃合 い、だって池はもう落っこちてきた鳥なりケモノなりでぎゅうぎゅうづめになりかけてたからね。そこにはアヒルもドードーも、インコも子ワシも、そのほか色々かわった生き物がいてね、アリスがいちばん前に出て、みんないっしょに岸辺まで泳いでいったんだ。

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1
Chapter 2
Chapter 3
Chapter 4
Chapter 5
Chapter 6
Chapter 7
Chapter 8
Chapter 9
Chapter 10
Chapter 11
Chapter 12

Chapter 3

Click a checkbox to toggle a feature on or off in the text.

Cultural

Incorrect Word Usage

Nonsense Words

Onomatopoeia

Play on Words

Repetition

A Caucus-Race and a Long Tale

They were indeed a queer-looking party that assembled on the bank--the birds with draggled feathers, the animals with their fur clinging close to them, and all dripping wet, cross, and uncomfortable.

The first question of course was, how to get dry again: they had a consultation about this, and after a few minutes it seemed quite natural to Alice to find herself talking familiarly with them, as if she had known them all her life. Indeed, she had quite a long argument with the Lory, who at last turned sulky, and would only say, ‘I am older than you, and must know better’; and this Alice would not allow without knowing how old it was, and, as the Lory positively refused to tell its age, there was no more to be said.

At last the Mouse, who seemed to be a person of authority among them, called out, ‘Sit down, all of you, and listen to me! I’LL soon make you dry enough!’ They all sat down at once, in a large ring, with the Mouse in the middle. Alice kept her eyes anxiously fixed on it, for she felt sure she would catch a bad cold if she did not get dry very soon.

‘Ahem!’ said the Mouse with an important air, ‘are you all ready? This is the driest thing I know. Silence all round, if you please! “William the Conqueror, whose cause was favoured by the pope, was soon submitted to by the English, who wanted leaders, and had been of late much accustomed to usurpation and conquest. Edwin and Morcar, the earls of Mercia and Northumbria--“’

‘Ugh!’ said the Lory, with a shiver.

‘I beg your pardon!’ said the Mouse, frowning, but very politely: ‘Did you speak?’

‘Not I!’ said the Lory hastily.

‘I thought you did,’ said the Mouse. ‘--I proceed. “Edwin and Morcar, the earls of Mercia and Northumbria, declared for him: and even Stigand, the patriotic archbishop of Canterbury, found it advisable--“’

‘Found WHAT?’ said the Duck.

‘Found IT,’ the Mouse replied rather crossly: ‘of course you know what “it” means.’

‘I know what “it” means well enough, when I find a thing,’ said the Duck: ‘it’s generally a frog or a worm. The question is, what did the archbishop find?’

The Mouse did not notice this question, but hurriedly went on, ‘“--found it advisable to go with Edgar Atheling to meet William and offer him the crown. William’s conduct at first was moderate. But the insolence of his Normans--” How are you getting on now, my dear?’ it continued, turning to Alice as it spoke.

‘As wet as ever,’ said Alice in a melancholy tone: ‘it doesn’t seem to dry me at all.’

‘In that case,’ said the Dodo solemnly, rising to its feet, ‘I move that the meeting adjourn, for the immediate adoption of more energetic remedies--’

‘Speak English!’ said the Eaglet. ‘I don’t know the meaning of half those long words, and, what’s more, I don’t believe you do either!’ And the Eaglet bent down its head to hide a smile: some of the other birds tittered audibly.

‘What I was going to say,’ said the Dodo in an offended tone, ‘was, that the best thing to get us dry would be a Caucus-race.’

‘What IS a Caucus-race?’ said Alice; not that she wanted much to know, but the Dodo had paused as if it thought that SOMEBODY ought to speak, and no one else seemed inclined to say anything.

‘Why,’ said the Dodo, ‘the best way to explain it is to do it.’ (And, as you might like to try the thing yourself, some winter day, I will tell you how the Dodo managed it.)

First it marked out a race-course, in a sort of circle, [‘the exact shape doesn’t matter,’ it said,) and then all the party were placed along the course, here and there. There was no ‘One, two, three, and away,’ but they began running when they liked, and left off when they liked, so that it was not easy to know when the race was over. However, when they had been running half an hour or so, and were quite dry again, the Dodo suddenly called out ‘The race is over!’ and they all crowded round it, panting, and asking, ‘But who has won?’

This question the Dodo could not answer without a great deal of thought, and it sat for a long time with one finger pressed upon its forehead (the position in which you usually see Shakespeare, in the pictures of him), while the rest waited in silence. At last the Dodo said, ‘EVERYBODY has won, and all must have prizes.’

‘But who is to give the prizes?’ quite a chorus of voices asked.

‘Why, SHE, of course,’ said the Dodo, pointing to Alice with one finger; and the whole party at once crowded round her, calling out in a confused way, ‘Prizes! Prizes!’

Alice had no idea what to do, and in despair she put her hand in her pocket, and pulled out a box of comfits, (luckily the salt water had not got into it), and handed them round as prizes. There was exactly one a-piece all round.

‘But she must have a prize herself, you know,’ said the Mouse.

‘Of course,’ the Dodo replied very gravely. ‘What else have you got in your pocket?’ he went on, turning to Alice.

‘Only a thimble,’ said Alice sadly.

‘Hand it over here,’ said the Dodo.

Then they all crowded round her once more, while the Dodo solemnly presented the thimble, saying ‘We beg your acceptance of this elegant thimble’; and, when it had finished this short speech, they all cheered.

Alice thought the whole thing very absurd, but they all looked so grave that she did not dare to laugh; and, as she could not think of anything to say, she simply bowed, and took the thimble, looking as solemn as she could.

The next thing was to eat the comfits: this caused some noise and confusion, as the large birds complained that they could not taste theirs, and the small ones choked and had to be patted on the back. However, it was over at last, and they sat down again in a ring, and begged the Mouse to tell them something more.

‘You promised to tell me your history, you know,’ said Alice, ‘and why it is you hate--C and D,’ she added in a whisper, half afraid that it would be offended again.

‘Mine is a long and a sad tale!’ said the Mouse, turning to Alice, and sighing.

‘It IS a long tail, certainly,’ said Alice, looking down with wonder at the Mouse’s tail; ‘but why do you call it sad?’ And she kept on puzzling about it while the Mouse was speaking, so that her idea of the tale was something like this:--

                             'Fury said to a

                             mouse That he

                            met in the

                           house,
                         “Let us

                          both go to

                           law: I will

                            prosecute

                             YOU.--Come,

                                I’ll take no

                               denial; We

                              must have a

                            trial:
                          For really this

                         morning I’ve

                        nothing

                        to do.”
                          Said the

                          mouse to the

                           cur, “Such

                            a trial,

                             dear Sir,
                                With

                              no jury

                            or judge,

                           would be

                          wasting

                          our

                          breath.”
                            “I’ll be

                            judge, I’ll

                             be jury,”

                                 Said

                             cunning

                              old Fury:
                              “I’ll

                              try the

                                whole

                                cause,

                                  and

                               condemn

                               you

                              to

                               death.”'
            

‘You are not attending!’ said the Mouse to Alice severely. ‘What are you thinking of?’

‘I beg your pardon,’ said Alice very humbly: ‘you had got to the fifth bend, I think?’

‘I had NOT !’ cried the Mouse, sharply and very angrily.

‘A knot!’ said Alice, always ready to make herself useful, and looking anxiously about her. ‘Oh, do let me help to undo it!’

‘I shall do nothing of the sort,’ said the Mouse, getting up and walking away. ‘You insult me by talking such nonsense!’

‘I didn’t mean it!’ pleaded poor Alice. ‘But you’re so easily offended, you know!’

The Mouse only growled in reply.

‘Please come back and finish your story!’ Alice called after it; and the others all joined in chorus, ‘Yes, please do!’ but the Mouse only shook its head impatiently, and walked a little quicker.

‘What a pity it wouldn’t stay!’ sighed the Lory, as soon as it was quite out of sight; and an old Crab took the opportunity of saying to her daughter ‘Ah, my dear! Let this be a lesson to you never to lose YOUR temper!’ ‘Hold your tongue, Ma!’ said the young Crab, a little snappishly. ‘You’re enough to try the patience of an oyster!’

‘I wish I had our Dinah here, I know I do!’ said Alice aloud, addressing nobody in particular. ‘She’d soon fetch it back!’

‘And who is Dinah, if I might venture to ask the question?’ said the Lory.

Alice replied eagerly, for she was always ready to talk about her pet: ‘Dinah’s our cat. And she’s such a capital one for catching mice you can’t think! And oh, I wish you could see her after the birds! Why, she’ll eat a little bird as soon as look at it!’

This speech caused a remarkable sensation among the party. Some of the birds hurried off at once: one old Magpie began wrapping itself up very carefully, remarking, ‘I really must be getting home; the night-air doesn’t suit my throat!’ and a Canary called out in a trembling voice to its children, ‘Come away, my dears! It’s high time you were all in bed!’ On various pretexts they all moved off, and Alice was soon left alone.

‘I wish I hadn’t mentioned Dinah!’ she said to herself in a melancholy tone. ‘Nobody seems to like her, down here, and I’m sure she’s the best cat in the world! Oh, my dear Dinah! I wonder if I shall ever see you any more!’ And here poor Alice began to cry again, for she felt very lonely and low-spirited. In a little while, however, she again heard a little pattering of footsteps in the distance, and she looked up eagerly, half hoping that the Mouse had changed his mind, and was coming back to finish his story.

ドードーめぐりで長々しっぽり

なんともけったいな絵づらのご一行がほとりにお集まり――羽を引きずった鳥さんたちに、毛がぴたーとなったむくじゃらたち、みんなずぶぬれで気持ち悪くていやな気分。

さてここで考えるべきは、どうやってぱさぱさにするか。かわかし方を話し合ううち、ものの数分するとけっこうなじんできたというか、気づいたらみんなと仲良くお話ししていて、生まれたときからの知り合いみたくなっていてね。なるほどインコとは長々言い争ったものだから、しまいにはむすっとされたんだけど、ここで「わたしの方がお姉さんなの、だからモノをもっとわかってるに決まってる」なんて言われようものなら、アリスだって相手のお年を知らないからそんなのうなづけないし、インコも自分からぜったいお年を口にしたくないので、どっちもあとはもう言えない。

とうとうハツカネズミが、そこそこひとかどのものみたいだってことで、よびかけてね、「すわれや、みなのしゅう、よおく聞け！　おれがすぐにでもお前らをぱっさぱさってほどにしてやる！」すぐさまみんなは大きく輪になってこしを下ろして、ネズミがどまんなか。アリスは気になるとばかりに目をネズミにじいっと、だっていますぐにでもかわかさないと、ひどい 風邪 を引きそうだと気にやんでいたんだ。

「おほん！」とネズミはもったいつけた感じで、「みなのしゅう、いいか？　こいつは知るかぎりいっとうぱっさぱさのやつよ。どうかごせいちょうを！『ウィリアム 征服王 、その 大義 が 教皇 さまのお目がねにかなったとあって、イングランドの民たみはすぐさまこれにひれふした。上に立つ者もなく、このごろは国が外から荒あらされ平らげられるのが常つねであったからだ。エドウィンとモーカー、つまりマーシアとノーサンブリアの主さまは……』」

「うげ！」とインコは身ぶるい。

「ごめんなすって！」とネズミは顔をしかめながらも、それでいてていねい。「あんた声あげたか？」

「いえいえ！」とあわてるインコ。

「そうかあ？」とネズミ。「まあ続きよ。『エドウィンとモーカー、つまりマーシアとノーサンブリアの主さまも、味方するとした。スティガンド、国うれうカンタベリ大司教までもが 得策 だと見たのが……』」

「何と見たって？」とアヒル。

「だと見た。」とネズミはちょっとむすっと答える。「もちろん『だ』の意味はわかんな。」

「『だ』くらいちゃんとわかっとるわい。モノを見つけりゃあ。」とアヒルは言う。「カエルだ、ミミズだ、ってな。聞きたいのは、大司教が『何』を見たのかだ。」

ネズミは聞かれたことにぴんと来なかったけれども、あわてて続けてね。「『得策だと見たのが、エドガー親王連れてウィリアムに 面会 し 冠 を 差 し出すことで、ウィリアムのふるまいは初めのうちおだやかだった。しかし 下部 のノルマンらしい 傲慢 な 態度 が……』と、今んとこどんなぐあいだ、なあ？」と言いながらアリスの方を向いている。

「まだびしょびしょ。」とアリスはしょんぼり、「ぜんぜんぱさぱさにならなくってよ。」

「ならば、」とドードーが立ち上がり大まじめに、「集まりの休会を提議ていぎする、なぜなれば、より 効果的 な 改善策 の速やかなる 採用 が……」

「国語をしゃべって！」と子ワシ。「そんな長っがーい言葉、半分も意味がわかんないし、どころか君だってさっぱりわかってないじゃない！」ここで子ワシ、うつむいて、にやけた顔をかくしてね。ほかの鳥さんもちらほら聞こえよがしにしのび笑い。

「言おうとしたことはただ、」とドードーは気をそこねてね、「ぱっさぱさにするのなら、いちばんいいのはドードーめぐりということなのだ。」

「なに、ドードーめぐり って。」と言うアリス。すごく知りたいというわけではなく、ドードーがだれか合いの手を入れよとばかりに間を取っていたのにだれひとりとして口をあけようとはしないようだったからね。

「ふむ、」とドードー、「やってみればいちばんよくわかろうて。」（まあ、冬の日なんかにやってみたくなるかもしれないし、ここでドードーが取りしきったことを教えておくね。）

まずは走るコースを作る、形は丸（「きっちりした丸でなくてもいい」とドードー）、それでやる人はコースのあっちこっちでいいからつく。「いちについて、よーい、どん！」っていうのもなくて、みんな好きなときに走り出して、好きなときにやめる。だからいつ終わるのかもわかりづらい。それでも半時間くらい続けると、またかなりぱっさぱさになってきて、そこでいきなりドードーが大声で、「そこまで！」みんなもまわりに集まって、ぜえはあたずねる。「で、だれの勝ち？」

この問いかけには、ドードーもものすごく考えないと答えが出てこなくてね、しばらくすわりこんで、ひたいに指１本当ててね（ほらシェイクスピアが絵のなかでいつもやってるあの 格好 ）、そのあいだのこりのみんなはしずかに待ってる。とうとうドードーが言うんだ、「みんなの勝ちである、全員にほうびをさずけねば。」

「でも、ごほうびをあたえる役はだれが？」と、みんなの口がそろう。

「ふむ、むろん、あの子よ。」とドードーはアリスを指さしてね、するとやってた連中がわーっとまわりにむらがってきて、もう口々にわめくんだ、「ごほうび！　ごほうび！」

アリスはどうしてよいやらさっぱりで、しょうがないからポケットに手をつっこんで、ドライフルーツの箱を取り出してね（うまいこと 塩水 は中に入ってなくて）、ごほうびにまわりへわたしていったんだ。ぐるりのみんなにきっちりひとりひとつずつ。

「でもあの子にもごほうびをやらねえとな。」とネズミ。

「むろん、」とドードーの答えはやっぱり大げさ。「まだ何かそなたのポケットにはあろう？」と続けてアリスを見る。

「指ぬきだけです。」と悲しげなアリス。

「こっちへかしなされ。」とドードー。

で、みんなはふたたびまわりに集まって、そんななかでドードーはぎょうぎょうしく指ぬきをさしだして、こんな言葉。「この見事なる指ぬきをわれらからあなたさまに進ぜよう。」と、この短い 式典 が終わると、その場のみんながぱちぱち わあわあ。

アリスには何から何までむちゃくちゃだと思えたけど、みんなまじめな顔をするもんだから、ふき出すわけにもいかなくて、でも何も言うことが思いつかないから、とりあえずおじぎをして、指ぬきを受け取って、できるだけぎょうぎょうしい顔をする。

続いてお次は、ドライフルーツを食べるだんなんだけど、これがしっちゃかめっちゃかなさわぎになってね、大きな鳥はすぐなくなるとぶつくさ言うし、小さいのはのどにつかえて 背中 をとんとんしなきゃいけないし。それでもなんとか終わって、ふたたび 輪 になって、すわって。ネズミに何かまたお話をとおねだり。

「だん取りでは、ご自分のむかっ話でしたかしら。」とアリス、「その、なぜおきらいなのか――ネ、とイ、が。」 怒 らせまいと、こわごわ小声で言ったので、ところどころ聞こえなくてね。

「おれのは、長々しっぽりよ！」とネズミはアリスの方を向いてため息。

「長々の おしっぽ、ほんっとに。」とアリスはきらきらした目をネズミのしっぽに下ろしてね、「でも、後ろの〈りよ〉って何のこと？」そうしてそのことになやんだまま、ネズミも話していったから、だからお話も頭のなかではこんな感じになっちゃって……

「イカリーわ
　　んわんネズ
　　　　ミにいちゃ
　　　　　　もん、『出る
　　　　　　　　とこ出よう
　　　　　　　　　ぜ、うった
　　　　　　　　　　えてやる――
　　　　　　　　　　さあ、し
　　　　　　　　　のごの言
　　　　　　　うなよ。は
　　　　　　　っきりと
　　　　　おさば
　　　　きよ。
　　　今朝は
　　まあそ
　れだけ
にしとい
てやる。』
　犬ころ
　　に言う
　　　ネズミ、
　　　　『そんな
　　　　　のいやだ
　　　　　　よ、きみ、
　　　　　　　いったい
　　　　　　　　だれがさ
　　　　　　　　　ばくの、
　　　　　　　　　ただの時
　　　　　　　　間のむだ
　　　　　　じゃない。』
　　　　　『さばくの
　　　　はやっぱ
　　　り、おれ
　　だろ。』
　と
うら
かく
　犬
　　ころ。
　　　　『はん
　　　　　けつは
　　　　　　出た
　　　　　　　ぞ、
　　　　　　　　言い
　　　　　　　わた
　　　　　　す、
　　　　お前
　　　　は
　死けい。』」

「耳かっぽじってねえな！」とネズミはアリスにびしっと。「何考えてんだ？」

「ごめんあそばせ。」とおそれいるアリス。「５つめの曲がり角にいらしたところ、よね？」

「わっ からんな ！」と声をあげるネズミは、とげとげぷんすか。

「あ、からんだ？」と言うアリス、いつでも人の役に立ちたいざかりなので、目をかがやかせてきょろきょろしてね、「まあ、でしたらほどかせていただけて？」

「そんなこと何も言わねえよ！」とネズミは立ち上がって、「そんなすっからかんの話でバカにされるなんざ！」

「思いちがいよ！」とアリスは苦しまぎれの言いわけ。「でもあなただってずいぶんいらちだこと。」

ネズミの返事はただうなり声だけ。

「さっさとお話の続きをしめてくださる？」とアリスが 背中 によびかけると、ほかのみんなもあとからそろって、「そうだ、しめるんだ！」ところがネズミはいらいらと頭をふるだけで、足早に歩いてゆく。

「ざんねん、お去りだなんて！」とインコがため息ついたのは、見えなくなってすぐのこと。そしておばさんガニはついでとばかりにむすめに小言。「ほらね！　つまり、あなたもかっかしちゃダメってことなのよ！」

「ママはだまってて！」と子ガニはややつっけんどん。「がまん強いカキだってどうにかなりそうよ！」

「ここにうちのダイナちゃんがいたらな、できるのに！」とアリスの大声は特にだれに向けてというわけでもなく。「あの子ならあいつをたちまち連れもどしてきてよ！」

「そのダイナってどなた？　よろしければ教えてくださらない？」とインコ。

こんな話をしては、一同大さわぎになるわけで――たちまちにげまどう鳥もいたほど、おじさんカササギなんかそうろっと身じたくを始めてこう口に出してね、「そろそろうちに帰らねばな、夜風はのどをいためるので。」それからカナリアは声をふるわせながら子どもたちによびかけてね、「行きましょうさあ！　もうみんなおねんねする時間よ！」いろいろ言いわけを作って去っていくみんな、アリスはたちまちひとりぼっち。

「あたくしとしたことがダイナのことを言い出すなんて！」としょんぼりひとりごと。「だれもお好きでないみたい、こちらでは。ぜったい世界一のネコなのに！　ああ、ダイナちゃん！　またちゃんと会えたりするのかしら！」と、ここでかわいそうで、アリスはまた大泣きのはじまり、だって心がとってもせつなくて、しょげていたからね。ところが少しすると、また耳に、かすかにぱたぱたという足音が遠くから聞こえてきたから、はっとして目を上げてね、どこかで思ってたんだ、ネズミが気を 変 えて、お話をしにもどってくるんじゃないかって。

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1
Chapter 2
Chapter 3
Chapter 4
Chapter 5
Chapter 6
Chapter 7
Chapter 8
Chapter 9
Chapter 10
Chapter 11
Chapter 12

Chapter 4

Click a checkbox to toggle a feature on or off in the text.

Cultural

Incorrect Word Usage

Nonsense Words

Onomatopoeia

Play on Words

Repetition

The Rabbit Sends in a Little Bill

It was the White Rabbit, trotting slowly back again, and looking anxiously about as it went, as if it had lost something; and she heard it muttering to itself ‘The Duchess! The Duchess! Oh my dear paws! Oh my fur and whiskers! She’ll get me executed, as sure as ferrets are ferrets! Where CAN I have dropped them, I wonder?’ Alice guessed in a moment that it was looking for the fan and the pair of white kid gloves, and she very good-naturedly began hunting about for them, but they were nowhere to be seen--everything seemed to have changed since her swim in the pool, and the great hall, with the glass table and the little door, had vanished completely.

Very soon the Rabbit noticed Alice, as she went hunting about, and called out to her in an angry tone, ‘Why, Mary Ann, what ARE you doing out here? Run home this moment, and fetch me a pair of gloves and a fan! Quick, now!’ And Alice was so much frightened that she ran off at once in the direction it pointed to, without trying to explain the mistake it had made.

‘He took me for his housemaid,’ she said to herself as she ran. ‘How surprised he’ll be when he finds out who I am! But I’d better take him his fan and gloves--that is, if I can find them.’ As she said this, she came upon a neat little house, on the door of which was a bright brass plate with the name ‘W. RABBIT’ engraved upon it. She went in without knocking, and hurried upstairs, in great fear lest she should meet the real Mary Ann, and be turned out of the house before she had found the fan and gloves.

‘How queer it seems,’ Alice said to herself, ‘to be going messages for a rabbit! I suppose Dinah’ll be sending me on messages next!’ And she began fancying the sort of thing that would happen: ‘“Miss Alice! Come here directly, and get ready for your walk!” “Coming in a minute, nurse! But I’ve got to see that the mouse doesn’t get out.” Only I don’t think,’ Alice went on, ‘that they’d let Dinah stop in the house if it began ordering people about like that!’

By this time she had found her way into a tidy little room with a table in the window, and on it (as she had hoped) a fan and two or three pairs of tiny white kid gloves: she took up the fan and a pair of the gloves, and was just going to leave the room, when her eye fell upon a little bottle that stood near the looking-glass. There was no label this time with the words ‘DRINK ME,’ but nevertheless she uncorked it and put it to her lips. ‘I know SOMETHING interesting is sure to happen,’ she said to herself, ‘whenever I eat or drink anything; so I’ll just see what this bottle does. I do hope it’ll make me grow large again, for really I’m quite tired of being such a tiny little thing!’

It did so indeed, and much sooner than she had expected: before she had drunk half the bottle, she found her head pressing against the ceiling, and had to stoop to save her neck from being broken. She hastily put down the bottle, saying to herself ‘That’s quite enough--I hope I shan’t grow any more--As it is, I can’t get out at the door--I do wish I hadn’t drunk quite so much!’

Alas! it was too late to wish that! She went on growing, and growing, and very soon had to kneel down on the floor: in another minute there was not even room for this, and she tried the effect of lying down with one elbow against the door, and the other arm curled round her head. Still she went on growing, and, as a last resource, she put one arm out of the window, and one foot up the chimney, and said to herself ‘Now I can do no more, whatever happens. What WILL become of me?’

Luckily for Alice, the little magic bottle had now had its full effect, and she grew no larger: still it was very uncomfortable, and, as there seemed to be no sort of chance of her ever getting out of the room again, no wonder she felt unhappy.

‘It was much pleasanter at home,’ thought poor Alice, ‘when one wasn’t always growing larger and smaller, and being ordered about by mice and rabbits. I almost wish I hadn’t gone down that rabbit-hole--and yet--and yet--it’s rather curious, you know, this sort of life! I do wonder what CAN have happened to me! When I used to read fairy-tales, I fancied that kind of thing never happened, and now here I am in the middle of one! There ought to be a book written about me, that there ought! And when I grow up, I’ll write one--but I’m grown up now,’ she added in a sorrowful tone; ‘at least there’s no room to grow up any more HERE.’

‘But then,’ thought Alice, ‘shall I NEVER get any older than I am now? That’ll be a comfort, one way--never to be an old woman--but then--always to have lessons to learn! Oh, I shouldn’t like THAT!’

‘Oh, you foolish Alice!’ she answered herself. ‘How can you learn lessons in here? Why, there’s hardly room for YOU, and no room at all for any lesson-books!’

And so she went on, taking first one side and then the other, and making quite a conversation of it altogether; but after a few minutes she heard a voice outside, and stopped to listen.

‘Mary Ann! Mary Ann!’ said the voice. ‘Fetch me my gloves this moment!’ Then came a little pattering of feet on the stairs. Alice knew it was the Rabbit coming to look for her, and she trembled till she shook the house, quite forgetting that she was now about a thousand times as large as the Rabbit, and had no reason to be afraid of it.

Presently the Rabbit came up to the door, and tried to open it; but, as the door opened inwards, and Alice’s elbow was pressed hard against it, that attempt proved a failure. Alice heard it say to itself ‘Then I’ll go round and get in at the window.’

‘THAT you won’t’ thought Alice, and, after waiting till she fancied she heard the Rabbit just under the window, she suddenly spread out her hand, and made a snatch in the air. She did not get hold of anything, but she heard a little shriek and a fall, and a crash of broken glass, from which she concluded that it was just possible it had fallen into a cucumber-frame, or something of the sort.

Next came an angry voice--the Rabbit’s--‘Pat! Pat! Where are you?’ And then a voice she had never heard before, ‘Sure then I’m here! Digging for apples, yer honour!’

‘Digging for apples, indeed!’ said the Rabbit angrily. ‘Here! Come and help me out of THIS!’ (Sounds of more broken glass.)

‘Now tell me, Pat, what’s that in the window?’

‘Sure, it’s an arm, yer honour!’ (He pronounced it ‘arrum.’)

‘An arm, you goose! Who ever saw one that size? Why, it fills the whole window!’

‘Sure, it does, yer honour: but it’s an arm for all that.’

‘Well, it’s got no business there, at any rate: go and take it away!’

There was a long silence after this, and Alice could only hear whispers now and then; such as, ‘Sure, I don’t like it, yer honour, at all, at all!’ ‘Do as I tell you, you coward!’ and at last she spread out her hand again, and made another snatch in the air. This time there were TWO little shrieks, and more sounds of broken glass. ‘What a number of cucumber-frames there must be!’ thought Alice. ‘I wonder what they’ll do next! As for pulling me out of the window, I only wish they COULD! I’m sure I don’t want to stay in here any longer!’

She waited for some time without hearing anything more: at last came a rumbling of little cartwheels, and the sound of a good many voices all talking together: she made out the words: ‘Where’s the other ladder?--Why, I hadn’t to bring but one; Bill’s got the other--Bill! fetch it here, lad!--Here, put ‘em up at this corner--No, tie ‘em together first--they don’t reach half high enough yet--Oh! they’ll do well enough; don’t be particular--Here, Bill! catch hold of this rope--Will the roof bear?--Mind that loose slate--Oh, it’s coming down! Heads below!’ (a loud crash)--‘Now, who did that?--It was Bill, I fancy--Who’s to go down the chimney?--Nay, I shan’t! YOU do it!--That I won’t, then!--Bill’s to go down--Here, Bill! the master says you’re to go down the chimney!’

‘Oh! So Bill’s got to come down the chimney, has he?’ said Alice to herself. ‘Shy, they seem to put everything upon Bill! I wouldn’t be in Bill’s place for a good deal: this fireplace is narrow, to be sure; but I THINK I can kick a little!’

She drew her foot as far down the chimney as she could, and waited till she heard a little animal (she couldn’t guess of what sort it was) scratching and scrambling about in the chimney close above her: then, saying to herself ‘This is Bill,’ she gave one sharp kick, and waited to see what would happen next.

The first thing she heard was a general chorus of ‘There goes Bill!’ then the Rabbit’s voice along--‘Catch him, you by the hedge!’ then silence, and then another confusion of voices--‘Hold up his head--Brandy now--Don’t choke him--How was it, old fellow? What happened to you? Tell us all about it!’

Last came a little feeble, squeaking voice, [‘That’s Bill,’ thought Alice,) ‘Well, I hardly know--No more, thank ye; I’m better now--but I’m a deal too flustered to tell you--all I know is, something comes at me like a Jack-in-the-box, and up I goes like a sky-rocket!’

‘So you did, old fellow!’ said the others.

‘We must burn the house down!’ said the Rabbit’s voice; and Alice called out as loud as she could, ‘If you do. I’ll set Dinah at you!’

There was a dead silence instantly, and Alice thought to herself, ‘I wonder what they WILL do next! If they had any sense, they’d take the roof off.’ After a minute or two, they began moving about again, and Alice heard the Rabbit say, ‘A barrowful will do, to begin with.’

‘A barrowful of WHAT?’ thought Alice; but she had not long to doubt, for the next moment a shower of little pebbles came rattling in at the window, and some of them hit her in the face. ‘I’ll put a stop to this,’ she said to herself, and shouted out, ‘You’d better not do that again!’ which produced another dead silence.

Alice noticed with some surprise that the pebbles were all turning into little cakes as they lay on the floor, and a bright idea came into her head. ‘If I eat one of these cakes,’ she thought, ‘it’s sure to make SOME change in my size; and as it can’t possibly make me larger, it must make me smaller, I suppose.’

So she swallowed one of the cakes, and was delighted to find that she began shrinking directly. As soon as she was small enough to get through the door, she ran out of the house, and found quite a crowd of little animals and birds waiting outside. The poor little Lizard, Bill, was in the middle, being held up by two guinea-pigs, who were giving it something out of a bottle. They all made a rush at Alice the moment she appeared; but she ran off as hard as she could, and soon found herself safe in a thick wood.

‘The first thing I’ve got to do,’ said Alice to herself, as she wandered about in the wood, ‘is to grow to my right size again; and the second thing is to find my way into that lovely garden. I think that will be the best plan.’

It sounded an excellent plan, no doubt, and very neatly and simply arranged; the only difficulty was, that she had not the smallest idea how to set about it; and while she was peering about anxiously among the trees, a little sharp bark just over her head made her look up in a great hurry.

An enormous puppy was looking down at her with large round eyes, and feebly stretching out one paw, trying to touch her. ‘Poor little thing!’ said Alice, in a coaxing tone, and she tried hard to whistle to it; but she was terribly frightened all the time at the thought that it might be hungry, in which case it would be very likely to eat her up in spite of all her coaxing.

Hardly knowing what she did, she picked up a little bit of stick, and held it out to the puppy; whereupon the puppy jumped into the air off all its feet at once, with a yelp of delight, and rushed at the stick, and made believe to worry it; then Alice dodged behind a great thistle, to keep herself from being run over; and the moment she appeared on the other side, the puppy made another rush at the stick, and tumbled head over heels in its hurry to get hold of it; then Alice, thinking it was very like having a game of play with a cart-horse, and expecting every moment to be trampled under its feet, ran round the thistle again; then the puppy began a series of short charges at the stick, running a very little way forwards each time and a long way back, and barking hoarsely all the while, till at last it sat down a good way off, panting, with its tongue hanging out of its mouth, and its great eyes half shut.

This seemed to Alice a good opportunity for making her escape; so she set off at once, and ran till she was quite tired and out of breath, and till the puppy’s bark sounded quite faint in the distance.

‘And yet what a dear little puppy it was!’ said Alice, as she leant against a buttercup to rest herself, and fanned herself with one of the leaves: ‘I should have liked teaching it tricks very much, if--if I’d only been the right size to do it! Oh dear! I’d nearly forgotten that I’ve got to grow up again! Let me see--how IS it to be managed? I suppose I ought to eat or drink something or other; but the great question is, what?’

The great question certainly was, what? Alice looked all round her at the flowers and the blades of grass, but she did not see anything that looked like the right thing to eat or drink under the circumstances. There was a large mushroom growing near her, about the same height as herself; and when she had looked under it, and on both sides of it, and behind it, it occurred to her that she might as well look and see what was on the top of it.

She stretched herself up on tiptoe, and peeped over the edge of the mushroom, and her eyes immediately met those of a large caterpillar, that was sitting on the top with its arms folded, quietly smoking a long hookah, and taking not the smallest notice of her or of anything else.

ウサギ、ビルくんをさしむける

なんと白ウサギがとろとろと引き返してきたわけで、歩きながらあたりをきょろきょろ、なくしものでもしたみたいで。そのひとりごとが聞こえてくる。「 御前 さま！　御前さま！　おお、ぴょんぴょん！　ああ、ぴょんぬるかな！　このままではあの方から 処 されてしまう、白イタチが白イタチのようにまさしく！　どこで落としたものか、はてさて。」アリスははたと気づいてね、あのせんすと白ヤギの手ぶくろをさがしてるんだって、だから親切のつもりであたりをさがそうとしたんだけど、もうどこにも見当たらなくって――すっかり様子が変わったみたいで、池で泳いでからこっち、ガラスのテーブルも小さなドアも大広間ごとまったく消えてしまっていて。

はやまもなくウサギに気づかれたアリスは、ちょうどあたりをさがしてうろうろしてたんだけど、もう頭ごなしに 怒 られてね、「おいメリアン！　こんなところで何をしておじゃる！　とっとと家へ一走りして、手ぶくろとせんすを持っておじゃれ！　早よう、ほれ！」するとおびえきったアリスは指さす方へすぐさまかけ足、人ちがいだと言おうにも言えずじまい。

「あたくしをメイドとかんちがいするなんて。」と走りながらひとりごと。「あたくしがだれだかわかったら、おどろいてよ！　でも今はせんすと手ぶくろを取ってきた方がよさそう――まあ、あったらの話ですけど。」と言ってるうちに目の前にこじんまりしたおうち、ドアのところにはつるつるした金ぞくの 表札 、お名前には〈シロー・ウサギ〉とほられていまして。とんとんともせずに立ち入るなり、 階段 をかけのぼった、だって本物のメリアンと出くわすとまずいことになるからね、せんすと手ぶくろ見つける前に家から追い出されちゃうし。

「なんてけったいなのかしら、」とアリスはひとりごと、「ウサギのお使いだなんて！　今度はダイナがあたくしをお使いにやるんじゃなくって？」すると、こうなるのかなって、あれやこれや思いうかんできてね、「『アリスおじょうさま、ただちにこちらへ、おさんぽのごしたくを！』『今行くから、ばあや！　でもこのネズミ穴を見はらないと、ダイナがもどってくるまで、あとネズミがにげでてこないか見ておかないと。』でもたぶん、」とアリスは続ける、「もうダイナはうちに置いとけなくなってよ、そんなことをあの子が人間に言いつけだしたら！」

このときまでになんとか入れたお部屋はこぎれいなところで、まどぎわにテーブルがひとつあり、その上には（思った通り）せんすとちっちゃい白ヤギの手ぶくろが何組か置いてあった。せんすと手ぶくろ１組を取り上げて出て行こうとしたとき、目に飛びこんできたのが、鏡わきに立てられた小びん。今度は〈ノンデ〉の 札 もなかったのに、さらさら気にせずせんをぬいて口につけてね。「きっとなにか面白いことが起きるにきまっててよ。」とひとりごと。「なにか食べたり飲んだりするといつもそう、だからこのびんだってきっと。今度はまた大きくなってくれるといいな、だってもうこんなにちーっちゃくなるのなんてほんとにうんざり！」

してこれその通りに、しかも思ってたよりも 早々 、びん半分ものまないうちに、気づけば頭が天井におさえつけられるので、首が折れないようにと身をかがめるはめに。あわててびんを下に置きながらひとりごと。「もうけっこうよ――もう大きくならなくていいから――このままじゃドアを出られない――あんなにたっぷり飲むんじゃなかった！」

なんたること！　そうは思ってももはや手おくれ！　ぐんぐん大きくなっていって、たちまちゆかにひざをつくほかなくなり、またたくまにそうするよゆうもなくなって、なんとか横になろうとしてね、ひじをドアにぶつけたり、反対のうでを頭まわりでまるめたり。まだまだ大きくなるから、最後の手として、うでの片方をまどの外へ出して、片足をえんとつのなかにつっこんで、そこでひとりごと。「もうこれでせいいっぱい、どうやっても。これからあたくしどうなるの？」

アリスにさいわい、まほうの小びんのききめはここで打ち止め、もう大きくはならない。とはいえやっぱりいごこち悪く、それにどうにも自分はこのお部屋の外に出られる見こみもなさそうで、気がふさぐのもむりはなく。

「おうちにいた方がまだいい。」とは、ふびんなアリスの想い。「ずっとのびちぢみしてばっかりとか、ネズミ・ウサギに頭ごなしってこともなくって。あのウサギ穴に入らなきゃよかった、って思う――けど――けれど――どこかへんてこ、ほら、こんな世界って。ふしぎなの、どんなことが起こってくれるのって！　いつもおとぎ話を読んでると、そんなのぜったい起こりっこないってきめつけるのに、いま、ここで、あたくしはそのまっただなか！　なら、あたくしについて書かれた本があってもよくてよ、じゃなくて？　大きくなったら書くんだから――まあ、今だって大きいけれど、」と、いじらしい口ぶりで続けてね、「といっても、ぎゅうぎゅうでここではもう大きくなれなくてよ。」

「だとすると、」とアリスは思う。「今よりもう年は取らないってこと？　ほっとしなくはないわ――おばあちゃんにならなくていいし――でもそうなると――いつまでもお勉強の山！　えっ、そんなのぜったいいや！」

「もう、アリスのバカ！」とひとりふた役。「ここでお勉強なんて、できっこないんだから！　ね、あなただけで ぎゅうぎゅうだから、ぜんぜん入らなくってよ、教科書なんか！」

というわけでそのまま、まずひとりめの役、それからもうひとり、というように、かけ合いをぜんぶひとりでやってたんだけど、何分かすると外から声がして、やめて耳をそばだてる。

「メリアン！　メリアン！」とその声。「とっとと手ぶくろを持っておじゃれ！」そのあと、 階段 からたたたたとかすかな足音。アリスはウサギがさがしに来たとかんづいて、ふるえだしたらなんと家までぐらぐら、すっかりどわすれ、自分が今ウサギの何千倍も大きいなんてことはね、だったらこわがらなくていいわけで。

そくざにウサギはドアまで来て、開けようとしたのに、内側に 開 くドアだから、アリスのひじがぐっとつっかえになって、やってみてもできずじまい。アリスの耳にひとりごとが、「ならば回りこんで、まどから入るでおじゃる。」

「そんなのむーりー！」と思うアリス、待ちかまえて、まどのま下にウサギの気配がしたところで、いきなり手をのばして、そのままつかむそぶり。何もつかまえられなかったけど、聞こえてくる小さなさけび声と、ずっこけてガラスをわった音。というわけで頭のなかでは、キュウリのなえ箱かそんな感じのものにつっこんだのかも、てなことに。

お次に来るのはぷりぷり声――ウサギのね――「パット！　パット！　どこにおじゃる！」それから今度は聞いたことのない声。「ここにおりますだ！　土リンゴほり中で、おやかたさま！」

「土リンゴほり、ほおお！」とぷんすかウサギ。「こちへおじゃれ、ここから出すでおじゃる！」（さらにガラスのわれた音。）

「さあ教えるでおじゃる、あのまどのものは何ぞえ？」

「きっとうんでだで、おやかたさま！」（正しくは、うで、ね。）

「うで！　あほうが！　あんな大きさのがおじゃるか！　ほれ、まどわくいっぱいぞ？」

「そうでごぜえますが、おやかたさま。やっぱどう見てもうんでだで。」

「なぬ、そんなの知ったことかえ、とにかくあれめを片づけておじゃれ！」

そのあと長々と静かで、アリスにもときどきささやき声が聞こえたくらい、それも「ぜってえいやですだ、おやかたさま、めっそうもねえ！」「言うた通りにおじゃれ、へたれめ！」といったもので、とうとうもう１度手をのばしてまたつかむそぶりをするはめに。今度はふたつの小さな 悲鳴 、それとまたしてもわれたガラスの音。「いっぱいたくさんキュウリのなえ箱があるのね！」とアリスは思う、「お次はどう出るかしら！　まどの外へ引き出すっていうなら、願ってもないことだけど！　ほんっともうここにじっとしてられなくってよ！」

しばらくじっとしているあいだ、何も聞こえなかったのだけど、ついに耳に入るごろごろ手おし車の音、たくさんの話し合うざわめき、わかった言葉は、「もうひとつハシゴがおじゃったな――なんぞ、持ってくんのひとつだけでよかったんか。ビルがもひとつ持ってて――ビル！　こっち持ってこい、おい！――ここ、この角に立てかけ――ちがう、まずふたつつなげねえと――その高さだと、まだとどかな――おお！　これでちょうどいい、やかまし言うな――ここだ、ビル！　このロープをつかめ――やねはだいじょうぶか？――気をつけろ、あのかわら、ずれて――あ、落ちてくる！　下の、気をつけい！」（ずどーん）――「さて、だれがあれやる？――ビルじゃねえか――だれがえんとつおりるでおじゃ――やめろ、おらあいやだ！　てめえ行けよ！――んな、おらだってそんなの！　行くべきはビルでおじゃる――おい、ビル！　おやかたさまがおおせだ、お前さんえんとつを下りてけって！」

「まあ！　ならビルがえんとつを下りなくちゃいけないってこと？」とアリスはひとりごと。「ふぅん、ぜんぶビルにおしつけたみたいね！　あたくしも、たくさんもらったってビルの代わりはおことわり。そこのだんろはたしかにせまいけど、たぶんちょっとけり上げるくらいは！」

できるだけだんろの底の方まで足を引いて、小動物の気配がするまで待ちぶせ、（相手の正体もよくわからないままに）がりっそろそろと、えんとつのなか間近あたりまで、とそのとき、「こいつがビルね」とひとりごとついでにしゅっとけり上げて、じっとして次に起こることをさぐる。

まず初めに聞こえたのが「ありゃビルだ」の大がっしょう、それからひとりウサギの声――「受け止めるでおじゃる、生けがきのそばぞ！」しーんとしたあと、また今度はざわざわあわてふためく――「あごを上だ――ブランデーを――つまらせるなよ――どういうことだ、おめえさん。何があった？　 子細 を教えてくれ。」

ついには、弱々しげなきぃきぃ声、（「こいつがビルね」とはアリスの考え）「んあ、よくわかんねえ――もうええ、あんがと。もうようなった――でも頭がこんがらがって何つったら――わかんのは、何かがこっちに来た、びっくり箱みてえに、んで、ぴょーんとロケット花火みてえに空へ。」

「たしかにそんなんだった、おめえさん！」と一同。

「この家を焼きはらわんとな！」とはウサギの声、そこでアリスはあらんばかりの大声でさけぶ、「やってみなさい、あなたたちにダイナをけしかけてよ！」

たちまち死んだようにしーんとなって、ひとり考えこむアリス、「次はどう出るつもりなのかしら！　まともに考えれば、屋根を外すとかだけど。」ものの数分もするとまたわたわたしだして、アリスの耳にもウサギの声が、「手おし車１台分でおじゃるな、まずは。」

「１台分の、何？」と思うアリス。でもそのなやみもすぐに晴れて、とたんに小石がたくさんぱらぱらと窓から入ってきて、いくつか顔に当たったり。「せき止めてやってよ、」とひとりごとのあと、大声でさけぶ、「またやったらしょうちしないんだから！」そうするとまたまたしーんとしずか。

アリスがはっとしてちょっとびっくり、なんとその小石、みんなゆかに落ちると小ぶりのケーキに変わってね、そこでぴんとひらめいた。「このケーキをひとつ食べたら、」と考えるアリス、「きっとあたくしの大きさも何かしら変わるはず。まあたぶん大きくはならないから、小さくなるってだんどり、かしらね。」

そこでケーキをひとつ丸飲みすると、気づけばうれしいことにいきなりちぢんでいく。ドアを通りぬけられるくらいに小さくなると、とたんにそのおうちからかけ出てね、すると見つかるのは外で立ちつくす小動物や小鳥たちのむれ。かわいそうにトカゲのビルくんはまんなかにいて、２ひきのモルモットにかかえられてて、びんから何か飲ませてもらっていたり。みんなして、アリスが出てきたのを見るなりおそいかかってきたんだけど、こっちもひっしで走ってね、たちまち気づくとぶじ深い森のなかにいて。

「第１にやるべきことは、」とアリスは森をうろうろしながらひとりごと。「また元の背たけになること、それから第２は、あのすてきなお庭へ出る道を見つけること。どうもそうしてみるのがいちばんよさそう。」

たしかに、してみるにうってつけで、すっきりわかりやすい思いつきに聞こえる。だけど、ただひとつこまったことに、とっかかりがさっぱりわからなくってね。そうして、あたりの木々のあいだをそわそわとのぞきこんでいると、ワンとほえる声が頭の上からして、それはもうびくっと顔を起こしたんだ。

１ぴきの図体のでかいワンコが、くりくり大きなお目々でこっちを見ていてね、ぷるぷると前足をのばしてさわろうとしてくる。「よしよし！」とアリスはあやす言葉のあと、口ぶえを強くふこうとしたんだけど、相手がはらぺこなのかなと気づいたらぶるぶるがとまらなくなっちゃってね、そうなってくると、いくらなだめてもやっぱりぺろり食べられちゃうわけで。

もう思わずとっさに木切れをひろい上げてワンコにつきだしてみた。するとワンコはたちまちおどりあがって、きゃんきゃんはしゃぐ、そして木切れにとびかかって、どうもじゃれたいみたいでね、そこでアリスもふみつぶされないよう、でっかいアザミのかげにひらりとよける、そして反対側から出ると、すぐさまワンコが木切れめがけてまたつっこんできたんだけど、でもつかまえようとあせるあまりすってんころりん、これはもう、考えてみれば馬車馬とふざけ合ってるみたいなものだから、アリスも足でふみつけられそうなときには、そのたびごと、はっとしてかけ足でアザミに回りこむ、だからワンコにしても小きざみに木切れへしかけるようになってね、じわじわ前につめるかと思いきや大きく後ろ、しじゅうぐるるるとほえっぱなしだったんだけど、はてにはとうとうはなれたところでへたりこんで、はあはあと口から舌を出して大きなお目々も半びらき。

これにアリスも、にげるのは今しかないとふんで、そこですぐさま動いてかけ足、そのうちこっちもへとへとで息切れ、やがてワンコのほえる声も遠くかすかになっていってね。

「まあでも、あんなワンコ、かわいらしいものね！」とアリスはひと息つこうとキンポウゲにもたれかかり、その葉っぱであおぎながら、「芸をしこんでみるのもけっこう面白そう、その――元の背たけになったらの話だけど！　んもう！　もう少しで元通りになるのをわすれるところよ！　う～んと――どうやればうまくいくのかしら。たぶん何かしら食べるか飲むかすればいいんだろうけど、いったいぜんたい、何を？」

その通り、いったいぜんたい、何を？　アリスがあたりをながめまわしても、草花あれど、都合よく飲み食いできそうなものはその場に何も見当たらない。ところがそばにひょっこり大きなキノコ、背たけと同じくらい。で、見上げたり、両わき、後ろに回ってみたりするうち、ふと思いつく。かさの上に何があるのか、目を向けてたしかめてみようかなって。

つまさき立ちで背のびして、キノコのへりからのぞきこむと、目にとびこんできたのが、こっちを向いた大きな青虫、てっぺんにすわりこんでうでを組み、ひそやかに水ぎせるをふかして、こちらにも何にも気にとめるそぶりがちっともない。

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1 | Chapter 2 | Chapter 3 | Chapter 4 | Chapter 5 | Chapter 6 | Chapter 7 | Chapter 8 | Chapter 9 | Chapter 10 | Chapter 11 | Chapter 12

Chapter 5

Advice from a Caterpillar

The Caterpillar and Alice looked at each other for some time in silence: at last the Caterpillar took the hookah out of its mouth, and addressed her in a languid, sleepy voice.

‘Who are YOU?’ said the Caterpillar.

This was not an encouraging opening for a conversation. Alice replied, rather shyly, ‘I--I hardly know, sir, just at present--at least I know who I WAS when I got up this morning, but I think I must have been changed several times since then.’

‘What do you mean by that?’ said the Caterpillar sternly. ‘Explain yourself!’

‘I can’t explain MYSELF, I’m afraid, sir’ said Alice, ‘because I’m not myself, you see.’

‘I don’t see,’ said the Caterpillar.

‘I’m afraid I can’t put it more clearly,’ Alice replied very politely, ‘for I can’t understand it myself to begin with; and being so many different sizes in a day is very confusing.’

‘It isn’t,’ said the Caterpillar.

‘Well, perhaps you haven’t found it so yet,’ said Alice; ‘but when you have to turn into a chrysalis--you will some day, you know--and then after that into a butterfly, I should think you’ll feel it a little queer, won’t you?’

‘Not a bit,’ said the Caterpillar.

‘Well, perhaps your feelings may be different,’ said Alice; ‘all I know is, it would feel very queer to ME.’

‘You!’ said the Caterpillar contemptuously. ‘Who are YOU?’

Which brought them back again to the beginning of the conversation. Alice felt a little irritated at the Caterpillar’s making such VERY short remarks, and she drew herself up and said, very gravely, ‘I think, you ought to tell me who YOU are, first.’

‘Why?’ said the Caterpillar.

Here was another puzzling question; and as Alice could not think of any good reason, and as the Caterpillar seemed to be in a VERY unpleasant state of mind, she turned away.

‘Come back!’ the Caterpillar called after her. ‘I’ve something important to say!’

This sounded promising, certainly: Alice turned and came back again.

‘Keep your temper,’ said the Caterpillar.

‘Is that all?’ said Alice, swallowing down her anger as well as she could.

‘No,’ said the Caterpillar.

Alice thought she might as well wait, as she had nothing else to do, and perhaps after all it might tell her something worth hearing. For some minutes it puffed away without speaking, but at last it unfolded its arms, took the hookah out of its mouth again, and said, ‘So you think you’re changed, do you?’

‘I’m afraid I am, sir,’ said Alice; ‘I can’t remember things as I used--and I don’t keep the same size for ten minutes together!’

‘Can’t remember WHAT things?’ said the Caterpillar.

‘Well, I’ve tried to say HOW DOTH THE LITTLE BUSY BEE , but it all came different!’ Alice replied in a very melancholy voice.

‘Repeat, YOU ARE OLD, FATHER WILLIAM ,’ said the Caterpillar.

Alice folded her hands, and began:--

‘You are old, Father William,’ the young man said,
‘And your hair has become very white;
And yet you incessantly stand on your head--
Do you think, at your age, it is right?’

‘In my youth,’ Father William replied to his son,
‘I feared it might injure the brain;
But, now that I’m perfectly sure I have none,
Why, I do it again and again.’

‘You are old,’ said the youth, ‘as I mentioned before,
And have grown most uncommonly fat;
Yet you turned a back-somersault in at the door--
Pray, what is the reason of that?’

‘In my youth,’ said the sage, as he shook his grey locks,
‘I kept all my limbs very supple
By the use of this ointment--one shilling the box--
Allow me to sell you a couple?’

‘You are old,’ said the youth, ‘and your jaws are too weak
For anything tougher than suet;
Yet you finished the goose, with the bones and the beak--
Pray how did you manage to do it?’

‘In my youth,’ said his father, ‘I took to the law,
And argued each case with my wife;
And the muscular strength, which it gave to my jaw,
Has lasted the rest of my life.’

‘You are old,’ said the youth, ‘one would hardly suppose
That your eye was as steady as ever;
Yet you balanced an eel on the end of your nose--
What made you so awfully clever?’

‘I have answered three questions, and that is enough,’
Said his father; ‘don’t give yourself airs!
Do you think I can listen all day to such stuff?
Be off, or I’ll kick you down stairs!’

‘That is not said right,’ said the Caterpillar.

‘Not QUITE right, I’m afraid,’ said Alice, timidly; ‘some of the words have got altered.’

‘It is wrong from beginning to end,’ said the Caterpillar decidedly, and there was silence for some minutes.

The Caterpillar was the first to speak.

‘What size do you want to be?’ it asked.

‘Oh, I’m not particular as to size,’ Alice hastily replied; ‘only one doesn’t like changing so often, you know.’

‘I DON’T know,’ said the Caterpillar.

Alice said nothing: she had never been so much contradicted in her life before, and she felt that she was losing her temper.

‘Are you content now?’ said the Caterpillar.

‘Well, I should like to be a LITTLE larger, sir, if you wouldn’t mind,’ said Alice: ‘three inches is such a wretched height to be.’

‘It is a very good height indeed!’ said the Caterpillar angrily, rearing itself upright as it spoke (it was exactly three inches high).

‘But I’m not used to it!’ pleaded poor Alice in a piteous tone. And she thought of herself, ‘I wish the creatures wouldn’t be so easily offended!’

‘You’ll get used to it in time,’ said the Caterpillar; and it put the hookah into its mouth and began smoking again.

This time Alice waited patiently until it chose to speak again. In a minute or two the Caterpillar took the hookah out of its mouth and yawned once or twice, and shook itself. Then it got down off the mushroom, and crawled away in the grass, merely remarking as it went, ‘One side will make you grow taller, and the other side will make you grow shorter.’

‘One side of WHAT? The other side of WHAT?’ thought Alice to herself.

‘Of the mushroom,’ said the Caterpillar, just as if she had asked it aloud; and in another moment it was out of sight.

Alice remained looking thoughtfully at the mushroom for a minute, trying to make out which were the two sides of it; and as it was perfectly round, she found this a very difficult question. However, at last she stretched her arms round it as far as they would go, and broke off a bit of the edge with each hand.

‘And now which is which?’ she said to herself, and nibbled a little of the right-hand bit to try the effect: the next moment she felt a violent blow underneath her chin: it had struck her foot!

She was a good deal frightened by this very sudden change, but she felt that there was no time to be lost, as she was shrinking rapidly; so she set to work at once to eat some of the other bit. Her chin was pressed so closely against her foot, that there was hardly room to open her mouth; but she did it at last, and managed to swallow a morsel of the lefthand bit.

* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * *

‘Come, my head’s free at last!’ said Alice in a tone of delight, which changed into alarm in another moment, when she found that her shoulders were nowhere to be found: all she could see, when she looked down, was an immense length of neck, which seemed to rise like a stalk out of a sea of green leaves that lay far below her.

‘What CAN all that green stuff be?’ said Alice. ‘And where HAVE my shoulders got to? And oh, my poor hands, how is it I can’t see you?’ She was moving them about as she spoke, but no result seemed to follow, except a little shaking among the distant green leaves.

As there seemed to be no chance of getting her hands up to her head, she tried to get her head down to them, and was delighted to find that her neck would bend about easily in any direction, like a serpent. She had just succeeded in curving it down into a graceful zigzag, and was going to dive in among the leaves, which she found to be nothing but the tops of the trees under which she had been wandering, when a sharp hiss made her draw back in a hurry: a large pigeon had flown into her face, and was beating her violently with its wings.

‘Serpent!’ screamed the Pigeon.

‘I’m NOT a serpent!’ said Alice indignantly. ‘Let me alone!’

‘Serpent, I say again!’ repeated the Pigeon, but in a more subdued tone, and added with a kind of sob, ‘I’ve tried every way, and nothing seems to suit them!’

‘I haven’t the least idea what you’re talking about,’ said Alice.

‘I’ve tried the roots of trees, and I’ve tried banks, and I’ve tried hedges,’ the Pigeon went on, without attending to her; ‘but those serpents! There’s no pleasing them!’

Alice was more and more puzzled, but she thought there was no use in saying anything more till the Pigeon had finished.

‘As if it wasn’t trouble enough hatching the eggs,’ said the Pigeon; ‘but I must be on the look-out for serpents night and day! Why, I haven’t had a wink of sleep these three weeks!’

‘I’m very sorry you’ve been annoyed,’ said Alice, who was beginning to see its meaning.

‘And just as I’d taken the highest tree in the wood,’ continued the Pigeon, raising its voice to a shriek, ‘and just as I was thinking I should be free of them at last, they must needs come wriggling down from the sky! Ugh, Serpent!’

‘But I’m NOT a serpent, I tell you!’ said Alice. ‘I’m a--I’m a--’

‘Well! WHAT are you?’ said the Pigeon. ‘I can see you’re trying to invent something!’

‘I--I’m a little girl,’ said Alice, rather doubtfully, as she remembered the number of changes she had gone through that day.

‘A likely story indeed!’ said the Pigeon in a tone of the deepest contempt. ‘I’ve seen a good many little girls in my time, but never ONE with such a neck as that! No, no! You’re a serpent; and there’s no use denying it. I suppose you’ll be telling me next that you never tasted an egg!’

‘I HAVE tasted eggs, certainly,’ said Alice, who was a very truthful child; ‘but little girls eat eggs quite as much as serpents do, you know.’

‘I don’t believe it,’ said the Pigeon; ‘but if they do, why then they’re a kind of serpent, that’s all I can say.’

This was such a new idea to Alice, that she was quite silent for a minute or two, which gave the Pigeon the opportunity of adding, ‘You’re looking for eggs, I know THAT well enough; and what does it matter to me whether you’re a little girl or a serpent?’

‘It matters a good deal to ME,’ said Alice hastily; ‘but I’m not looking for eggs, as it happens; and if I was, I shouldn’t want YOURS: I don’t like them raw.’

‘Well, be off, then!’ said the Pigeon in a sulky tone, as it settled down again into its nest. Alice crouched down among the trees as well as she could, for her neck kept getting entangled among the branches, and every now and then she had to stop and untwist it. After a while she remembered that she still held the pieces of mushroom in her hands, and she set to work very carefully, nibbling first at one and then at the other, and growing sometimes taller and sometimes shorter, until she had succeeded in bringing herself down to her usual height.

It was so long since she had been anything near the right size, that it felt quite strange at first; but she got used to it in a few minutes, and began talking to herself, as usual. ‘Come, there’s half my plan done now! How puzzling all these changes are! I’m never sure what I’m going to be, from one minute to another! However, I’ve got back to my right size: the next thing is, to get into that beautiful garden--how IS that to be done, I wonder?’ As she said this, she came suddenly upon an open place, with a little house in it about four feet high. ‘Whoever lives there,’ thought Alice, ‘it’ll never do to come upon them THIS size: why, I should frighten them out of their wits!’ So she began nibbling at the righthand bit again, and did not venture to go near the house till she had brought herself down to nine inches high.

青虫の教え

青虫とアリスはしばらくだまったまま目を合わせていたんだけど、とうとう青虫が口から水ぎせるを外して、うつらうつらけだるそうに声をかけてきた。

「だれじゃ、おぬし。」と青虫。

こんなきっかけでは話も始めづらくって。アリスもどこかもじもじしながら答えてね、「あたくし――よくわかりませんの、今のところ――少なくとも今朝起きたときにはだれだったかわかってたのに、それからあたくし、どうも何度か変わってしまったみたいで。」

「どういうことかの？」と青虫はぴしゃり。「はっきりしてくれ！」

「だからはっきりしませんの、あいにく！」とアリス。「あたくしがあたくしじゃないの、わかって？」

「わからん。」と青虫。

「あいにく、これ以上何とも言えませんの。」とていねいに受け答えするアリス。「だって自分でもよくぞんじませんし、そもそも、１日でこんな色々な背たけになれば、頭もこんがらがってよ。」

「そうでもない。」と青虫。

「ふん、きっとあなたはまだあんまりおわかりでないのね。」とアリス。「でもあなただって、いずれさなぎになって――いつの日にかほら――そのあとちょうちょに変わったりしたら、そういうのやっぱりあなたもちょっとけったいに思えるものでしてよ、そうでしょう？」

「いささかも。」と青虫。

「まあ、あなたのお気持ちはちがうかもしれませんけど、」とアリス。「少なくとも、あたくしにはとてもけったいに思えるってこと。」

「おぬしとな！」と青虫は鼻でわらいながら、「そのおぬしはだれなのじゃ。」

というわけで、また話はふりだしに。アリスは、青虫のそっけなすぎるしゃべり口にちょっといらいらしてね、そこでむねをはって、いたけだかに言う、「まずはご自分から名乗るのがすじとぞんじますけど？」

「なぜかね？」と青虫。

これはまたまたなやましくて、何の言いわけも思いつかないアリス、青虫もひどくいやな気分になっているみたいなので、そこで回れ右。

「そこへもどれ！」と青虫が後ろから声をかけてきてね。「大事なことを教えてやる！」

たしかに悪くない話に思えたから、アリスはくるっとして引き返す。

「そう 怒 るな。」と青虫。

「それだけ？」とアリスは、なるだけいらいらを飲みこむ。

「いや。」と青虫。

ほかにすることもないので、とりあえず待つことにすれば、そのうちきっと向こうも耳をかせるだけのことを話してくれる、そうアリスはふんだ。しばらくのあいだ、もの言わずぷかぷかやってたんだけど、やがてうでをほどいて、ふたたび口から水ぎせるを外して、ひとこと。「自分が変わったと申すのじゃな？」

「あいにくね。」とアリス。「前できてたことが思い出せないの――それに、身体も１０分と同じ大きさを保ってられなくって！」

「思い出せぬとは、何をじゃ？」と青虫。

「その、 『がんばるぞミツバチ』 を歌ってみたのに、ぜんぜんちがってて！」とアリスはとってもしょんぼりした声でお返事。

「ならばどうだ、 『ウィリアムじいさん』 は。」と青虫。

アリスは手を組んで、歌い出す――

もう年なんだ　ウィリアムじいさん
頭は 白髪 だし
なのにいつでも　逆立ちばかりで――
わきまえろ

むすこに向かい　じいさん言う
若さはおそれさ
自分がバカだとわかれば
あとはやるだけさ

もう年なんだ　わかってくれ
それに太りすぎだ
なのに戸口で　バク 宙 なんてさ――
かんがえろ

白髪 ふりわけ　じいさん言う
ひと箱１シル
薬のおかげでしなやか――
どうじゃふた箱？

もう年なんだ　はぐきも弱い
あぶらみでやっとだ
なのにガチョウほねごと平らげ――
なんなんだ

わかいころは　へりくつばっか
夫婦ゲンカさ
おかげでアゴもじょうぶよ
こりゃ一生ものさ

もう年なんだ　ふつうだったら
目もしょぼしょぼのはず
なのに鼻にウナギを立てて――
器用 かよ！

３べん言えば　わかるじゃろ！
いい気になるなよ
もうたくさんじゃわい　いなねば
上からけおとす！

「正しくないのう。」と青虫。

「わりとね、あいにく。」とアリスはおずおず。「ところどころちがってはいてよ。」

「初めから終わりまでまちがっておる。」と青虫はばっさり、そのあとしばし、しぃん。

先に口を開いたのは青虫。

「どれくらいの背たけになりたい？」とたずねてきてね。

「べつに、背たけにこだわりなんかなくって、」とあわててお返事するアリス、「ただ、ころころ変わるのはいただけなくてよ、やっぱり。」

「さっぱり。」と青虫。

アリスは何にも言えない。生まれてこのかたこんなにきっぱりにべもないのははじめてで、自分でもだんだんはらが立ってきてね。

「今は足りておるのか？」と青虫。

「う～ん、もうちょっとばかり大きいほうがいただけそう、といったところね。」とアリス。「７センチの背たけって、なってみるとみじめなものよ。」

「こりゃほどよい背たけなんじゃぞ！」と 怒 った青虫が、しゃべるままに背すじをすっくと（ちょうど７センチのたけにね）。

「でも、こんなのしっくりこなくてよ！」と、弱ったアリスはみじめたらしく食いさがる。そうして、こう思う、「ここの生き物、こらえしょうってもの、ないのかしら！」

「そのうちしっくりこようて。」と青虫は口に水ぎせるをくわえて、またふかし始める。

今度もアリスは、相手がまた話す気になるまでぐっとこらえてね。ものの数分すると青虫は口から水ぎせるを外して、数度あくびもして身をゆすぶって。それからキノコから下りて、草むらへとくねくねと立ち入り、去りぎわのすて言葉。「こっちがわで身体がのびる、そっちがわで身体がちぢむ。」

「こっちって何の？　そっちって何の？」とひとり思うアリス。

「キノコのじゃ。」と青虫、口に出てない言葉に返事したと思いきや、まばたきするともう目の前から消えていて。

アリスは少しのあいだキノコにうたがわしい目を向けていたんだけど、そのどっちがどっちか見さだめようおとしてね、それでまったくの丸だったものだから、これはたいへんな 難問 だと気づいてね。とはいえとうとう両うでをとどくかぎりめいっぱいぐるりと回して、両手それぞれでちょびっとはしっこをもぎってね。

「それで今のはどっちがどっち？」とひとりごと、、試しに何が起きるかなと右手のかけらをちょびっとかじってみると。またたくまもなく、いきなりアゴ下へごちんと何かがぶつかる。なんと足とごっつんこだ！

このいきなりの変わりように、たいへんおそれをなしたものの、はげしくちぢんでいくのでぐずぐずしてはいられないと思って、とっさにもうひとつのかけらを食べにかかる。アゴが足にぐっとくっついているから、口を開けるのもむりに近いのに、なんとかやりとげて、ついに左手のかけらをちょっぴり飲みこむ。

＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊ 　　＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊ ＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊　　　＊

「うん！　ようやく頭が楽になってよ！」とアリスがはしゃいだのもつかのま、すぐにうろたえだしたのは、自分の 肩 がどこにも見つからなくなったから。ながめおろして目にとびこんだのは、かぎりなくのびた首で、遠く下に広がる緑の葉の海から１本つき出ているみたい。

「あの緑のしろもの-は、何だっていうの？」とアリス、「それにあたくしの肩は、どこに行ってて？　それから、もう、なんてこと、あたくしの手ったら、どうやったらそんな 迷子 に！」と口にしながら、あれこれ動かしてみたんだけど、どうもそのあとに起こったのは、遠くの緑の葉っぱのゆらゆらだけ。

頭まで手を上げるのはむりそうなので、そこで頭を手のところまで下ろしてみようとしてね、しかもうれしいことに、なんと首はどの向きへもやすやすと曲げられる、ヘビみたいに。そこで首を見事にうねうねと曲げてみせ、葉っぱのなかへつっこんで初めて、自分がそれまで下でうろついていた木々のてっぺんにいるだけなんだと気づいたんだけど、せつな、しゃーっとおどかす声にさっと引っこめると。顔に飛びかかってくる大きなハト、したたかに羽を打ちつけてくる。

「ヘビめ！」とさけぶハト。

「あたくしヘビじゃなくてよ！」とアリスもぷんすか。「よして！」

「ヘビよ、やっぱり！」とくりかえすハト、でもさっきよりもいきおいがなくてね、そのあとしくしくと、「どこへ行っても！　どうしようもないのよ！」

「言ってること、ちっともぴんと来なくてよ。」とアリス。

「木の根元も行ってみた、土手にも行った、生けがきも行ってみたのに。」とハトはこっちそっちのけで続ける、「あいつらヘビが！　いつまでもあきたらない！」

ますますわからないアリスだけれど、もう口を出してもしかたないので、終わるまでそのまま。

「タマゴかえすのがそう手間じゃないっていうのかいさ、」とハト。「ましてやヘビに目を光らせなくちゃいけなくて、夜も昼もよ！　あああ、この３週間、ひとねむりもしてないっていうのに！」

「おなやみお気の毒さま。」と、アリスにも言わんとすることがわかってきた。

「だから森いちばんの高い木にのぼって、」とひきつづき声をうわずらせるハト、「やっとのがれられたと思っていたとたん、うねうね空からしつこく来るじゃないのよ！　うげっ！　ヘビ！」

「でも、あたくしヘビじゃなくてよ、だから！」とアリス。「あたくし……あたくし……」

「ふん！　何だっていうの？」とハト。「何かごまかそうとしてんじゃないだろうね！」

「あたし――女の子だもん。」と言いつつ、どこかしっくりこないアリス、その日いく度となくのびちぢみしたのを思い出してしまってね。

「都合のいい言いのがれね！」とさげすみきったぐあいのハト。「生まれてこのかたおおぜい女の子を見てきたけれど、そんな首の長いのはひとっこひとりいなかったね！　いやいや！　あんたはヘビ、口ごたえしてもむだよ。どうせ次には、タマゴなんて味わったことないって言いくさりやがるんだろ！」

「タマゴくらい味わったことあってよ、ええ。」と言うアリスはほんとに正直もの、「でも、女の子もヘビといっしょでちゃんとタマゴを食べてよ、ほら。」

「信じられないね、」とハト、「そうだとしても、そんならやっぱり、ヘビのなかまじゃないか。それだけは言えるね。」

これにはアリスも考えがおよばず、なのでものの数分はだんまりで、それがハトにだめおしするすきをやってしまい、「あんたはタマゴをさがしてる、そんなことはお見通しなんだから。こっちからしたら、女の子だろうとヘビだろうと大してちがいないさね！」

「あたくしには大ちがいよ。」とかっとなったアリス、「それにあいにくタマゴはご入り用でないの。そうだとしても、なんでわざわざあなたのものなんか。それに生なまなんていただけなくってよ。」

「ふん、なら、しっしっ！」とむすっとしながらハトはまた自分の巣におさまる。アリスはアリスで、木々のあいだ、なるだけ身をかがめたんだけど、首が枝にからまるばっかりなので、そのたびごとにとちゅうでほどくはめに。しばらくしてふと、キノコのかけらを手ににぎったままと思い出してね、あらためてそうろっとあつかいながら、まずはひとつをかじり、さらにもうひとつ、のびたりちぢんだりしながら、ようやくいつもの背たけにおさまることができた。

かなりひさびさ背たけが元に近くなったので、初めはとっぴに思えたけど、数分もするとしっくりきて、そしてれいのごとくひとりごとの始まり。「ふう！　これで半分はかなったわけね！　ほんとわけわかんなくてよ、ころころ変わるなんて！　次から次へと、何になっていくのか読めないし！　とはいっても、元の背たけにもどれたんだから。お次は、あのきらびやかなお庭に入ることね――どうやってやったものかしら？」と言いながら、ふと出たのがひらけたところ、そこに１メートル２０くらいの小屋が。「どなたのおうちにしても、」と考えるアリス、「この大きさで顔を合わせるのはよした方がよさそう。だって、向こうさまこしをぬかしてしまいかねなくてよ！」そこでまた右手のかけらをかじりだして、とりあえずおうちに近づく前に自分の背たけを２３センチに落としたんだ。

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1
Chapter 2
Chapter 3
Chapter 4
Chapter 5
Chapter 6
Chapter 7
Chapter 8
Chapter 9
Chapter 10
Chapter 11
Chapter 12

Chapter 6

Click a checkbox to toggle a feature on or off in the text.

Cultural

Incorrect Word Usage

Nonsense Words

Onomatopoeia

Play on Words

Repetition

Pig and Pepper

For a minute or two she stood looking at the house, and wondering what to do next, when suddenly a footman in livery came running out of the wood--(she considered him to be a footman because he was in livery: otherwise, judging by his face only, she would have called him a fish)--and rapped loudly at the door with his knuckles. It was opened by another footman in livery, with a round face, and large eyes like a frog; and both footmen, Alice noticed, had powdered hair that curled all over their heads. She felt very curious to know what it was all about, and crept a little way out of the wood to listen.

The Fish-Footman began by producing from under his arm a great letter, nearly as large as himself, and this he handed over to the other, saying, in a solemn tone, ‘For the Duchess. An invitation from the Queen to play croquet.’ The Frog-Footman repeated, in the same solemn tone, only changing the order of the words a little, ‘From the Queen. An invitation for the Duchess to play croquet.’

Then they both bowed low, and their curls got entangled together.

Alice laughed so much at this, that she had to run back into the wood for fear of their hearing her; and when she next peeped out the Fish-Footman was gone, and the other was sitting on the ground near the door, staring stupidly up into the sky.

Alice went timidly up to the door, and knocked.

‘There’s no sort of use in knocking,’ said the Footman, ‘and that for two reasons. First, because I’m on the same side of the door as you are; secondly, because they’re making such a noise inside, no one could possibly hear you.’ And certainly there was a most extraordinary noise going on within--a constant howling and sneezing, and every now and then a great crash, as if a dish or kettle had been broken to pieces.

‘Please, then,’ said Alice, ‘how am I to get in?’

‘There might be some sense in your knocking,’ the Footman went on without attending to her, ‘if we had the door between us. For instance, if you were INSIDE, you might knock, and I could let you out, you know.’ He was looking up into the sky all the time he was speaking, and this Alice thought decidedly uncivil. ‘But perhaps he can’t help it,’ she said to herself; ‘his eyes are so VERY nearly at the top of his head. But at any rate he might answer questions.--How am I to get in?’ she repeated, aloud.

‘I shall sit here,’ the Footman remarked, ‘till tomorrow--’

At this moment the door of the house opened, and a large plate came skimming out, straight at the Footman’s head: it just grazed his nose, and broke to pieces against one of the trees behind him.

‘--or next day, maybe,’ the Footman continued in the same tone, exactly as if nothing had happened.

‘How am I to get in?’ asked Alice again, in a louder tone.

‘ARE you to get in at all?’ said the Footman. ‘That’s the first question, you know.’

It was, no doubt: only Alice did not like to be told so. ‘It’s really dreadful,’ she muttered to herself, ‘the way all the creatures argue. It’s enough to drive one crazy!’

The Footman seemed to think this a good opportunity for repeating his remark, with variations. ‘I shall sit here,’ he said, ‘on and off, for days and days.’

‘But what am I to do?’ said Alice.

‘Anything you like,’ said the Footman, and began whistling.

‘Oh, there’s no use in talking to him,’ said Alice desperately: ‘he’s perfectly idiotic!’ And she opened the door and went in.

The door led right into a large kitchen, which was full of smoke from one end to the other: the Duchess was sitting on a three-legged stool in the middle, nursing a baby; the cook was leaning over the fire, stirring a large cauldron which seemed to be full of soup.

‘There’s certainly too much pepper in that soup!’ Alice said to herself, as well as she could for sneezing.

There was certainly too much of it in the air. Even the Duchess sneezed occasionally; and as for the baby, it was sneezing and howling alternately without a moment’s pause. The only things in the kitchen that did not sneeze, were the cook, and a large cat which was sitting on the hearth and grinning from ear to ear.

‘Please would you tell me,’ said Alice, a little timidly, for she was not quite sure whether it was good manners for her to speak first, ‘why your cat grins like that?’

‘It’s a Cheshire cat,’ said the Duchess, ‘and that’s why. Pig!’

She said the last word with such sudden violence that Alice quite jumped; but she saw in another moment that it was addressed to the baby, and not to her, so she took courage, and went on again:--

‘I didn’t know that Cheshire cats always grinned; in fact, I didn’t know that cats COULD grin.’

‘They all can,’ said the Duchess; ‘and most of ‘em do.’

‘I don’t know of any that do,’ Alice said very politely, feeling quite pleased to have got into a conversation.

‘You don’t know much,’ said the Duchess; ‘and that’s a fact.’

Alice did not at all like the tone of this remark, and thought it would be as well to introduce some other subject of conversation. While she was trying to fix on one, the cook took the cauldron of soup off the fire, and at once set to work throwing everything within her reach at the Duchess and the baby--the fire-irons came first; then followed a shower of saucepans, plates, and dishes. The Duchess took no notice of them even when they hit her; and the baby was howling so much already, that it was quite impossible to say whether the blows hurt it or not.

‘Oh, PLEASE mind what you’re doing!’ cried Alice, jumping up and down in an agony of terror. ‘Oh, there goes his PRECIOUS nose’; as an unusually large saucepan flew close by it, and very nearly carried it off.

‘If everybody minded their own business,’ the Duchess said in a hoarse growl, ‘the world would go round a deal faster than it does.’

‘Which would NOT be an advantage,’ said Alice, who felt very glad to get an opportunity of showing off a little of her knowledge. ‘Just think of what work it would make with the day and night! You see the earth takes twenty-four hours to turn round on its axis--’

‘Talking of axes,’ said the Duchess, ‘chop off her head!’

Alice glanced rather anxiously at the cook, to see if she meant to take the hint; but the cook was busily stirring the soup, and seemed not to be listening, so she went on again: ‘Twenty-four hours, I THINK; or is it twelve? I--’

‘Oh, don’t bother ME,’ said the Duchess; ‘I never could abide figures!’ And with that she began nursing her child again, singing a sort of lullaby to it as she did so, and giving it a violent shake at the end of every line:

‘Speak roughly to your little boy,
And beat him when he sneezes:
He only does it to annoy,
Because he knows it teases.’

CHORUS.
(In which the cook and the baby joined):--
‘Wow! wow! wow!’

While the Duchess sang the second verse of the song, she kept tossing the baby violently up and down, and the poor little thing howled so, that Alice could hardly hear the words:--

‘I speak severely to my boy,
I beat him when he sneezes;
For he can thoroughly enjoy
The pepper when he pleases!’

CHORUS.
Wow! wow! wow!’

‘Here! you may nurse it a bit, if you like!’ the Duchess said to Alice, flinging the baby at her as she spoke. ‘I must go and get ready to play croquet with the Queen,’ and she hurried out of the room. The cook threw a frying-pan after her as she went out, but it just missed her.

Alice caught the baby with some difficulty, as it was a queer-shaped little creature, and held out its arms and legs in all directions, ‘just like a star-fish,’ thought Alice. The poor little thing was snorting like a steam-engine when she caught it, and kept doubling itself up and straightening itself out again, so that altogether, for the first minute or two, it was as much as she could do to hold it.

As soon as she had made out the proper way of nursing it, (which was to twist it up into a sort of knot, and then keep tight hold of its right ear and left foot, so as to prevent its undoing itself,) she carried it out into the open air. ‘IF I don’t take this child away with me,’ thought Alice, ‘they’re sure to kill it in a day or two: wouldn’t it be murder to leave it behind?’ She said the last words out loud, and the little thing grunted in reply (it had left off sneezing by this time). ‘Don’t grunt,’ said Alice; ‘that’s not at all a proper way of expressing yourself.’

The baby grunted again, and Alice looked very anxiously into its face to see what was the matter with it. There could be no doubt that it had a VERY turn-up nose, much more like a snout than a real nose; also its eyes were getting extremely small for a baby: altogether Alice did not like the look of the thing at all. ‘But perhaps it was only sobbing,’ she thought, and looked into its eyes again, to see if there were any tears.

No, there were no tears. ‘If you’re going to turn into a pig, my dear,’ said Alice, seriously, ‘I’ll have nothing more to do with you. Mind now!’ The poor little thing sobbed again (or grunted, it was impossible to say which), and they went on for some while in silence.

Alice was just beginning to think to herself, ‘Now, what am I to do with this creature when I get it home?’ when it grunted again, so violently, that she looked down into its face in some alarm. This time there could be NO mistake about it: it was neither more nor less than a pig, and she felt that it would be quite absurd for her to carry it further.

So she set the little creature down, and felt quite relieved to see it trot away quietly into the wood. ‘If it had grown up,’ she said to herself, ‘it would have made a dreadfully ugly child: but it makes rather a handsome pig, I think.’ And she began thinking over other children she knew, who might do very well as pigs, and was just saying to herself, ‘if one only knew the right way to change them--’ when she was a little startled by seeing the Cheshire Cat sitting on a bough of a tree a few yards off.

The Cat only grinned when it saw Alice. It looked good-natured, she thought: still it had VERY long claws and a great many teeth, so she felt that it ought to be treated with respect.

‘Cheshire Puss,’ she began, rather timidly, as she did not at all know whether it would like the name: however, it only grinned a little wider. ‘Come, it’s pleased so far,’ thought Alice, and she went on. ‘Would you tell me, please, which way I ought to go from here?’

‘That depends a good deal on where you want to get to,’ said the Cat.

‘I don’t much care where--’ said Alice.

‘Then it doesn’t matter which way you go,’ said the Cat.

‘--so long as I get SOMEWHERE,’ Alice added as an explanation.

‘Oh, you’re sure to do that,’ said the Cat, ‘if you only walk long enough.’

Alice felt that this could not be denied, so she tried another question. ‘What sort of people live about here?’

‘In THAT direction,’ the Cat said, waving its right paw round, ‘lives a Hatter: and in THAT direction,’ waving the other paw, ‘lives a March Hare. Visit either you like: they’re both mad.’

‘But I don’t want to go among mad people,’ Alice remarked.

‘Oh, you can’t help that,’ said the Cat: ‘we’re all mad here. I’m mad. You’re mad.’

‘How do you know I’m mad?’ said Alice.

‘You must be,’ said the Cat, ‘or you wouldn’t have come here.’

Alice didn’t think that proved it at all; however, she went on ‘And how do you know that you’re mad?’

‘To begin with,’ said the Cat, ‘a dog’s not mad. You grant that?’

‘I suppose so,’ said Alice.

‘Well, then,’ the Cat went on, ‘you see, a dog growls when it’s angry, and wags its tail when it’s pleased. Now I growl when I’m pleased, and wag my tail when I’m angry. Therefore I’m mad.’

‘I call it purring, not growling,’ said Alice.

‘Call it what you like,’ said the Cat. ‘Do you play croquet with the Queen to-day?’

‘I should like it very much,’ said Alice, ‘but I haven’t been invited yet.’

‘You’ll see me there,’ said the Cat, and vanished.

Alice was not much surprised at this, she was getting so used to queer things happening. While she was looking at the place where it had been, it suddenly appeared again.

‘By-the-bye, what became of the baby?’ said the Cat. ‘I’d nearly forgotten to ask.’

‘It turned into a pig,’ Alice quietly said, just as if it had come back in a natural way.

‘I thought it would,’ said the Cat, and vanished again.

Alice waited a little, half expecting to see it again, but it did not appear, and after a minute or two she walked on in the direction in which the March Hare was said to live. ‘I’ve seen hatters before,’ she said to herself; ‘the March Hare will be much the most interesting, and perhaps as this is May it won’t be raving mad--at least not so mad as it was in March.’ As she said this, she looked up, and there was the Cat again, sitting on a branch of a tree.

‘Did you say pig, or fig?’ said the Cat.

‘I said pig,’ replied Alice; ‘and I wish you wouldn’t keep appearing and vanishing so suddenly: you make one quite giddy.’

‘All right,’ said the Cat; and this time it vanished quite slowly, beginning with the end of the tail, and ending with the grin, which remained some time after the rest of it had gone.

‘Well! I’ve often seen a cat without a grin,’ thought Alice; ‘but a grin without a cat! It’s the most curious thing I ever saw in my life!’

She had not gone much farther before she came in sight of the house of the March Hare: she thought it must be the right house, because the chimneys were shaped like ears and the roof was thatched with fur. It was so large a house, that she did not like to go nearer till she had nibbled some more of the lefthand bit of mushroom, and raised herself to about two feet high: even then she walked up towards it rather timidly, saying to herself ‘Suppose it should be raving mad after all! I almost wish I’d gone to see the Hatter instead!’

ブタとコショウ

ものの数分ぼう立ちでおうちをながめて、次に何をしようかと思っているうち、ふいにお仕着せのめし使いが森から走り出てきて――（そいつをめし使いだと見たのはお仕着せすがただったからで、そうでなかったら顔だけではお魚としかわからなかっただろうね）――それからにぎった手の角っこでドアをとんとん。するとドアが開いて、お仕着せのめし使いがもうひとり、丸顔で大きなお目々でカエルみたい。さらにめし使いはふたりとも、見たところ頭に 粉 をふいたくるくる まきのカツラをかぶっているようで。へんてこで一体全体何なのかわくわくしてきてね、森からそろりと少し身を乗り出して耳をすませる。

お魚めし使いがまずわきから取り出だしたるは大きなお手紙、自分の体と同じほどの大きさで、これを相手に手わたしながら大げさに言うんだ、「御前さまへ。クイーンさまよりクローケーのおさそいなり。」カエルめし使いも同じく大げさにくりかえして「クイーンさまより。御前さまへクローケーのおさそいでありますか。」

そのあとふたりとも深々おじぎをすると、 まきまきカツラがからまりあう。

アリスは笑い転げてしまってね、さとられたかもと森のなかへかけもどるはめに。そうしてまた顔をのぞかせたときには、お魚めし使いはいなくなっていて、そのお相手がドアわきの地面にすわりこんで、空をぼんやり見つめていてね。

アリスはおずおずとドアのところへ行って、とんとん。

「ノックをしてもむだであります。」と言うめし使い、「そのわけはふたつ。ひとつは、わたくしめがあなたさまと同じくドアのこちらがわにおりますゆえ。もうひとつは、なかが相当さわがしいので、あなたさまがたたいても、だれにも聞こえちゃおりません。」してみるとたしかに内がわでは今もとてつもない物音がしていて――ひっきりなしにどなる声とくしゃみの音、合間にいちいちがしゃんがしゃん、まるでお皿かやかんが 粉々 にわれたみたい。

「それでしたら、」とアリス、「入るにはいかがすれば？」

「そもそもノックしてしかるべきは、」とめし使いはこちらの話も聞かずに続けてね、「おたがいがドアをはさんでいればこその話。たとえばあなたさまが内がわにいて、ノックをしたなら、わたくしめは外へ出してさしあげます。」話しているあいだもずっと空を見上げていたので、アリスにはあからさまにおぎょうぎが悪く思えてね。「でももしややむをえないのかも。」とひとりごちて、「お目々がまさに頭のだいたいてっぺん。それにしても聞いたことに答えてくれてもいいんでなくて。――入るにはいかがすれば？」ともう１度大声。

「わたくしめはじっとここに、」とめし使いの言い分、「明日まで……」

そのせつな、おうちのドアが開いて、大皿がすれすれを飛んできて、めし使いの頭へまっしぐら。ちょうど鼻をかすめて、後ろの木のひとつに当たって粉々に。

「……いやその次の日まで、か。」と続けるめし使いの話しぶりは、まったく何もなかったかのよう。

「入るにはいかがすれば？」とまたたずねるアリスはさらに声をはり上げていて。

「どうしてもなかへ入るのでありますか。」とめし使い。「まずそこのところどうなんです、ほら。」

言われてみれば。ただアリスもそれだけは言われたくなくって。「なんてはしたない。」とアリスはぶつぶつひとりごと、「そろいもそろってつっかかってくる。頭がおかしくなってもよさそうなものね！」

めし使いはさきほどの言葉をくりかえすには今しかないと思ったのか、言い方を変えてね。「わたくしめはじっとここに、やすみやすみ、来る日も来る日も。」

「でもあたくしはどうすればよくて？」とアリス。

「お好きにどうぞ。」とめし使いは口笛をふきだして。

「もう、話していてもらちが開かなくてよ。」とやれやれのアリス。「まったくのうすのろね！」そうしてドアを開けてなかへお立ち入り。

ドアはそのまま台所に続いていてね、もくもくけむりがすみずみまでいっぱい。御前さまはお部屋のまんなか、３本足のいすにこしかけ、赤ちゃんをあやしている。コックが火元にぐっとよって、大きなおなべでなみなみとしたスープをまぜまぜ。

「スープにこんなにコショウ、ぜったい入れすぎ！」アリスのひとりごとも、くしゃみのせいでこれがやっと。

コショウのひどさたるや、あたりにまんえんするほど。御前さままでときおりはくしゅん、赤ちゃんはというと、ひっきりなしにかわるがわるくくしゅんおぎゃあ。台所にいてくしゃみをしていないのはただふたり、コックと図体のでかいネコ、そのネコは火元のそばに丸まって、耳にとどきそうなくらいにこにこ 愛想 たっぷり。

「ごめんください、」とおそるおそるのアリス、そのわけはおぎょうぎとして、自分から話しかけていいものか自信がなかったから、「このネコちゃん、どうしてこんなに愛想がよろしいの？」

「こやつはチェシアのネコ、」と御前さま、「ゆえにな。ブタめ！」

しめにいきなりきつい言葉がでたので、アリスはもうとびあがってね、でもそのあとすぐ自分でなく赤ちゃんに向けたものとわかったから、気を取り直してまた話の続き。

「なるほどチェシアのネコは 愛想 よしってわけ。まさかネコがこんなに愛想よくできるなんて。」

「みなできおる、」と御前さま、「大半がそうしおる。」

「思いもよらなくてよ。」とアリスは取りつくろうものの、実はお話できたのがたいそううれしくって。

「そちがものを知らぬだけ、」と御前さま、「世のことわりじゃ。」

アリスもそんなふうに言われるのは気に入らなくて、何かべつの話をふった方がいいと思ってね。何かと決めかねているうちに、コックはスープのおなべを火から外すと、いきなりあたりのものを手当たり次第に御前さまと赤ちゃんに投げつけだしてね――火元の金具がまず飛んできて、そのあと続いて小なべやお大皿小皿が雨あられ。御前さまは自分に当たっても気にするそぶりさえなくって。赤ちゃんはずっとひどいくらいに泣きわめいてるから、ぶつかって痛いたいのか 痛 くないのかもよくわからない。

「ねえ、いいかげん気にしたらどうなの！」と声をはりあげるアリス、やきもきしてぴょんぴょん、「ほら、その子の大事なお鼻が！」そのときばかでかいシチューなべがぎりぎりのところに飛んできて、あわや鼻を持っていくところ。

「みながひとにちょっかい出さぬようになれば、」と御前さまはガラガラ声でうなってね、「世の中は今よりずいぶん早く回ろうというのに。」

「そんなことのどこがいいの。」とアリスは 知恵 をひけらかすなら今だと 得意満面 。「考えてもみて、そんなことをしたら昼と夜がどうなるか！　いいこと、地球は自転するのに２４時間ちょっきり……」

「ちょっきりとな、」と御前さま、「こやつの首をちょっきりだ！」

アリスはそわそわとコックに目をやってね、そのひとがまさか言うとおりにはと様子をうかがったんだけど、コックはせわしなくスープをかきまぜるばかりで、話を聞いていたそぶりもないから、また口を開いて、「２４時間、かな？　あれ１２時間？　えーと……」

「ああ、だまらっしゃい！」と御前さま。「数字なぞいらいらする！」そうしてさらにはまた子どもをあやしだして、それらしく子守歌みたいなのをうたうんだけど、１ふしごとにきつくゆすってね――

「小さな子どもはどやしつけろ
　くしゃみをしたらぶったたけ
そいつはただのいやがらせ
　わかってやってる、このクソガキァ」

コーラス
（コックと赤子がいっしょになって）
「わう！　わう！　わう！」

御前さまが２つめのふしをうたっているあいだなんか、赤ちゃんをあらあらしく上へ放り投げるわ、かわいそうに赤ちゃんは泣きわめくわで、アリスには歌詞かしが大半聞き取れなくて――

「わが家のガキにはしかりつける
　くしゃみをしたらぶったたく
放っておけばそのうちに
　コショウだって楽しみやがる」

コーラス
「わう！　わう！　わう！」

「ほれ！　よければちょっとあやしてみるがよい！」と御前さまはアリスに言って、しゃべりきらないうちに赤ちゃんを放り投げてくる。「わらわはそろそろクイーンさまとのクローケーのしたくじゃ。」と部屋をいそいそと出てゆく。去りぎわにコックが後ろからフライパンを投げつけたけど、ねらいは外れてね。

アリスがなんとか赤ちゃんを受け取ると、このけったいななりをした小さな生き物は手足を四方八方広げたので、「ヒトデみたい。」と思うアリス。かわいそうにこの小さいのは、受け取ったときには汽車のように鼻からぶーと湯気を出していて、やたら身をくねらせたりそりかえったりしたので、とにかくまずものの数分はかかえるだけでせいいっぱい。

ちゃんとあやすコツ（むすび目を作るみたいにねじって右の耳と左の足をぐっとおさえてほどけないようにすること）がわかるとすぐに、かかえたまま表に出てね。「あたくしがこの子を連れ出さなければ、」と思うアリス、「ものの数日できっと 殺 されてしまってよ。置き去りにするなんて 人殺 しも 同然 じゃなくて？」おしまいのところはもう声にも出ていて、小さいのも何かぐずっていて（このときにはくしゃみもおさまっていてね）。「ブーブー言わないの、」とアリス、「ものを言いたいのならちゃんとはっきり。」

赤ちゃんはまたもやブーブー、そこでアリスはいぶかしげに顔をのぞいてね、何かあったのかと思って。するとどこからどう見ても、そこにあるのはまさしく上向きの鼻、人の鼻というよりはもうブタの鼻、しかも目は赤ちゃんにしてはひどく小さくなっていて、とにかくアリスはそいつの 面 がまったく気に入らない。「でもめそめそしてるだけかも。」と考えて、また目をのぞいて、なみだがないかたしかめてみる。

ない、なみだなんかちっとも。「ブタになったりしたら、まったく、」とアリスは真顔、「こんりんざいかまってあげなくてよ。めっ！」かわいそうにその小さいのはまたもや泣いて（というかブーブー、と言っていいものやら）、しばらくは何も言わずに進んでいってね。

アリスの頭にはよぎりはじめていたことがあってね、「ところでこの生き物をうちにつれかえって、あたくしはどうしようっていうのかしら。」するとそのときまたブーブーとうるさくするので、顔をのぞきこんでちょっとびっくり。今度はもう見まちがいのしようがない、どこからどこまでもまったくのブタ、そうなるともはやつれていくのもとってもばからしくなってきてね。

そこでその小さい生き物を下ろして見守っていると、そそくさとっとこと森へ入っていったので、すごくほっとしてね。「大きくなったら、」とひとりごと、「ものすごくぶっさいくな子になりそうだったけど、ブタならちょっとはかっこよくなる、かも。」そうして今度は自分の知り合いのなかでもブタとしてならやっていけそうな子を思いうかべながら、ひとりごとを言おうとしてね、「ちゃんと化けるやり方を知ってたなら……」とちょうどそのとき、ちょっとびくっとしてね、目の前で、チェシアネコが数メートル先の木の大枝にちょこんといたんだ。

ネコは愛きょうよくにんまりするだけで、じっとアリスを見つめる。愛想のいいネコ、と思ったアリス。

しかもほんとに長いツメと、りっぱな歯がずらりとあるものだから、下手に出なければという気になってね。

「チェッシャにゃん。」とちょっぴりおずおずよびかけてね、だってそのよび方が相手のお気にめすかさっぱりわからなかったから。ところが向こうはさらにちょっとにやっとするだけ。「ふう、とりあえず気げんはいいみたい。」と思ったアリスは言葉を続けてね。「教えてくださいませんこと？　ここからどちらに行った方がよろしくて？」

「そいつはやっぱりお前の行きたいところ次第だにゃ。」とネコ。

「べつにどこでもよくてよ……」とアリス。

「にゃら、どこへにゃりとも行けばいい。」とネコ。

「……ちゃんとどこかへたどりつけるなら。」とアリスは付け足しの言いわけ。

「そりゃそにょくらいできるとも、」と言うネコ、「それにゃりに歩けば。」

アリスはたしかにもっともだと思ったので、今度はべつのことを問いかけてね。「このあたりには、どんなひとがお住み？」

「あっちの方にゃ、」とここでネコは右の肉球をぐるっとふってね、「ぼうし屋が住んでる。そんであっちの方にゃ、」と今度は左の肉球をふって、「ヤヨイウサギ。好きにゃ方に行け。どっちもおかしにゃやつだ。」

「でも、おかしなひとのところに行くのはごめんでしてよ。」と言い出すアリス。

「まあ仕方のにゃいこと。」とネコ。「ここじゃみんなおかしいにゃ。にゃあも、お前も。」

「あたくしがおかしい？　どうして？」

「そりゃそうにゃ、」とネコ、「でにゃきゃこんにゃとこに来ない。」

アリスはものも言いようだと思ったけど、とりあえず続けてね、「じゃあ、あなたがおかしいっていうのは？」

「まずもって、」とネコ、「犬はおかしくにゃい。これはいいにゃ？」

「まあそうね。」とアリス。

「にゃらわかるにゃ、」とたたみかけるネコ、「犬はおこるとうにゃって、うれしいとしっぽをふる。にゃのに、おいらはうれしいとうにゃるし、はらが立つとしっぽをふる。にゃから、おいらはおかしい。」

「それって、うなるじゃなくて、のどを鳴らすってことじゃにゃいの？」とアリス。

「どう言ってもおにゃじこと。」とネコ。「今日はクイーンとクローケーするんにゃにゃいのか？」

「ぜひやってみたくてよ。」とアリス、「でもおさそい受けてないし。」

「ではまたそこで。」と言うなりネコはぱっと消える。

アリスはこんなことにはもうわりと平気で、けったいなことが起きるのもなれっこ。それでもネコのいたところをじっと見ていたんだけど、するとまたぱっと出てきてね。

「ところで、赤んぼはどうにゃった？」とネコ。「聞くのをうっかりしてたにゃ。」

「ブタに化けてよ。」と事もなげに答えたアリスには、もうネコがもどってきたのも当たり前みたいで。

「そうにゃろうと思った。」と言ってネコはまた消える。

アリスはどうせまた出てくると思ってしばらく待ったんだけど、どうも出てこないので、ものの数分するとヤヨイウサギが住んでると言われた方へと進み出してね。「ぼうし屋は見たことあるから、」とひとりごと、「ヤヨイウサギの方がきっともっとずっと面白いはず、でもまあ今は５月だから、そこまでおかしくはないかも――少なくとも３月ほどおかしくないかな。」こう口にしながら見上げると、なんとそこにはまたネコが木の枝にちょこん。

「『ブタ』にゃっけ、『ブナ』にゃっけ？」とネコ。

「だから『ブタ』。」と答えるアリス、「あの、そんなむやみやたらにぱっと出たり消えたりしないでいただけて？　ひどくめまいがしてよ。」

「にゃるほど。」というネコ。なので今度はきわめてゆっくりと消えることにしてね、しっぽの先からじんわりと、おしまいには 愛想 だけが本体が消えたあとにもなごりとしてしばらくあって。

「まあ！　愛想なしのネコならよく見るけど、」と思うアリス、「ネコなしの愛想だなんて！　生まれてこのかたこんなへんてこなこと見たのはじめて！」

そんなに歩くわけでもなくすぐにヤヨイウサギのおうちが目に入ってくる。そのおうちにちがいないと思ったのは、えんとつが耳みたいな形で、屋根が毛なみ ふわふわ だったから。大きなおうちだったので、はじめは近よりたくなかったけど、とうとう左手にあったキノコのかけらをもうちょっとかじって、背たけを６０センチくらいに上げてね。そのあとでも近より方はこわごわで、ひとりごと、「やっぱりめちゃくちゃおかしかったらどうしよう！　こっちじゃなくぼうし屋の方に行けばよかったかな？」

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1 | Chapter 2 | Chapter 3 | Chapter 4 | Chapter 5 | Chapter 6 | Chapter 7 | Chapter 8 | Chapter 9 | Chapter 10 | Chapter 11 | Chapter 12

Chapter 7

A Mad Tea-Party

There was a table set out under a tree in front of the house, and the March Hare and the Hatter were having tea at it: a Dormouse was sitting between them, fast asleep, and the other two were using it as a cushion, resting their elbows on it, and talking over its head. ‘Very uncomfortable for the Dormouse,’ thought Alice; ‘only, as it’s asleep, I suppose it doesn’t mind.’

The table was a large one, but the three were all crowded together at one corner of it: ‘No room! No room!’ they cried out when they saw Alice coming. ‘There’s PLENTY of room!’ said Alice indignantly, and she sat down in a large arm-chair at one end of the table.

‘Have some wine,’ the March Hare said in an encouraging tone.

Alice looked all round the table, but there was nothing on it but tea. ‘I don’t see any wine,’ she remarked.

‘There isn’t any,’ said the March Hare.

‘Then it wasn’t very civil of you to offer it,’ said Alice angrily.

‘It wasn’t very civil of you to sit down without being invited,’ said the March Hare.

‘I didn’t know it was YOUR table,’ said Alice; ‘it’s laid for a great many more than three.’

‘Your hair wants cutting,’ said the Hatter. He had been looking at Alice for some time with great curiosity, and this was his first speech.

‘You should learn not to make personal remarks,’ Alice said with some severity; ‘it’s very rude.’

The Hatter opened his eyes very wide on hearing this; but all he SAID was, ‘Why is a raven like a writing-desk?’

‘Come, we shall have some fun now!’ thought Alice. ‘I’m glad they’ve begun asking riddles.--I believe I can guess that,’ she added aloud.

‘Do you mean that you think you can find out the answer to it?’ said the March Hare.

‘Exactly so,’ said Alice.

‘Then you should say what you mean,’ the March Hare went on.

‘I do,’ Alice hastily replied; ‘at least--at least I mean what I say--that’s the same thing, you know.’

‘Not the same thing a bit!’ said the Hatter. ‘You might just as well say that “I see what I eat” is the same thing as “I eat what I see”!’

‘You might just as well say,’ added the March Hare, ‘that “I like what I get” is the same thing as “I get what I like”!’

‘You might just as well say,’ added the Dormouse, who seemed to be talking in his sleep, ‘that “I breathe when I sleep” is the same thing as “I sleep when I breathe”!’

‘It IS the same thing with you,’ said the Hatter, and here the conversation dropped, and the party sat silent for a minute, while Alice thought over all she could remember about ravens and writing-desks, which wasn’t much.

The Hatter was the first to break the silence. ‘What day of the month is it?’ he said, turning to Alice: he had taken his watch out of his pocket, and was looking at it uneasily, shaking it every now and then, and holding it to his ear.

Alice considered a little, and then said ‘The fourth.’

‘Two days wrong!’ sighed the Hatter. ‘I told you butter wouldn’t suit the works!’ he added looking angrily at the March Hare.

‘It was the BEST butter,’ the March Hare meekly replied.

‘Yes, but some crumbs must have got in as well,’ the Hatter grumbled: ‘you shouldn’t have put it in with the bread-knife.’

The March Hare took the watch and looked at it gloomily: then he dipped it into his cup of tea, and looked at it again: but he could think of nothing better to say than his first remark, ‘It was the BEST butter, you know.’

Alice had been looking over his shoulder with some curiosity. ‘What a funny watch!’ she remarked. ‘It tells the day of the month, and doesn’t tell what o’clock it is!’

‘Why should it?’ muttered the Hatter. ‘Does YOUR watch tell you what year it is?’

‘Of course not,’ Alice replied very readily: ‘but that’s because it stays the same year for such a long time together.’

‘Which is just the case with MINE,’ said the Hatter.

Alice felt dreadfully puzzled. The Hatter’s remark seemed to have no sort of meaning in it, and yet it was certainly English. ‘I don’t quite understand you,’ she said, as politely as she could.

‘The Dormouse is asleep again,’ said the Hatter, and he poured a little hot tea upon its nose.

The Dormouse shook its head impatiently, and said, without opening its eyes, ‘Of course, of course; just what I was going to remark myself.’

‘Have you guessed the riddle yet?’ the Hatter said, turning to Alice again.

‘No, I give it up,’ Alice replied: ‘what’s the answer?’

‘I haven’t the slightest idea,’ said the Hatter.

‘Nor I,’ said the March Hare.

Alice sighed wearily. ‘I think you might do something better with the time,’ she said, ‘than waste it in asking riddles that have no answers.’

‘If you knew Time as well as I do,’ said the Hatter, ‘you wouldn’t talk about wasting IT. It’s HIM .’

‘I don’t know what you mean,’ said Alice.

‘Of course you don’t!’ the Hatter said, tossing his head contemptuously. ‘I dare say you never even spoke to Time!’

‘Perhaps not,’ Alice cautiously replied: ‘but I know I have to beat time when I learn music.’

‘Ah! that accounts for it,’ said the Hatter. ‘He won’t stand beating. Now, if you only kept on good terms with him, he’d do almost anything you liked with the clock. For instance, suppose it were nine o’clock in the morning, just time to begin lessons: you’d only have to whisper a hint to Time, and round goes the clock in a twinkling! Half-past one, time for dinner!’

(‘I only wish it was,’ the March Hare said to itself in a whisper.)

‘That would be grand, certainly,’ said Alice thoughtfully: ‘but then--I shouldn’t be hungry for it, you know.’

‘Not at first, perhaps,’ said the Hatter: ‘but you could keep it to half-past one as long as you liked.’

‘Is that the way YOU manage?’ Alice asked.

The Hatter shook his head mournfully. ‘Not I!’ he replied. ‘We quarrelled last March--just before HE went mad, you know--’ (pointing with his tea spoon at the March Hare,) ‘--it was at the great concert given by the Queen of Hearts, and I had to sing

“ Twinkle, twinkle, little bat!
How I wonder what you’re at! ”

You know the song, perhaps?’

‘I’ve heard something like it,’ said Alice.

‘It goes on, you know,’ the Hatter continued, ‘in this way:--

“ Up above the world you fly,
Like a tea-tray in the sky . Twinkle, twinkle--“’

Here the Dormouse shook itself, and began singing in its sleep ‘Twinkle, twinkle, twinkle, twinkle--’ and went on so long that they had to pinch it to make it stop.

‘Well, I’d hardly finished the first verse,’ said the Hatter, ‘when the Queen jumped up and bawled out, “He’s murdering the time! Off with his head!”’

‘How dreadfully savage!’ exclaimed Alice.

‘And ever since that,’ the Hatter went on in a mournful tone, ‘he won’t do a thing I ask! It’s always six o’clock now.’

A bright idea came into Alice’s head. ‘Is that the reason so many tea-things are put out here?’ she asked.

‘Yes, that’s it,’ said the Hatter with a sigh: ‘it’s always tea-time, and we’ve no time to wash the things between whiles.’

‘Then you keep moving round, I suppose?’ said Alice.

‘Exactly so,’ said the Hatter: ‘as the things get used up.’

‘But what happens when you come to the beginning again?’ Alice ventured to ask.

‘Suppose we change the subject,’ the March Hare interrupted, yawning. ‘I’m getting tired of this. I vote the young lady tells us a story.’

‘I’m afraid I don’t know one,’ said Alice, rather alarmed at the proposal.

‘Then the Dormouse shall!’ they both cried. ‘Wake up, Dormouse!’ And they pinched it on both sides at once.

The Dormouse slowly opened his eyes. ‘I wasn’t asleep,’ he said in a hoarse, feeble voice: ‘I heard every word you fellows were saying.’

‘Tell us a story!’ said the March Hare.

‘Yes, please do!’ pleaded Alice.

‘And be quick about it,’ added the Hatter, ‘or you’ll be asleep again before it’s done.’

‘Once upon a time there were three little sisters,’ the Dormouse began in a great hurry; ‘and their names were Elsie, Lacie, and Tillie; and they lived at the bottom of a well--’

‘What did they live on?’ said Alice, who always took a great interest in questions of eating and drinking.

‘They lived on treacle,’ said the Dormouse, after thinking a minute or two.

‘They couldn’t have done that, you know,’ Alice gently remarked; ‘they’d have been ill.’

‘So they were,’ said the Dormouse; ‘VERY ill.’

Alice tried to fancy to herself what such an extraordinary ways of living would be like, but it puzzled her too much, so she went on: ‘But why did they live at the bottom of a well?’

‘Take some more tea,’ the March Hare said to Alice, very earnestly.

‘I’ve had nothing yet,’ Alice replied in an offended tone, ‘so I can’t take more.’

‘You mean you can’t take LESS,’ said the Hatter: ‘it’s very easy to take MORE than nothing.’

‘Nobody asked YOUR opinion,’ said Alice.

‘Who’s making personal remarks now?’ the Hatter asked triumphantly.

Alice did not quite know what to say to this: so she helped herself to some tea and bread-and-butter, and then turned to the Dormouse, and repeated her question. ‘Why did they live at the bottom of a well?’

The Dormouse again took a minute or two to think about it, and then said, ‘It was a treacle-well.’

‘There’s no such thing!’ Alice was beginning very angrily, but the Hatter and the March Hare went ‘Sh! sh!’ and the Dormouse sulkily remarked, ‘If you can’t be civil, you’d better finish the story for yourself.’

‘No, please go on!’ Alice said very humbly; ‘I won’t interrupt again. I dare say there may be ONE.’

‘One, indeed!’ said the Dormouse indignantly. However, he consented to go on. ‘And so these three little sisters--they were learning to draw, you know--’

‘What did they draw?’ said Alice, quite forgetting her promise.

‘Treacle,’ said the Dormouse, without considering at all this time.

‘I want a clean cup,’ interrupted the Hatter: ‘let’s all move one place on.’

He moved on as he spoke, and the Dormouse followed him: the March Hare moved into the Dormouse’s place, and Alice rather unwillingly took the place of the March Hare. The Hatter was the only one who got any advantage from the change: and Alice was a good deal worse off than before, as the March Hare had just upset the milk-jug into his plate.

Alice did not wish to offend the Dormouse again, so she began very cautiously: ‘But I don’t understand. Where did they draw the treacle from?’

‘You can draw water out of a water-well,’ said the Hatter; ‘so I should think you could draw treacle out of a treacle-well--eh, stupid?’

‘But they were IN the well,’ Alice said to the Dormouse, not choosing to notice this last remark.

‘Of course they were’, said the Dormouse; ‘--well in.’

This answer so confused poor Alice, that she let the Dormouse go on for some time without interrupting it.

‘They were learning to draw,’ the Dormouse went on, yawning and rubbing its eyes, for it was getting very sleepy; ‘and they drew all manner of things--everything that begins with an M--’

‘Why with an M?’ said Alice.

‘Why not?’ said the March Hare.

Alice was silent.

The Dormouse had closed its eyes by this time, and was going off into a doze; but, on being pinched by the Hatter, it woke up again with a little shriek, and went on: ‘--that begins with an M, such as mouse-traps, and the moon, and memory, and muchness--you know you say things are “much of a muchness”--did you ever see such a thing as a drawing of a muchness?’

‘Really, now you ask me,’ said Alice, very much confused, ‘I don’t think--’

‘Then you shouldn’t talk,’ said the Hatter.

This piece of rudeness was more than Alice could bear: she got up in great disgust, and walked off; the Dormouse fell asleep instantly, and neither of the others took the least notice of her going, though she looked back once or twice, half hoping that they would call after her: the last time she saw them, they were trying to put the Dormouse into the teapot.

‘At any rate I’ll never go THERE again!’ said Alice as she picked her way through the wood. ‘It’s the stupidest tea-party I ever was at in all my life!’

Just as she said this, she noticed that one of the trees had a door leading right into it. ‘That’s very curious!’ she thought. ‘But everything’s curious today. I think I may as well go in at once.’ And in she went.

Once more she found herself in the long hall, and close to the little glass table. ‘Now, I’ll manage better this time,’ she said to herself, and began by taking the little golden key, and unlocking the door that led into the garden. Then she went to work nibbling at the mushroom (she had kept a piece of it in her pocket) till she was about a foot high: then she walked down the little passage: and THEN--she found herself at last in the beautiful garden, among the bright flower-beds and the cool fountains.

おかしなお茶会

なんとひとつのテーブルが家のまん前の木かげにもうけられてあってね、ヤヨイウサギとぼうし屋がそこでお茶のまっ 最中 。あいだにはヤマネもすわっていて、ぐっすりいねむり。そこでふたりはそいつをクッション代わりにそれぞれひじ置きにしてね、頭ごしにおしゃべり。「ひどく落ち着かなくてよ、ヤマネには。」と思うアリス。「ただぐっすりだから気にならないのかも。」

テーブルはでっかいのに、３にんはすみっこにぎゅっとより集まっていてね。「 席 ならもうないぞ！」と、やってきたアリスを見つけて声を上げて。「いっぱいあってよ！」とぷんすかアリス、そうしてテーブルのはしにあった大きなアームチェアにどしん。

「ワインでも飲め。」と 景気 づけにヤヨイウサギ。

アリスはテーブルをぐるっと見回したけど、そこにあるのはほんのお茶だけ。「どこにワインなんか。」と言い返す。

「どこにもねえ。」とヤヨイウサギ。

「とんだ 無礼者 ね、ないものをすすめるなんて。」とアリスはごりっぷく。

「てめえこそ無礼者だ、さそわれもしねえのに、すわりやがって。」とヤヨイウサギ。

「まさか３にんだけのテーブルだなんて。」とアリス。「空いてるところもずいぶんあるけれど。」

「かみの毛、のびすぎだな。」と言い出すぼうし屋。どうにも気になったのか、しばらくアリスを見つめていたんだけど、ようやく口から出た言葉がそれで。

「ひとに口出しするなんてダメなんだから。」とアリスはびしっと言いつけてね、「とってもぶしつけ。」

ぼうし屋はこれを耳にして目を丸くしたんだけど、口にしたのはこれだけ、「カラスとかけて 勉強机 ととく、その心は？」

「ふぅん、ちょっと面白そうじゃない！」と思うアリス。「のぞむところよ、なぞかけなら――あれね、もうわかりそう。」とわざわざ声に出す。

「それはつまり、もう答えがわかるってえことか。」とヤヨイウサギ。

「その通り。」とアリス。

「じゃあ、わかったってことは言えるんだろうな。」とたたみかけるヤヨイウサギ。

「だから、」とアリスはあわててお返事、「そのうち――そのうち言えるってことはわかったの――同じでしてよ、ほら。」

「同じなものか！」とぼうし屋。「ならば、『食べるってことは見える』と『見えるってことは食べる』、これが同じというのかね！」

「ほかにも、」と付け加えるヤヨイウサギ、「『ものになるってことは好きだ』と『好きだってことはものになる』、これも同じか！」

「まだまだ、」と口をはさむヤマネは、ねごとでも言っているかのようで、「『ねむれるってことは息がある』と『息があるってことはねむれる』、これも同じですか？」

「おまえのはおんなじだ。」とぼうし屋、ここでおしゃべりはとぎれて、ものどもみんなしばしだんまり、そのあいだにアリスはカラスや机ののことをできるだけ思い出してみたけど、大したこともなくって。

そのだんまりをはじめにやぶったのは、ぼうし屋でね。「今日は何日かね。」とアリスの方を向く。ポケットから時計を取り出して、それをまじまじ、時おりたびたびゆすぶって、耳に当ててみたり。

アリスはちょっと考えたあと、「４日。」

「２日くるっておる！」とぼうし屋はため息。「言ったろ、時計のからくりにバターは合わんと！」とそのあと、いかりの目を向けられるヤヨイウサギ。

「最高級のバターだぜ。」と答えるヤヨイウサギはどうにも弱ごし。

「ああ、だがパンくずがまじったにちがいない、」とグチるぼうし屋、「またぞろパン切りナイフなんぞ使うからだ。」

ヤヨイウサギはその時計を取って、しぶっ面でまじまじ、そのあとカップのお茶にひたしてまたまじまじ、ところがさっきの言葉よりいい言葉が思いつかないのか、「最高級のバターだったのに、ほれ。」

アリスはなにやらわくわくしながら、かたごしにまじまじ。「面白い時計だこと！」と口に出してね。「時をつけずに日をつげるなんて！」

「何を言うか。」とこぼすぼうし屋。「きみの時計は年をつげたりせんだろ？」

「当たり前。」とアリスはにべもない。「だってそれだと１年間ずっと同じじゃないの。」

「それはこちらのとて同じこと。」とぼうし屋。

アリスはひどくもやもやした気持ちになってね、ぼうし屋の言い分は返事になってないように思えたんだけど、それでもたしかに言葉にはなっていて。「おっしゃること、よくわからないんですけど。」とできるだけていねいに言い返す。

「ヤマネがまたいねむりしておる。」と言いながらぼうし屋は、熱めのお茶を相手の鼻にかけてね。

ヤマネはしんぼうたまらんと頭をふって目も開けずに、「もちろんもちろんまさにそれを言おうとしていたんです。」

「さっきのなぞかけはもうわかったかね？」と言いつつぼうし屋はまたアリスの方を向く。

「いいえお手上げ。」というのがアリスのお返事。「答えは何？」

「これっぽちもわからん。」とぼうし屋。

「おれも。」とヤヨイウサギ。

アリスはやれやれとため息。「もっとましなことができてよ、」と言うしかない、「そんな答えのないなぞかけで時間をつぶすだなんて。」

「わがはいくらい時間どのとお近づきになれば、」とぼうし屋、「 よびすてでつぶすだなんて言いはせん。どのをつけろ。」

「あなた何をおっしゃってるやらさっぱり。」とアリス。

「ああそうだろうとも！」と、ぼうし屋はさげすむようにあごを上げてね、「なんならきみは時間どのと口をきいたこともないからな！」

「まあね、」とアリスはおそるおそるお返事、「でもせわしないときには時間をさいたりしてよ。」

「おお！　だからか。」とぼうし屋。「時間どのはさかれるのがおきらいだ。なかよくなりさえすれば、時計のことはだいたいよろしくしてくださる。たとえば朝の９時だとしよう、ちょうどおけいこの始まる時間、ならばきみは時間どのにほんのちょっとささやくだけでいい、くるくると時間がまたたくまに回る！　１時半、ごちそうの時間だ！」

（「そうなりゃどんなにいいか。」とヤヨイウサギはぼそぼそひとりごと。）

「それはそれはけっこうだこと、」とアリスはあいづち、「でもそれじゃあ――おなかが空かないんじゃなくて、ほら。」

「はじめのうちは、おそらく。」とぼうし屋。「だが好きなだけ１時半にとどめおくことができる。」

「で、そうしてるのね、あなたは？」とたずねるアリス。

ぼうし屋はやるせなく首をふる。「いいや！」との答え。「先の３月にけんかをしてな……おまえがおかしくなる直前のことだ、ほれ……」（とティースプーンでヤヨイウサギを指し示してね）「……あれはハートのクイーンがもよおした大音楽会でのこと。わがはいは歌をうたう役でな。

『てかてか　ひかる
やみの　こうもり』

この歌は知ってるかね？」

「聞いたことあってよ、なにかそんな歌。」とアリス。

「では引き続き、ほれ、」と続けるぼうし屋、「このように――

『ひらひら　とぶよ
おぼんのように
てかてか……』」

ここでヤマネは身をふるふる、ねむったままうたいだしてね、「 てかてか てかてか ……」とあまりに長々続けるので、ふたりがつねってやめさせた。

「まあこのふしをうたいきらんうちに、」とぼうし屋、「クイーンさまはどなりなさる、『時間のむだっ！　首をちょん切れ！』」

「おそるるに足る話ね！」と声をはりあげるアリス。

「そうして時間どのをむだ死にさせて以後、」とおくやみとばかりのぼうし屋、「たのみごとを聞いてくれんようになった！　今もずっと６時のままだ。」

ぱっとアリスの頭にひらめきが。「そのせいで、こんなにたくさんティーセットが置かれてあるのね？」とたしかめる。

「ご名答。」とため息をつくぼうし屋。「いつもお茶の時間なのだ、あいまに洗いものをする時間もない。」

「ということは、ぐるりとずれていくってわけ？」とアリス。

「さよう、」とぼうし屋、「どんどん使ってゆく。」

「でも１周しちゃったらいったいどうなるの？」とアリスはふみこんでみる。

「話を変えようや。」とわりこむヤヨイウサギ、あくびをしてね。「あきてきた。そこでどうだ、このじょうちゃんにお話をしてもらうってのは。」

「め、めっそうもなくてよ。」とアリスはいきなりの申し出にちょっとあたふた。

「ならヤマネにさせよう！」とふたりは声をはりあげる。「起きろ、ヤマネ！」そうして両がわからいきなりつねってね。

ヤマネはゆっくり目を開いて。「ねてませんよ、」と弱々かすれ声、「みんなの言うことは一言一句聞こえてましたよ。」

「話をしろ！」とヤヨイウサギ。

「ええ、よろしく！」とおねがいするアリス。

「さあさっさとしろ、」とせっつくぼうし屋、「さもないと話が終わるより先にこいつまたねてしまうぞ。」

「昔々あるところに３人のかわいい姉妹がおりました。」とヤマネは大あわてではじめてね、「名前はエルシー、レイシー、ティリー。３人は井戸の底に住んでおり……」

「食べるものはあって？」とアリスは飲み食いのことにかかってはいつもきょうみしんしん。

「シロップを食べています。」とヤマネが言えたのは、ものの数分考えた末。

「そんなの無理よ、ほら。」と言うアリスの口ぶりはやさしげ。「病気になってしまってよ。」

「だから３人は、」とヤマネ、「もちろん病気に。」

アリスはちょっと思いうかべてみてね、そんなとてつもないくらしを、でもあんまりにももやもやしてきて、そこでこう引き取る、「でも井戸の底に住んでいるのはなぜかしら？」

「もう１ぱいどうだ。」とヤヨイウサギがアリスにいう口ぶりはたいへん熱心。

「まだ何もいただいてなくてよ。」と気を悪くしたアリスが返す、「だからもう１ぱいだなんて無理。」

「では１ぱいも飲めないということか。」とぼうし屋、「ゼロ足す１で１ぱい目だからな。」

「あなたは口をはさまないで。」とアリス。

「ひとに口出ししているのは、きみではないのか！」と問いつめるぼうし屋は得意満面とくいまんめん。

アリスは何と言い返してよいのかさっぱりだったので、自分でお茶とパンを取ってから、ヤマネに向き直って、また同じおうかがい。「井戸の底に住んでいるのはなぜかしら？」

ヤマネのまたものの数分かけて考えた末に口から出た答えは、「シロップの井戸ですから。」

「そんなのありえない！」とぷんすかしだすアリスに、ぼうし屋とヤヨイウサギは「しっ、しーっ。」とやってね、むすっとしながらヤマネはこう言う、「おぎょうぎよくできないのならお話のオチは勝手にすればいいです。」

「おねがい、続けて！」ととても素直になるアリス。「もう口をはさんだりしないから。そんなのひとつくらいはあるかも。」

「ひとつも、ですと！」とヤマネはぷんすか。だけどしぶしぶ続ける。「なのでその３人の姉妹は――かきわける練習をしていました、ほら……」

「かきわけるって何を？」とアリスはさっきの 約束 もまったくどこへやら。

「シロップです。」と今度のヤマネはちっとも考えずにお答え。

「きれいなカップがほしい。」とぼうし屋が口をはさむ。「さあ、みなのもの、席をひとつずらそう。」

言いながら席をずらして、それにヤマネも続いてね、ヤヨイウサギはヤマネのいたところに、そしてアリスもしぶしぶヤヨイウサギのすわっていた席へ。席がえで得したのはぼうし屋ただひとり。そしてアリスは前よりかなり悪くなったのだけど、それというのもヤヨイウサギがさっきミルク入れをお皿にひっくり返していたから。

アリスはもうヤマネをおこらせたくなかったので、おそるおそる切り出した。「でもわからなくてよ。井戸でどうシロップをかきわけるの？」

「プールでなら水をかきわける。」とぼうし屋。「シロップの井戸ならシロップをかきわける――当たり前だ、バカ者。」

「でも底はせまくってよ。」とヤマネにたずねるアリス、終わりの言葉は聞かんぷり。

「もちろんせまい。」とヤマネ。「だから そこそこに。」

かわいそうにこのお答えのせいでアリスの頭はハテナだらけ、なので食い下がらずにしばらくそのままヤマネに話を続けさせてね。

「３人はかきわけるおけいこ中、」と続けるヤマネはあくびをして目をこすっていてね、どんどんねむくなっていたんだ、「いろんなものをかきわけます――『お』で始まるあらゆるものをかきわけるのです……」

「どうして『お』なの？」とアリス。

「いけねえのか？」とヤヨイウサギ。

アリスはだんまり。

もうこのときヤマネは目をとじてしまっていて、うとうとしていたのに、ぼうし屋につねられ、ひゃっと小さく声を上げてまた目をぱちくり、そして話の続き。「……『お』で始まるものです。たとえば、おとりとか、お月さまとか、思い出とか、おっちょことか――ほら言うでしょ、『おっちょこちょい』って――見たことありますか、『おっちょこ』をちょいとかきわけた絵というのを。」

「そんないきなり聞かれても。」とアリスの頭はハテナだらけ、「ないと……」

「ならば口を出すでない。」とぼうし屋。

この無礼な物言いにアリスもがまんの 限界 、ほとほとうんざりして席を立ち、歩き出してね。ヤマネはたちまちねむりこんでしまって、ほかのふたりもその子が去ろうともちっとも気にせず、その子はちらちらとふり返って、よび止めてくれるかなとどこかで思ってたんだけどね、最後に目にうつったのはふたりがヤマネをティーポットにおしこもうとしているところ。

「もうこんりんざいこんなとこには来なくってよ！」とアリスは森をかきわけつき進んでいってね、「生まれてこのかたこんなバカバカしいお茶会はじめて！」

こんなことを言っているうちに、ふと目についた一本の木、そこに何やらなかへと続くドアがついていて。「まあ、へんてこりん！」とアリスは思ってね、「でも今日はみんなへんてこりん。だからいきなり入ってもたぶんまあよろしくてよ。」というわけで、なかへお立ち入り。

すると気づけばまたもや大広間、そばには小さなガラスのテーブル。「さあて今度こそうまくやってみせてよ。」とひとりごと、まずはちっちゃな金の 鍵 を手にとって、庭へ続くドアを開ける。それから手をつけるのがキノコ（まだかけらをポケットに残してあったからね）、かじっていって最後は３０センチくらいの背たけに。そのあと短いろうかをぬけていって、そしてお次は――気づいたらとうとうきらびやかなお庭だ、あたりにはきらめく 花園 、すずしげな 泉 だ。

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1
Chapter 2
Chapter 3
Chapter 4
Chapter 5
Chapter 6
Chapter 7
Chapter 8
Chapter 9
Chapter 10
Chapter 11
Chapter 12

Chapter 8

Click a checkbox to toggle a feature on or off in the text.

Cultural

Incorrect Word Usage

Nonsense Words

Onomatopoeia

Play on Words

Repetition

The Queen’s Croquet-Ground

A large rose-tree stood near the entrance of the garden: the roses growing on it were white, but there were three gardeners at it, busily painting them red. Alice thought this a very curious thing, and she went nearer to watch them, and just as she came up to them she heard one of them say, ‘Look out now, Five! Don’t go splashing paint over me like that!’

‘I couldn’t help it,’ said Five, in a sulky tone; ‘Seven jogged my elbow.’

On which Seven looked up and said, ‘That’s right, Five! Always lay the blame on others!’

‘YOU’D better not talk!’ said Five. ‘I heard the Queen say only yesterday you deserved to be beheaded!’

‘What for?’ said the one who had spoken first.

‘That’s none of YOUR business, Two!’ said Seven.

‘Yes, it IS his business!’ said Five, ‘and I’ll tell him--it was for bringing the cook tulip-roots instead of onions.’

Seven flung down his brush, and had just begun ‘Well, of all the unjust things--’ when his eye chanced to fall upon Alice, as she stood watching them, and he checked himself suddenly: the others looked round also, and all of them bowed low.

‘Would you tell me,’ said Alice, a little timidly, ‘why you are painting those roses?’

Five and Seven said nothing, but looked at Two. Two began in a low voice, ‘Why the fact is, you see, Miss, this here ought to have been a RED rose-tree, and we put a white one in by mistake; and if the Queen was to find it out, we should all have our heads cut off, you know. So you see, Miss, we’re doing our best, afore she comes, to--’ At this moment Five, who had been anxiously looking across the garden, called out ‘The Queen! The Queen!’ and the three gardeners instantly threw themselves flat upon their faces. There was a sound of many footsteps, and Alice looked round, eager to see the Queen.

First came ten soldiers carrying clubs; these were all shaped like the three gardeners, oblong and flat, with their hands and feet at the corners: next the ten courtiers; these were ornamented all over with diamonds, and walked two and two, as the soldiers did. After these came the royal children; there were ten of them, and the little dears came jumping merrily along hand in hand, in couples: they were all ornamented with hearts. Next came the guests, mostly Kings and Queens, and among them Alice recognised the White Rabbit: it was talking in a hurried nervous manner, smiling at everything that was said, and went by without noticing her. Then followed the Knave of Hearts, carrying the King’s crown on a crimson velvet cushion; and, last of all this grand procession, came THE KING AND QUEEN OF HEARTS.

Alice was rather doubtful whether she ought not to lie down on her face like the three gardeners, but she could not remember ever having heard of such a rule at processions; ‘and besides, what would be the use of a procession,’ thought she, ‘if people had all to lie down upon their faces, so that they couldn’t see it?’ So she stood still where she was, and waited.

When the procession came opposite to Alice, they all stopped and looked at her, and the Queen said severely ‘Who is this?’ She said it to the Knave of Hearts, who only bowed and smiled in reply.

‘Idiot!’ said the Queen, tossing her head impatiently; and, turning to Alice, she went on, ‘What’s your name, child?’

‘My name is Alice, so please your Majesty,’ said Alice very politely; but she added, to herself, ‘Why, they’re only a pack of cards, after all. I needn’t be afraid of them!’

‘And who are THESE?’ said the Queen, pointing to the three gardeners who were lying round the rosetree; for, you see, as they were lying on their faces, and the pattern on their backs was the same as the rest of the pack, she could not tell whether they were gardeners, or soldiers, or courtiers, or three of her own children.

‘How should I know?’ said Alice, surprised at her own courage. ‘It’s no business of MINE.’

The Queen turned crimson with fury, and, after glaring at her for a moment like a wild beast, screamed ‘Off with her head! Off--’

‘Nonsense!’ said Alice, very loudly and decidedly, and the Queen was silent.

The King laid his hand upon her arm, and timidly said ‘Consider, my dear: she is only a child!’

The Queen turned angrily away from him, and said to the Knave ‘Turn them over!’

The Knave did so, very carefully, with one foot.

‘Get up!’ said the Queen, in a shrill, loud voice, and the three gardeners instantly jumped up, and began bowing to the King, the Queen, the royal children, and everybody else.

‘Leave off that!’ screamed the Queen. ‘You make me giddy.’ And then, turning to the rose-tree, she went on, ‘What HAVE you been doing here?’

‘May it please your Majesty,’ said Two, in a very humble tone, going down on one knee as he spoke, ‘we were trying--’

‘I see!’ said the Queen, who had meanwhile been examining the roses. ‘Off with their heads!’ and the procession moved on, three of the soldiers remaining behind to execute the unfortunate gardeners, who ran to Alice for protection.

‘You shan’t be beheaded!’ said Alice, and she put them into a large flower-pot that stood near. The three soldiers wandered about for a minute or two, looking for them, and then quietly marched off after the others.

‘Are their heads off?’ shouted the Queen.

‘Their heads are gone, if it please your Majesty!’ the soldiers shouted in reply.

‘That’s right!’ shouted the Queen. ‘Can you play croquet?’

The soldiers were silent, and looked at Alice, as the question was evidently meant for her.

‘Yes!’ shouted Alice.

‘Come on, then!’ roared the Queen, and Alice joined the procession, wondering very much what would happen next.

‘It’s--it’s a very fine day!’ said a timid voice at her side. She was walking by the White Rabbit, who was peeping anxiously into her face.

‘Very,’ said Alice: ‘--where’s the Duchess?’

‘Hush! Hush!’ said the Rabbit in a low, hurried tone. He looked anxiously over his shoulder as he spoke, and then raised himself upon tiptoe, put his mouth close to her ear, and whispered ‘She’s under sentence of execution.’

‘What for?’ said Alice.

‘Did you say “What a pity!”?’ the Rabbit asked.

‘No, I didn’t,’ said Alice: ‘I don’t think it’s at all a pity. I said “What for?”’

‘She boxed the Queen’s ears--’ the Rabbit began. Alice gave a little scream of laughter. ‘Oh, hush!’ the Rabbit whispered in a frightened tone. ‘The Queen will hear you! You see, she came rather late, and the Queen said--’

‘Get to your places!’ shouted the Queen in a voice of thunder, and people began running about in all directions, tumbling up against each other; however, they got settled down in a minute or two, and the game began.

Alice thought she had never seen such a curious croquet-ground in her life; it was all ridges and furrows; the balls were live hedgehogs, the mallets live flamingoes, and the soldiers had to double themselves up and to stand on their hands and feet, to make the arches.

The chief difficulty Alice found at first was in managing her flamingo: she succeeded in getting its body tucked away, comfortably enough, under her arm, with its legs hanging down, but generally, just as she had got its neck nicely straightened out, and was going to give the hedgehog a blow with its head, it WOULD twist itself round and look up in her face, with such a puzzled expression that she could not help bursting out laughing: and when she had got its head down, and was going to begin again, it was very provoking to find that the hedgehog had unrolled itself, and was in the act of crawling away: besides all this, there was generally a ridge or furrow in the way wherever she wanted to send the hedgehog to, and, as the doubled-up soldiers were always getting up and walking off to other parts of the ground, Alice soon came to the conclusion that it was a very difficult game indeed.

The players all played at once without waiting for turns, quarrelling all the while, and fighting for the hedgehogs; and in a very short time the Queen was in a furious passion, and went stamping about, and shouting ‘Off with his head!’ or ‘Off with her head!’ about once in a minute.

Alice began to feel very uneasy: to be sure, she had not as yet had any dispute with the Queen, but she knew that it might happen any minute, ‘and then,’ thought she, ‘what would become of me? They’re dreadfully fond of beheading people here; the great wonder is, that there’s any one left alive!’

She was looking about for some way of escape, and wondering whether she could get away without being seen, when she noticed a curious appearance in the air: it puzzled her very much at first, but, after watching it a minute or two, she made it out to be a grin, and she said to herself ‘It’s the Cheshire Cat: now I shall have somebody to talk to.’

‘How are you getting on?’ said the Cat, as soon as there was mouth enough for it to speak with.

Alice waited till the eyes appeared, and then nodded. ‘It’s no use speaking to it,’ she thought, ‘till its ears have come, or at least one of them.’ In another minute the whole head appeared, and then Alice put down her flamingo, and began an account of the game, feeling very glad she had someone to listen to her. The Cat seemed to think that there was enough of it now in sight, and no more of it appeared.

‘I don’t think they play at all fairly,’ Alice began, in rather a complaining tone, ‘and they all quarrel so dreadfully one can’t hear oneself speak--and they don’t seem to have any rules in particular; at least, if there are, nobody attends to them--and you’ve no idea how confusing it is all the things being alive; for instance, there’s the arch I’ve got to go through next walking about at the other end of the ground--and I should have croqueted the Queen’s hedgehog just now, only it ran away when it saw mine coming!’

‘How do you like the Queen?’ said the Cat in a low voice.

‘Not at all,’ said Alice: ‘she’s so extremely--’ Just then she noticed that the Queen was close behind her, listening: so she went on, ‘--likely to win, that it’s hardly worth while finishing the game.’

The Queen smiled and passed on.

‘Who ARE you talking to?’ said the King, going up to Alice, and looking at the Cat’s head with great curiosity.

‘It’s a friend of mine--a Cheshire Cat,’ said Alice: ‘allow me to introduce it.’

‘I don’t like the look of it at all,’ said the King: ‘however, it may kiss my hand if it likes.’

‘I’d rather not,’ the Cat remarked.

‘Don’t be impertinent,’ said the King, ‘and don’t look at me like that!’ He got behind Alice as he spoke.

‘A cat may look at a king,’ said Alice. ‘I’ve read that in some book, but I don’t remember where.’

‘Well, it must be removed,’ said the King very decidedly, and he called the Queen, who was passing at the moment, ‘My dear! I wish you would have this cat removed!’

The Queen had only one way of settling all difficulties, great or small. ‘Off with his head!’ she said, without even looking round.

‘I’ll fetch the executioner myself,’ said the King eagerly, and he hurried off.

Alice thought she might as well go back, and see how the game was going on, as she heard the Queen’s voice in the distance, screaming with passion. She had already heard her sentence three of the players to be executed for having missed their turns, and she did not like the look of things at all, as the game was in such confusion that she never knew whether it was her turn or not. So she went in search of her hedgehog.

The hedgehog was engaged in a fight with another hedgehog, which seemed to Alice an excellent opportunity for croqueting one of them with the other: the only difficulty was, that her flamingo was gone across to the other side of the garden, where Alice could see it trying in a helpless sort of way to fly up into a tree.

By the time she had caught the flamingo and brought it back, the fight was over, and both the hedgehogs were out of sight: ‘but it doesn’t matter much,’ thought Alice, ‘as all the arches are gone from this side of the ground.’ So she tucked it away under her arm, that it might not escape again, and went back for a little more conversation with her friend.

When she got back to the Cheshire Cat, she was surprised to find quite a large crowd collected round it: there was a dispute going on between the executioner, the King, and the Queen, who were all talking at once, while all the rest were quite silent, and looked very uncomfortable.

The moment Alice appeared, she was appealed to by all three to settle the question, and they repeated their arguments to her, though, as they all spoke at once, she found it very hard indeed to make out exactly what they said.

The executioner’s argument was, that you couldn’t cut off a head unless there was a body to cut it off from: that he had never had to do such a thing before, and he wasn’t going to begin at HIS time of life.

The King’s argument was, that anything that had a head could be beheaded, and that you weren’t to talk nonsense.

The Queen’s argument was, that if something wasn’t done about it in less than no time she’d have everybody executed, all round. (It was this last remark that had made the whole party look so grave and anxious.)

Alice could think of nothing else to say but ‘It belongs to the Duchess: you’d better ask HER about it.’

‘She’s in prison,’ the Queen said to the executioner: ‘fetch her here.’ And the executioner went off like an arrow.

The Cat’s head began fading away the moment he was gone, and, by the time he had come back with the Duchess, it had entirely disappeared; so the King and the executioner ran wildly up and down looking for it, while the rest of the party went back to the game.

クイーンさまのクローケー場

大きなバラの木が１本、庭を入ったところに立っていて、さいてるバラはどれも白なのに、その場にいた３まいの庭係が、いそいそとそいつを赤にぬっていてね。これがアリスにはすごくへんてこなことに思えたものだから、そばでじっくり見ようと足を向けると、近づくなり聞こえてくる、うちひとりの言葉、「おい気ぃつけろよ、５！　そんなふうにこっちへ絵の具をはねかけんな、こら！」

「しょうがねえだろ。」と５はむっとした声を返す、「７がこっちのひじを小づきやがった。」

それに７も見上げて口をはさむ、「やんのか、５！　いつもいつもひとのせいにしやがって！」

「てめえ言ってるばあいかよ！」と５。「聞いたぜつい昨日、クインのやつがてめえは打ち首ものだっつってな！」

「ワケは？」と口火を切ったやつ。

「てめえの知ったこっちゃねえだろ、２！」と７。

「いいや、知ったこっちゃあるんだな！」と５、「だから教えてやんよ――ワケってのはタマネギとまちがえてチューリップの根っこを料理係に持ってったってな！」

７はハケを放り出してまくし立てる、「はあ！　そんなおかどちげえ――」とここでたまたま目にうつるアリス、じーっとのぞきこんでいたから向こうはふいに言葉をつまらせてね。ほかの２まいもふり返り、みんなしてふかぶかおじぎ。

「教えていただけて？」とアリスはちょっぴりおずおず、「どうしてバラに色なんかつけてらして？」

５と７はおしだまって２をにらむだけ。そこで２が小声で、「その何だ、実はさ、ほら、じょうちゃん、本当はこいつ赤いバラの木のはずだったんだけど、手ちがいでオレら白いのを植えちまってさ、クインに見つかるはめにでもあったら、もうオレらみんなそろって首切られるってワケよ。つーわけでさ、じょうちゃん、来ないうちにやれることやっとこ――」と、まさにこのとき、庭の向こうをそわそわと見つめていた５が声をあげる、「クインのやつだ！　クインだ！」庭係の３まいはあわててぺたんとうつぶせにたおれる。おおぜいの足音にふり返ったアリスは、当のクイーンにじいっと目をそそぐ。

まずやってきたのが、こんぼうをかまえた１０まいの 強者 たち、すがた形は庭係３まいと同じで、長四角のぺらぺら、角のところに手足がついててね。お次は１０まいのそばづかえ、ダイヤにそろって色取られ、強者と同じで２列になって歩いている。そのあとに来るのが王子さま王女さま、１０まいいらっしゃて、このかわい子ちゃんたち２人１組で手をつないで、うきうき軽やかに進む、そろってハートがらのおあしらい。次に来るのがお歴々、キングにクイーンがほとんどだけど、そこでそのなかにアリスはあの白ウサギを見つけてね、でもせかせかとお話しながら言われたことにはあいそ笑いするばかりで、気づかずに前を通り過ぎて。そのあと続くのがハートのジャック、おしいだいたるふわふわ てかてかまっ赤な台の上にはキングのかんむり、そしてこの大ねり歩きのとりをかざるのが、ハートのキングとクイーンだ。

アリスには、自分もその庭係３まいと同じようにひれふした方がいいのかちょっとはっきりしなかったけど、ねり歩きにそんな決まりがあるとも耳にしたこともなかったので、「それに、ねり歩きにいったい何のねうちがあって？」と思ってね、「ひれふして顔を下向きにしたら、どのみち見えないもの。」だからその場に立ったままじっとしていた。

ねり歩きはアリスのまん前まで来ると、そろって立ち止まって目を向けてくる、そこでクイーンが一言ぴしゃり、「こやつはだれよの。」たずね先はハートのジャック、だけど返ってくるのはおじぎとにこにこだけ。

「バカ者！」とクイーンは、頭をつーんとそらして、そのあとアリスの方をむいてさらにひとこと、「そこな子ども、名は何と言う？」

「あたくしの名前はアリスです、クイーンさま。」とアリスはうやうやしく受け答え、でも実は心のなかでは、「ふん、どうせただのトランプ１組。おそるるに足らずよ！」

「ではあれは何よの。」とクイーンが指さしたのは、バラの木のまわりにたおれている３まいの庭係、だってうつぶせになっていたし、背中のがらはどのトランプもおんなじだから、そこにいるのが庭係なのか、強者、そばづかえ、はたまた自分の子どもたちなのか、さっぱりでね。

「あたくしに聞かないで。」と言うアリス、その気の強さに自分でもびっくり。「知ったこっちゃなくてよ。」

怒 りで真っ赤になるクイーン、ちらっとにらみつけてから、やにわにけだものよろしくいきなり声をあらげて、「こやつの首をちょん切れ！　こやつの……」

「すっからかん！」とアリスが大声で言ってのけると、クイーンは静かに。

キングがその手をクイーンのうでに置いて、おずおず言い出す、「これお前、考え直さんか。ほんの子どもだ！」

クイーンはぷいっと顔をそむけて、ジャックに言いつける、「こやつらひっくり返せ！」

ジャックは、そうろっと片足でやってのけた。

「立てい！」とクイーンがきぃきぃ大声をあげると、３まいの庭係はたちまちとび起き、おじぎを始めてね、キングにクイーン、王子王女にみなみなさまへ。

「ええいやめい！」とかなきり声のクイーン、「目が回る。」とそこでバラの木の方を向いて続ける、「ここで今まで何をしておった？」

「おそれながらクイーンさま。」とへりくだるふりして２は、しゃべるあいだ片ひざをついて、「なんとか３まいで――」

「もうわかった！」と、そのあいだにバラをたしかめていたクイーンは、「こやつらの首をちょん切れ！」そしてねり歩きは動き出し、 処 すための強者が３まい、あとに残されたので、追いつめられた庭係はアリスにかけよって助けを求める。

「打ち首なんかさせなくってよ！」って、アリスは３まいともを手近の大きな植木ばちにつっこんでね。だから３まいの強者は、ものの数分うろうろとさがしただけで、あとはみんなの後を追ってすたすたすた。

「首はのうなったかえ？」とクイーンの大声。

「みな首なしにてございまする、クイーンさま！」と強者の返事も大声。

「よろしい！」とクイーンの大声、「そちはクローケーができるか？」

おしだまった強者ども、目を向ける先はアリス、つまりどうも、聞かれてるよってことみたいで。

「はいっ！」とアリスの大声。

「ならばこちへ！」と声をひびかせるクイーン、ねり歩きの仲間になったアリスは、これから何が始まるのか気になる気になる。

「これ――よいお日がらであるな！」とわきからおずおずひと声。なんととなりを歩いていたのはあの白ウサギ、こわごわ顔をのぞかれていてね。

「本当に。」とアリス、「 御前 さまはどちら？」

「しっ！　しーっ！」とひそひそ早口で返すウサギ、話しているあいだもそわそわ後ろをふりかえりながら、やがてつま先立ちして小さく耳打ち、「御前さまは処けいを言いわたされておじゃる。」

「どうして？」とアリス。

「どうしてなかなかおいたわしやとな?!」と聞き返すウサギ。

「そうじゃなくて。」とアリス。「悲しいとかじゃなくて、わけを聞いてるの。」

「クイーンさまにびんたをはったのじゃよ――」と言い出すウサギ。アリスはぷぷっとふきだして。「これ、しーっ！」とウサギはびくびく ひそひそ声。「クイーンさまに聞こえるでおじゃる！　ほれ、あの方がちょっとちこくされたもんで、クイーンさまがな――」

「ものども 位置 につけい！」と大声をとどろかせるクイーン、一同はてんでばらばらに走り出して、たがいにごっつんこ。けれどもものの数分で位置につきおわって、すぐに試合が始まったんだ。

アリスは思った、生まれてこのかたこんなへんてこなクローケー場見たことないって。そこらじゅうが凸凹で。玉は生きたハリネズミだし、ボールを打つつちは生きたフラミンゴ、それに強者どもがわざわざ両手両足をついて身体を２つ折り、玉のくぐるところをつくってね。

なかでもいちばんむつかしいってアリスがまず気づいたのが、フラミンゴのあつかい。なんとかうまくそいつのどう体を、おさまりのいいよう、わきにおしこんで、足をぶらぶらさせてみたんだけど、たいていは、首をうまくまっすぐにして頭でハリネズミを打とうとしたとたん、そいつに身体をひねられ顔をのぞきこまれてね、相手があまりにこまった顔をするもんだから、ぷっとふきだしちゃうしかなくって。それから頭を下向きにしてしきりなおしても、今度はハリネズミが丸まってくれずにちょろちょろどっか行き出すもんだから、いらだたしいったらなくて。ましてやそれどころか、ハリネズミをどこへ転がしたいにしても、たいてい行く先には凸か凹、それに２つ折りの強者どもはしじゅう起き上がってべつのところへ歩いていっちゃうから、アリスもたちまち、この試合むつかしすぎると思うにいたる。

やってる人も自分の番を待たずにみんないっせいにやるし、ずーっと大声で言い合い、ハリネズミの取り合い。なのであっというまにクイーンは 怒 りばくはつ、どしんどしん歩いていって、「あの男の首をちょん切れ！」とか「あの女の首をちょん切れ！」ってどなること１分に１回。

アリスはどうにも気もそぞろ、たしかにまだクイーンとは１度も口げんかしてなかったけど、いつ起こるともしれないから、「そうなったとき、」とアリスは考える、「あたくしの身はどうなるの？　このひとたち、ここにいるひとたちを打ち首にしたくてしたくて仕方ないみたい。こんな調子で、だれかひとりでも生き残れたものかしら！」

にげのびる手立てをさがしながら、すがたを見られずに立ち去れるのかしらと思っていたところ、気づけばお空のなかにぱっとへんてこなものが登場。はじめは何がなにやらわけがわからなかったけど、ものの数分もながめていると、そいつが 愛想 だとわかってきたので、ひとりごと、「これはチェシアのネコね。やっと話し相手ができてよ。」

「うまくやってるかにゃ？」とネコは、話せるだけの口が出たとたんに言ってね。

アリスはお目々が出てくるまで待ってから、うなづく。「まだ話しかけてもむだ。」と思ってね、「あの子の耳が、せめて片方でも出てから。」１分もすると頭がまるまるあらわれたので、それからアリスは持ってたフラミンゴを下ろして、ゲームのことをかくかくしかじか、聞いてくれる相手ができて、もううれしくってね。ネコはそれだけ見えればじゅうぶんと思ったらしく、そこから先は出てこない。

「あのひとたち、たぶんまともにゲームできていなくてよ。」と言い出すアリスの口ぶりはちょっぴり 不満 たらたらでね、「それにみんなひどくさわぎ立てるものだから自分が何言ってるかもわからなくって――それにルールにちっともこだわらないみたいで。どうせあったとしても、だれも耳なんかかさないし――それにもうわけがわからないのが、何から何まで生き物だってこと。たとえば、次に通さなきゃいけないゲートがあっても、そいつはグラウンドのはしっこまでてくてく歩いて行っちゃうし――あたくしがクイーンさまのハリネズミに当て打ちしようとしたら、そいつはあたくしが来たのを目にしてにげていっちゃうんだもん！」

「クイーンはどうにゃい？」と小声のネコ。

「もうだめ。」とアリス、「だってめちゃくちゃ――」とちょうどそこでクイーンが背後で聞いているのに気がついて、言葉の先がこんなふうに、「――お強いんだもの、もうゲームなんてやってられないって気持ちね。」

クイーンはにっこりと笑って通りすぎる。

「だれと話しておる？」とキングがアリスにお近づき、ものめずらしそうにネコの頭を見つめてね。

「お友だちの――チェシアのネコです。」とアリス。「どうぞよしなに。」

「 面 がまったく気に食わん。」とキング。「だがのぞみとあらば、わが手に口づけしてもよいぞ。」

「べーつにぃ。」と答えるネコ。

「こらえしょうのないやつめ、」とキング、「そのような目でわしを見おって！」と言いつつアリスの後ろにかくれてね。

「ネコでも王さまが見られる。」とアリス。「そう読んだ本にも書いてあってよ、でも何だったかしらん。」

「むう、やつを追いはらわねば。」と言い切ったキングは、そのとき通りがかったクイーンに声をかけて、「おまえ、あのネコを追っぱらってはくれまいか。」

クイーンは大小問わず、やっかいごとおさめるときにはこれしかない、「こやつの首をちょん切れ！」と、あたりに目をやることもなく言う。

「処けい人をじきじきに連れてこようぞ。」とやる気まんまんのキングはいそいそその場を外す。

アリスは自分ももどってゲームのゆくえを見守った方がいいかなと思ったんだけど、そのあいだもクイーンの声が遠くから聞こえてね、心のままにさけんでいて。やってる人でも、もう３人が打つ順をまちがえたってことで処けいを言いわたされたのを耳にしていたし、自分としてもこんなありさま見てられないと思ってね、だってゲームは自分の番かどうかもわからないくらいしっちゃかめっちゃかなんだから。なのでとりあえず自分のハリネズミをさがしに。

ハリネズミはほかのハリネズミと取っ組み合いのけんかをしていて、今ならそのふたつをうまい具合に当て打ちできるとアリスは思ったんだけど、ただこまったことに、自分のフラミンゴが遠く庭のはしっこまで行ってしまっていてね、アリスの目には、そいつが木のひとつにとびうつろうと、むだなあがきをしているのが見えて。

つかまえたフラミンゴをかかえてもどってくるころには、けんかもお開き、ハリネズミは２ひきともすがたがなくってね。「もうどうでもよくてよ。」と思うアリス、「ゲートもみんなグラウンドのこっちがわにはいなくなってることだし。」そこでにがさないよう、そいつをわきにぎゅっとかかえて、お友だちともうちょっとお話でもと引き返していく。

チェシアのネコのところへもどると、びっくりしたのが気づけばまわりに人だかりができてたってこと。それになんと処けい人とキングとクイーンとのあいだでいざこざが起きていてね、いちどきにみんなしゃべるものだから、そのあいだその場にいるものはまったくおしだまるだけで、なんとも気まずそうで。

アリスがあらわれたとたん、その３人には助けの船みたいにうつったのか、その子に向かってそれぞれの言い分をくりかえすんだけど、やっぱりいちどきに言うものだから、だれが何を言ってるのかはっきり聞き取ろうにも本当にややこしくって。

処けい人の言い分は、切りはなす身体もないのに首は切れないということ、それからそんなことこれまでしたこともないし、今さらこの年でやってみる気もないとのこと。

キングの言い分は、頭のあるものは打ち首にできるはず、たわけた話を言うなというもの。

クイーンの言い分は、今すぐさまただちに手が下されないのであれば、だれかれかまわずみな処すというもの。（この言葉が決め手となって、その場の一同どうにもみなざわざわ。）

アリスにはもうこう言うしかないと思えてね、「ネコのかい主は御前さまです。その方にうかがうのがよろしいかと。」

「あやつはオリのなかじゃ。」とクイーンは処けい人に言ってね。「ここへ連れてこい。」すると処けい人はひょうふっと走り去る。

ネコの頭はそのとたんに消えだして、御前さまを連れてもどってきたときにはもう、まったくいなくなっていてね。そこでキングと処けい人はむやみやたらにそこらをさがしまわるんだけど、そのうちその場のみんなもゲームにもどっていっちゃった。

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1
Chapter 2
Chapter 3
Chapter 4
Chapter 5
Chapter 6
Chapter 7
Chapter 8
Chapter 9
Chapter 10
Chapter 11
Chapter 12

Chapter 9

Click a checkbox to toggle a feature on or off in the text.

Cultural

Incorrect Word Usage

Nonsense Words

Onomatopoeia

Play on Words

Repetition

The Mock Turtle’s Story

‘You can’t think how glad I am to see you again, you dear old thing!’ said the Duchess, as she tucked her arm affectionately into Alice’s, and they walked off together.

Alice was very glad to find her in such a pleasant temper, and thought to herself that perhaps it was only the pepper that had made her so savage when they met in the kitchen.

‘When I’M a Duchess,’ she said to herself, (not in a very hopeful tone though), ‘I won’t have any pepper in my kitchen AT ALL. Soup does very well without--Maybe it’s always pepper that makes people hot-tempered,’ she went on, very much pleased at having found out a new kind of rule, ‘and vinegar that makes them sour--and camomile that makes them bitter--and--and barley-sugar and such things that make children sweet-tempered. I only wish people knew that: then they wouldn’t be so stingy about it, you know--’

She had quite forgotten the Duchess by this time, and was a little startled when she heard her voice close to her ear. ‘You’re thinking about something, my dear, and that makes you forget to talk. I can’t tell you just now what the moral of that is, but I shall remember it in a bit.’

‘Perhaps it hasn’t one,’ Alice ventured to remark.

‘Tut, tut, child!’ said the Duchess. ‘Everything’s got a moral, if only you can find it.’ And she squeezed herself up closer to Alice’s side as she spoke.

Alice did not much like keeping so close to her: first, because the Duchess was VERY ugly; and secondly, because she was exactly the right height to rest her chin upon Alice’s shoulder, and it was an uncomfortably sharp chin. However, she did not like to be rude, so she bore it as well as she could.

‘The game’s going on rather better now,’ she said, by way of keeping up the conversation a little.

‘’Tis so,’ said the Duchess: ‘and the moral of that is--“Oh, ‘tis love, ‘tis love, that makes the world go round!”’

‘Somebody said,’ Alice whispered, ‘that it’s done by everybody minding their own business!’

‘Ah, well! It means much the same thing,’ said the Duchess, digging her sharp little chin into Alice’s shoulder as she added, ‘and the moral of THAT is--“Take care of the sense, and the sounds will take care of themselves.”’

‘How fond she is of finding morals in things!’ Alice thought to herself.

‘I dare say you’re wondering why I don’t put my arm round your waist,’ the Duchess said after a pause: ‘the reason is, that I’m doubtful about the temper of your flamingo. Shall I try the experiment?’

‘HE might bite,’ Alice cautiously replied, not feeling at all anxious to have the experiment tried.

‘Very true,’ said the Duchess: ‘flamingoes and mustard both bite. And the moral of that is--“Birds of a feather flock together.”’

‘Only mustard isn’t a bird,’ Alice remarked.

‘Right, as usual,’ said the Duchess: ‘what a clear way you have of putting things!’

‘It’s a mineral, I THINK,’ said Alice.

‘Of course it is,’ said the Duchess, who seemed ready to agree to everything that Alice said; ‘there’s a large mustard-mine near here. And the moral of that is--“The more there is of mine, the less there is of yours.”’

‘Oh, I know!’ exclaimed Alice, who had not attended to this last remark, ‘it’s a vegetable. It doesn’t look like one, but it is.’

‘I quite agree with you,’ said the Duchess; ‘and the moral of that is--“Be what you would seem to be”--or if you’d like it put more simply--“Never imagine yourself not to be otherwise than what it might appear to others that what you were or might have been was not otherwise than what you had been would have appeared to them to be otherwise.”’

‘I think I should understand that better,’ Alice said very politely, ‘if I had it written down: but I can’t quite follow it as you say it.’

‘That’s nothing to what I could say if I chose,’ the Duchess replied, in a pleased tone.

‘Pray don’t trouble yourself to say it any longer than that,’ said Alice.

‘Oh, don’t talk about trouble!’ said the Duchess. ‘I make you a present of everything I’ve said as yet.’

‘A cheap sort of present!’ thought Alice. ‘I’m glad they don’t give birthday presents like that!’ But she did not venture to say it out loud.

‘Thinking again?’ the Duchess asked, with another dig of her sharp little chin.

‘I’ve a right to think,’ said Alice sharply, for she was beginning to feel a little worried.

‘Just about as much right,’ said the Duchess, ‘as pigs have to fly; and the m--’

But here, to Alice’s great surprise, the Duchess’s voice died away, even in the middle of her favourite word ‘moral,’ and the arm that was linked into hers began to tremble. Alice looked up, and there stood the Queen in front of them, with her arms folded, frowning like a thunderstorm.

‘A fine day, your Majesty!’ the Duchess began in a low, weak voice.

‘Now, I give you fair warning,’ shouted the Queen, stamping on the ground as she spoke; ‘either you or your head must be off, and that in about half no time! Take your choice!’

The Duchess took her choice, and was gone in a moment.

‘Let’s go on with the game,’ the Queen said to Alice; and Alice was too much frightened to say a word, but slowly followed her back to the croquet-ground.

The other guests had taken advantage of the Queen’s absence, and were resting in the shade: however, the moment they saw her, they hurried back to the game, the Queen merely remarking that a moment’s delay would cost them their lives.

All the time they were playing the Queen never left off quarrelling with the other players, and shouting ‘Off with his head!’ or ‘Off with her head!’ Those whom she sentenced were taken into custody by the soldiers, who of course had to leave off being arches to do this, so that by the end of half an hour or so there were no arches left, and all the players, except the King, the Queen, and Alice, were in custody and under sentence of execution.

Then the Queen left off, quite out of breath, and said to Alice, ‘Have you seen the Mock Turtle yet?’

‘No,’ said Alice. ‘I don’t even know what a Mock Turtle is.’

‘It’s the thing Mock Turtle Soup is made from,’ said the Queen.

‘I never saw one, or heard of one,’ said Alice.

‘Come on, then,’ said the Queen, ‘and he shall tell you his history,’

As they walked off together, Alice heard the King say in a low voice, to the company generally, ‘You are all pardoned.’ ‘Come, THAT’S a good thing!’ she said to herself, for she had felt quite unhappy at the number of executions the Queen had ordered.

They very soon came upon a Gryphon, lying fast asleep in the sun. (IF you don’t know what a Gryphon is, look at the picture.) ‘Up, lazy thing!’ said the Queen, ‘and take this young lady to see the Mock Turtle, and to hear his history. I must go back and see after some executions I have ordered’; and she walked off, leaving Alice alone with the Gryphon. Alice did not quite like the look of the creature, but on the whole she thought it would be quite as safe to stay with it as to go after that savage Queen: so she waited.

The Gryphon sat up and rubbed its eyes: then it watched the Queen till she was out of sight: then it chuckled. ‘What fun!’ said the Gryphon, half to itself, half to Alice.

‘What IS the fun?’ said Alice.

‘Why, SHE,’ said the Gryphon. ‘It’s all her fancy, that: they never executes nobody, you know. Come on!’

‘Everybody says “come on!” here,’ thought Alice, as she went slowly after it: ‘I never was so ordered about in all my life, never!’

They had not gone far before they saw the Mock Turtle in the distance, sitting sad and lonely on a little ledge of rock, and, as they came nearer, Alice could hear him sighing as if his heart would break. She pitied him deeply. ‘What is his sorrow?’ she asked the Gryphon, and the Gryphon answered, very nearly in the same words as before, ‘It’s all his fancy, that: he hasn’t got no sorrow, you know. Come on!’

So they went up to the Mock Turtle, who looked at them with large eyes full of tears, but said nothing.

‘This here young lady,’ said the Gryphon, ‘she wants for to know your history, she do.’

‘I’ll tell it her,’ said the Mock Turtle in a deep, hollow tone: ‘sit down, both of you, and don’t speak a word till I’ve finished.’

So they sat down, and nobody spoke for some minutes. Alice thought to herself, ‘I don’t see how he can EVEN finish, if he doesn’t begin.’ But she waited patiently.

‘Once,’ said the Mock Turtle at last, with a deep sigh, ‘I was a real Turtle.’

These words were followed by a very long silence, broken only by an occasional exclamation of ‘Hjckrrh!’ from the Gryphon, and the constant heavy sobbing of the Mock Turtle. Alice was very nearly getting up and saying, ‘Thank you, sir, for your interesting story,’ but she could not help thinking there MUST be more to come, so she sat still and said nothing.

‘When we were little,’ the Mock Turtle went on at last, more calmly, though still sobbing a little now and then, ‘we went to school in the sea. The master was an old Turtle--we used to call him Tortoise--’

‘Why did you call him Tortoise, if he wasn’t one?’ Alice asked.

‘We called him Tortoise because he taught us,’ said the Mock Turtle angrily: ‘really you are very dull!’

‘You ought to be ashamed of yourself for asking such a simple question,’ added the Gryphon; and then they both sat silent and looked at poor Alice, who felt ready to sink into the earth. At last the Gryphon said to the Mock Turtle, ‘Drive on, old fellow! Don’t be all day about it!’ and he went on in these words:

‘Yes, we went to school in the sea, though you mayn’t believe it--’

‘I never said I didn’t!’ interrupted Alice.

‘You did,’ said the Mock Turtle.

‘Hold your tongue!’ added the Gryphon, before Alice could speak again. The Mock Turtle went on.

‘We had the best of educations--in fact, we went to school every day--’

‘I’VE been to a day-school, too,’ said Alice; ‘you needn’t be so proud as all that.’

‘With extras?’ asked the Mock Turtle a little anxiously.

‘Yes,’ said Alice, ‘we learned French and music.’

‘And washing?’ said the Mock Turtle.

‘Certainly not!’ said Alice indignantly.

‘Ah! then yours wasn’t a really good school,’ said the Mock Turtle in a tone of great relief. ‘Now at OURS they had at the end of the bill, “French, music, AND WASHING--extra.”’

‘You couldn’t have wanted it much,’ said Alice; ‘living at the bottom of the sea.’

‘I couldn’t afford to learn it.’ said the Mock Turtle with a sigh. ‘I only took the regular course.’

‘What was that?’ inquired Alice.

‘Reeling and Writhing, of course, to begin with,’ the Mock Turtle replied; ‘and then the different branches of Arithmetic--Ambition, Distraction, Uglification, and Derision.’

‘I never heard of “Uglification,”’ Alice ventured to say. ‘What is it?’

The Gryphon lifted up both its paws in surprise. ‘What! Never heard of uglifying!’ it exclaimed. ‘You know what to beautify is, I suppose?’

‘Yes,’ said Alice doubtfully: ‘it means--to--make--anything--prettier.’

‘Well, then,’ the Gryphon went on, ‘if you don’t know what to uglify is, you ARE a simpleton.’

Alice did not feel encouraged to ask any more questions about it, so she turned to the Mock Turtle, and said ‘What else had you to learn?’

‘Well, there was Mystery,’ the Mock Turtle replied, counting off the subjects on his flappers, ‘--Mystery, ancient and modern, with Seaography: then Drawling--the Drawling-master was an old conger-eel, that used to come once a week: HE taught us Drawling, Stretching, and Fainting in Coils.’

‘What was THAT like?’ said Alice.

‘Well, I can’t show it you myself,’ the Mock Turtle said: ‘I’m too stiff. And the Gryphon never learnt it.’

‘Hadn’t time,’ said the Gryphon: ‘I went to the Classics master, though. He was an old crab, HE was.’

‘I never went to him,’ the Mock Turtle said with a sigh: ‘he taught Laughing and Grief, they used to say.’

‘So he did, so he did,’ said the Gryphon, sighing in his turn; and both creatures hid their faces in their paws.

‘And how many hours a day did you do lessons?’ said Alice, in a hurry to change the subject.

‘Ten hours the first day,’ said the Mock Turtle: ‘nine the next, and so on.’

‘What a curious plan!’ exclaimed Alice.

‘That’s the reason they’re called lessons,’ the Gryphon remarked: ‘because they lessen from day to day.’

This was quite a new idea to Alice, and she thought it over a little before she made her next remark. ‘Then the eleventh day must have been a holiday?’

‘Of course it was,’ said the Mock Turtle.

‘And how did you manage on the twelfth?’ Alice went on eagerly.

‘That’s enough about lessons,’ the Gryphon interrupted in a very decided tone: ‘tell her something about the games now.’

ウミガメフーミのものがたり

「うれしいこといかばかりか、また顔を合わせられるとは、なつかしいことよの。」と御前さまはなれなれしくアリスのわきにうでを通してきてね、ふたりは連れだって歩き出すことに。

アリスも御前さまのごきげんがよろしいとわかって、とてもほっとしてね、台所で会ったときあんなにつっけんどんだったのも、よもやコショウのせいかなとも思えてきたり。

「あたくしが御前さまなら、」とひとりごと（とはいえ 現実 にはなれそうにもないけど）「コショウなんて台所に置かせないんだから、ひとつも。なくてもスープはうまくできてよ。たぶんコショウのせいでいつもみんな かっか してるのね。」と、これは大発見とばかりにしたり顔、そのあと、「それから、おすのせいでみんなしかめっ面――カモミールのせいでしぶい顔――黒アメとかあああいうのがあれば子どももほころび顔。そこのところみんなわかってくれたらいいのに。そうしたらみんなアメを出しおしみしないようになって、ほら――」

ここまで来ると御前さまのことなんかすっかりどわすれ、そこへその声が耳元で聞こえたものだから、ちょっとびくっとしちゃってね。「何か考えごとかえ、おまえさん、それでおしゃべりはおそろかと。そんなそちにぴったりの教えは、今はうまく出てこんが、まあそのうち思い出そうて。」

「たぶんそんなのなくてよ。」とアリスは思いきって口答え。

「ちっ、ちっ、子どもよの！」と御前さま。「何にでも教えは見いだせるものじゃ、気づきさえあればな。」とお話のあいだアリスに体をべたべたくっつけてね。

相手が近すぎるのがアリスはあんまりうれしくなくってね、だってなにより御前さまのお顔はほんとにぶさいくだし、それからアリスのかたの高さが、あごをのせるのにちょうどいいみたいで、しかもそのあごは気持ち悪いことにとがってると来た。とはいえ無礼なことはしたくなかったので、できるだけがまん。

「ゲームは今そこそこうまく行ってるみたいね。」と、もうちょっと会話を続けてみる。

「うむ。」と御前さま。「そしてそこから学べる教えとは――『おお、それこそ愛、愛こそが世をうまくめぐらせる！』」

「どなたかによれば、」とつぶやくアリス、「それって、みんながひとにちょっかい出さなければの話じゃなくて？」

「おお、さよう！　つまりはまさしくそういうこと。」と言いつつ御前さまはアリスのかたに、とがったあごをぐりぐりぐり、たたみかけるように「そしてそこから学べる教えとは――『意味が決まれば自ずから言の葉も決まる。』」

「何からでも教えに気づきたがるおひとってわけね。」とひとり思うアリス。

「みなまで言うな、そちはこう思うのじゃろ、わらわがどうしてこしに手を回さんかと。」とほざく御前さま、ちょっと間をあけて、「そのわけは、そちのフラミンゴがやにわにあばれんかとあやぶんでおるからじゃ。ためしてもよいかの？」

「たぶんかみついてよ。」と身がまえるアリス、そんなのたまったもんじゃないからね。

「それもそうじゃの。」と御前さま。「フラミンゴもからしも、やられればひりひりする。そこから学べる教えとは――『 類 は友をよぶ。』」

「でも、からしは生き物じゃなくてよ。」とつっかかるアリス。

「うむ、ふつうはな。」と御前さま。「なんとはっきりものを言うやつじゃ！」

「なら石とか岩ね、たぶん。」とアリス。

「むろんそうとも。」とほざく御前さまは、アリスの言うことなら何でもうなずいていくご様子。「ここほど近くの山にも、からしがたくさんうまっておる。そしてそこから学べる教えとは――『うまればうまるほどうまくなる。』」

「あ、わかった！」とさけぶアリス、相手の決めぜりふなんて聞いちゃいない。「 野菜 ね、それっぽくはないけど、きっとそう。」

「そちの言うとおり。」と言い出す御前さま。「そしてそこから学べる教えとは――『そう見えるのならそうなのだ。』――すなわちさらにわかりよう言えば――『おのれのことを、ひとの目にうつるものとはちがうなどとは思わんこと、かつてそうであった、そうであったかもしれない、事実そうであったおのれとはちがうなどとは、それもまたひとの目にはちがってうつるのだから。』」

「たぶん、書き起こしたものがあれば、」とまじめに取り合うアリス、「もっとよくわかると思うんだけど。おっしゃってること、ちょっとついていけなくてよ。」

「こんなもの、ものは言いよう、大したことない。」と返す御前さまはごまんえつ。

「ならもうわざわざしていただかなくてけっこう！」とアリス。

「そんなわざわざだなんて！」と御前さま。「これまでの言葉をみな、そちに進ぜよう。」

「やっすいおくりものね！」と思うアリス。「みんながたんじょう日プレゼントにこんなのくれなくてよかった！」でも思い切って声に出すことはできずじまい。

「また考えごとかえ？」とたずねてくる御前さまのとんがったあごがまたつきささる。

「あたくしだって考えごとしてしかるべきよ。」とつんつん言い出すアリス、だってちょっとわずらわしく思えてきたものだから。

「しかるべきじゃとも、」と御前さま、「ブタが空を飛ぶくらいには。そしてそこからま……」

ところがここで、アリスもほんとにびっくり、御前さまの声がとぎれてね、大好きな「学べる教え」という言葉を言いかけたところだったのに、組んでたうでもぶるぶるしだして。アリスが顔を上げると、なんとクイーンが自分たちの前に立ちはだかってうで組み、おまけに雷雨のごとくけわしいお顔。

「お日がらもよく、クイーンさま。」と切り出す御前さまの声はか細く小さい。

「よいか、よおく聞くがいい。」と大声のクイーン、話しているあいだもどんどん足ぶみ。「この場からそなたがのうなるか首がのうなるか、いずれがよい？　たった今よりすぐさまだ！　さあ決めろ！」

決めた御前さまは、ただちにいなくなった。

「さてゲームの続きよの。」とアリスに言うクイーン。アリスもこわくてこわくて何も言い出せなくて、とりあえずそうろっとうしろからついていってクローケー場に。

残ってやってたひとたちもみんな、クイーンがいないのをいいことに、かげで一休みをしていてね。ところがすがたが見えたもんだから、とたんにあわててゲームにもどる、クイーンはただ、少しでもおくれたら、きさまらの命はないぞと言うばかり。

みんながやってるあいだも、ずっとクイーンはやってるひとたちみんなとの口げんかをやめなくて、「あの男の首をちょん切れ！」とか「あの女の首をちょん切れ！」ってわめくばっかり。言いわたされたやつはみんな、強者にしょっぴかれていくから、そうなるともちろん玉くぐらせの役ができなくなるわけで、そんなこんなで３０分かそこらもたつと、残ったのはキングとクイーンとアリスだけで、あとはみんな処けいを言いわたされてしょっぴかれてしまった。

そこでクイーンも手をとめて、ぜえはあ言いながら、アリスに一言、「そちはもうウミガメフーミに会うたか？」

「いいえ。」とアリス。「そもそもウミガメフーミが何だかぞんじませんし。」

「ウミガメフーミスープのもとになるものよの。」とクイーン。

「そんなの見たことも聞いたこともなくてよ。」とアリス。

「ならばこちへ。」とクイーン、「さすれば本人がいわれを教えてくれよう。」

いっしょになってそこをはなれるとき、アリスの耳へ、キングがその場のみんなにかける声がかすかに、「このたびはみな大目に見る」って。「はあ、ほっとしてよ！」とひとりごと、だってクイーンが処けいをたくさん言いつけてかなり気を落としていたからね。

まもなく行き当たったのが１ぴきのグリフォン、日なたですやすやねていてね（グリフォンがどんなのか知らないなら、さし絵をごらん。）「起きよ、なまけもの！」とクイーン、「この 姫君 をウミガメフーミのところへあないして、いわれを聞かせてやれい。わらわはもどって、言いつけておいた処けいを見とどけねばならん。」とはなれていって、ひとり残されたアリスとグリフォン。アリスはこの生き物のつらがまえがそこまで気に入ったわけではないんだけど、考え合わせてみると、そいつとここにいても、あのぷんすかクイーンについていくのも、どっちでもあぶないのはどうも変わりなさそうだから、じっとしてたんだ。

身体を起こしたグリフォンが目をこすって、そのあと見えなくなるまでクイーンをまじまじ。そのあとふくみ笑い。「けっさくでい！」とグリフォンは、ひとりごと半分でアリスに言う。

「けっさくって、何が？」とアリス。

「あの女さ。」とグリフォン。「みんなあいつの思いこみでい、だれひとり処けいなんてされねえってことよ。こっちだ！」

「ここの方々『こっちだ』ばっかり。」と思いつつもアリスはそいつにゆっくりついていく。「生まれてこのかた、そんなふうに言いつけられたこと、なくてよ、なくってよ！」

歩いてほどなく遠くに見えてくるウミガメフーミ、いわおの小さなでっぱりに、ひとり悲しそうにこしかけていてね、近づくにつれ聞こえてくるそのため息、まるでむねがはりさけたみたい。だから心からかわいそうになって、「何が悲しくって？」とグリフォンにたずねたんだけど、グリフォンの答えは、さっきのとほとんど同じような言葉でね、「みんなあいつの思いこみでい、悲しいことなんてべつにありゃしねえ。こっちだ！」

で、ウミガメフーミのところまでたどりつくと、大きな目をうるうるさせて見てくるわりに、ものも言わない。

「こちらの 姫君 が、」とグリフォン、「おめえのいわれを知りてえんだとさ。」

「そちらに申します。」とウミガメフーミは、消え入りそうな声で、「おふたかたとも、おすわりくだせえ、しまいまでどうかお静かに。」

というわけで、こしを下ろして、しばしのあいだ一同だんまり。そこでアリスは考えごと、「始まらないなら、おしまいも何もないんじゃなくて？」でもじっとこらえる。

「昔は、」とついに口を開くウミガメフーミ、ふかいため息ついて、「あっしもまっとうなウミガメでした。」

そう切り出したあと長い長い間があってね、ときどきグリフォンの「ひっくるぅー」というおたけびがはさまったり、ひっきりなしウミガメフーミのさめざめという泣き声が聞こえたりするくらいで。アリスは立ち上がって「面白いお話ご苦労さま。」と言い捨てそうになるところだったけど、きっと何かあるはずとどうしても思えるのもあって、すわったままだまっていたんだ。

「まだ小せえころは、」とウミガメフーミはおもむろに続きを話し出してね、たびたびまだしゃくり上げたりしながら、「海の学びやに通うたもんで。先生はウミガメのじいさんで――あっしらはよくスッポンと呼んどり……」

「どうしてそんなあだ名になって？　ほんとはちがうのに。」と口をはさむアリス。

「まっさらな本は 素本 と言うだろ。」とウミガメフーミはぷんすか、「あんたほんとににぶいむすめだ！」

「てめえそんな当たりめえのこと聞いてはずかしくねえのか？」とグリフォンが追いうち、そのあとはふたりとももの言わずすわったまま、かわいそうなやつと目を向けてくるので、アリスは穴があったら入りたい気持ちになってきて。やがてグリフォンがウミガメフーミに声をかけてね、「続けろい、こんにゃろ！　日がくれちまう！」するとウミガメフーミはこう言葉をついでいく――

「で、あっしらは海の 学舎 に通うとりました、あんたは信じられんかもしれねえが……」

「できないって言うの？」と口をはさむアリス。

「ああ。」とウミガメフーミ。

「じゃかあしい！」とかぶせるグリフォン。

「とにかく一等の学舎でした――そのはずで、あっしら週日、学校行ってたんですぜ……」

「あたくしだって『週日学校』に通ってよ。」とアリス。「そんなのでじまんするつもり？」

「 選択 はどうだ？」とたずねるウミガメフーミはちょっぴりそわそわ。

「もちろん、」とアリス、「受けてよ、フランス語に音楽。」

「洗い物はしねえのかい？」とウミガメフーミ。

「するわけないじゃない！」とアリスはぷんすか。

「おお！　ならあんたんとこは、ええ学舎じゃねえんで。」とウミガメフーミの口ぶりはたいへんほっとしたようで。「あっしらんとこじゃ、 勘定 の最後にフランス語と音楽と洗い物は『せんたく』てえあったな。」

「べつに必要ないことなくて。」とアリス。「海の底でくらしてるんだもの。」

「まあ、あっしは習うゆとりがなかったもんで。」とウミガメフーミはため息。「普通の科目だけでやした。」

「何があるの？」とくいつくアリス。

「そりゃあ、より方にまき方から始めまして、」と答えるウミガメフーミ、「それから算数を一通りやりまして――わたし算にひっきり算、ばけ算にわらい算。」

「ばけ算だなんて初耳。」と思い切って口に出すアリス。「何それ。」

グリフォンはびっくり、前足をふたつとも高く上げて、「化け物ってな知らねえか！」とさけんでね。「 化粧 ってのはわかるだろ、ああ？」

「ええ、」と言うアリスは自信なさげ、「それって――あの――きれいに――化ける――ことでしょ。」

「それで、」と引き取るグリフォン、「化け物のことを知らねえたあ、てめえアホウよ。」

しょげてしまったアリス、そこからまた何かをたずねる気にもならなくてね、だからウミガメフーミの方を向いて言ったんだ。「ほかに何のお勉強したの？」

「へえ、からっきしを。」と答えるウミガメフーミはひれでひとつずつ科目を数えていってね――「からっきし、こりゃあ昔のも今のもで、それにとばっちり。あとはヨガ 倒錯 ――ヨガの先生はアナゴのじいさんで、週１でありやす。ヨガの体操でぐるぐるこんがらがって、わけわかんなくなりやす。」

「それってどうやるわけ？」とアリス。

「いや、あっしにゃあとてもとても。」とウミガメフーミ。「身体がかたくて。それにグリフォンのだんなも知りやせんし。」

「ひまがねえもんでな。」とグリフォン。「まあ古文の先生にはついたさ。カニのじいさんよ、そいつは。」

「あっしは行っとりませんが。」とウミガメフーミはため息。「何でも昔の笑ってん語と歯ぎしりや語を教えなさるとか。」

「そうよ、そうともよ。」と今度はグリフォンもため息。そして２ひきの生き物はその前足で顔をおおってね。

「で、１日に何時間くらいあるわけ？」とアリスはあわてて話を切りかえる。

「１日目は８時間、」とウミガメフーミ、「次の日は４時間と続いていくんで。」

「すっごくへんてこりん！」と思わず声に出すアリス。

「そこはそら 時間割 て言うだろう？」と言い出すグリフォン、「日ごと半分に割られていくんよ。」

これはアリスには思いもよらないことだったので、ちょっと考えてみてから次にはこんなことを言い出してね。「じゃあ割り切れなくなった５日目はお休み？」

「その通りでごぜえやす。」

「でもそれじゃ６日目はどうするの？」とわくわくしながら続けるアリス。

「時間割の話あもういい。」とグリフォンがばっさり割りこんでね。「さあ、この子におゆうぎでも教えてやろうや。」

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1 | Chapter 2 | Chapter 3 | Chapter 4 | Chapter 5 | Chapter 6 | Chapter 7 | Chapter 8 | Chapter 9 | Chapter 10 | Chapter 11 | Chapter 12

Chapter 10

The Lobster Quadrille

The Mock Turtle sighed deeply, and drew the back of one flapper across his eyes. He looked at Alice, and tried to speak, but for a minute or two sobs choked his voice. ‘Same as if he had a bone in his throat,’ said the Gryphon: and it set to work shaking him and punching him in the back. At last the Mock Turtle recovered his voice, and, with tears running down his cheeks, he went on again:--

‘You may not have lived much under the sea--’ (‘I haven’t,’ said Alice)--‘and perhaps you were never even introduced to a lobster--’ (Alice began to say ‘I once tasted--’ but checked herself hastily, and said ‘No, never’) ‘--so you can have no idea what a delightful thing a Lobster Quadrille is!’

‘No, indeed,’ said Alice. ‘What sort of a dance is it?’

‘Why,’ said the Gryphon, ‘you first form into a line along the sea-shore--’

‘Two lines!’ cried the Mock Turtle. ‘Seals, turtles, salmon, and so on; then, when you’ve cleared all the jelly-fish out of the way--’

‘THAT generally takes some time,’ interrupted the Gryphon.

‘--you advance twice--’

‘Each with a lobster as a partner!’ cried the Gryphon.

‘Of course,’ the Mock Turtle said: ‘advance twice, set to partners--’

‘--change lobsters, and retire in same order,’ continued the Gryphon.

‘Then, you know,’ the Mock Turtle went on, ‘you throw the--’

‘The lobsters!’ shouted the Gryphon, with a bound into the air.

‘--as far out to sea as you can--’

‘Swim after them!’ screamed the Gryphon.

‘Turn a somersault in the sea!’ cried the Mock Turtle, capering wildly about.

‘Change lobsters again!’ yelled the Gryphon at the top of its voice.

‘Back to land again, and that’s all the first figure,’ said the Mock Turtle, suddenly dropping his voice; and the two creatures, who had been jumping about like mad things all this time, sat down again very sadly and quietly, and looked at Alice.

‘It must be a very pretty dance,’ said Alice timidly.

‘Would you like to see a little of it?’ said the Mock Turtle.

‘Very much indeed,’ said Alice.

‘Come, let’s try the first figure!’ said the Mock Turtle to the Gryphon. ‘We can do without lobsters, you know. Which shall sing?’

‘Oh, YOU sing,’ said the Gryphon. ‘I’ve forgotten the words.’

So they began solemnly dancing round and round Alice, every now and then treading on her toes when they passed too close, and waving their forepaws to mark the time, while the Mock Turtle sang this, very slowly and sadly:--

‘“Will you walk a little faster?” said a whiting to a snail.
“There’s a porpoise close behind us, and he’s treading on my tail.

See how eagerly the lobsters and the turtles all advance!
They are waiting on the shingle--will you come and join the dance?

Will you, won’t you, will you, won’t you, will you join the dance?
Will you, won’t you, will you, won’t you, won’t you join the dance?

“You can really have no notion how delightful it will be
When they take us up and throw us, with the lobsters, out to sea!” But the snail replied “Too far, too far!” and gave a look askance--
Said he thanked the whiting kindly, but he would not join the dance.

Would not, could not, would not, could not, would not join the dance.
Would not, could not, would not, could not, could not join the dance.

‘“What matters it how far we go?” his scaly friend replied. “There is another shore, you know, upon the other side. The further off from England the nearer is to France-- Then turn not pale, beloved snail, but come and join the dance.

Will you, won’t you, will you, won’t you, will you join the dance?
Will you, won’t you, will you, won’t you, won’t you join the dance?”

’

‘Thank you, it’s a very interesting dance to watch,’ said Alice, feeling very glad that it was over at last: ‘and I do so like that curious song about the whiting!’

‘Oh, as to the whiting,’ said the Mock Turtle, ‘they--you’ve seen them, of course?’

‘Yes,’ said Alice, ‘I’ve often seen them at dinn--’ she checked herself hastily.

‘I don’t know where Dinn may be,’ said the Mock Turtle, ‘but if you’ve seen them so often, of course you know what they’re like.’

‘I believe so,’ Alice replied thoughtfully. ‘They have their tails in their mouths--and they’re all over crumbs.’

‘You’re wrong about the crumbs,’ said the Mock Turtle: ‘crumbs would all wash off in the sea. But they HAVE their tails in their mouths; and the reason is--’ here the Mock Turtle yawned and shut his eyes.--‘Tell her about the reason and all that,’ he said to the Gryphon.

‘The reason is,’ said the Gryphon, ‘that they WOULD go with the lobsters to the dance. So they got thrown out to sea. So they had to fall a long way. So they got their tails fast in their mouths. So they couldn’t get them out again. That’s all.’

‘Thank you,’ said Alice, ‘it’s very interesting. I never knew so much about a whiting before.’

‘I can tell you more than that, if you like,’ said the Gryphon. ‘Do you know why it’s called a whiting?’

‘I never thought about it,’ said Alice. ‘Why?’

‘IT DOES THE BOOTS AND SHOES.’ the Gryphon replied very solemnly.

Alice was thoroughly puzzled. ‘Does the boots and shoes!’ she repeated in a wondering tone.

‘Why, what are YOUR shoes done with?’ said the Gryphon. ‘I mean, what makes them so shiny?’

Alice looked down at them, and considered a little before she gave her answer. ‘They’re done with blacking, I believe.’

‘Boots and shoes under the sea,’ the Gryphon went on in a deep voice, ‘are done with a whiting. Now you know.’

‘And what are they made of?’ Alice asked in a tone of great curiosity.

‘Soles and eels, of course,’ the Gryphon replied rather impatiently: ‘any shrimp could have told you that.’

‘If I’d been the whiting,’ said Alice, whose thoughts were still running on the song, ‘I’d have said to the porpoise, “Keep back, please: we don’t want YOU with us!”’

‘They were obliged to have him with them,’ the Mock Turtle said: ‘no wise fish would go anywhere without a porpoise.’

‘Wouldn’t it really?’ said Alice in a tone of great surprise.

‘Of course not,’ said the Mock Turtle: ‘why, if a fish came to ME, and told me he was going a journey, I should say “With what porpoise?”’

‘Don’t you mean “purpose”?’ said Alice.

‘I mean what I say,’ the Mock Turtle replied in an offended tone. And the Gryphon added ‘Come, let’s hear some of YOUR adventures.’

‘I could tell you my adventures--beginning from this morning,’ said Alice a little timidly: ‘but it’s no use going back to yesterday, because I was a different person then.’

‘Explain all that,’ said the Mock Turtle.

‘No, no! The adventures first,’ said the Gryphon in an impatient tone: ‘explanations take such a dreadful time.’

So Alice began telling them her adventures from the time when she first saw the White Rabbit. She was a little nervous about it just at first, the two creatures got so close to her, one on each side, and opened their eyes and mouths so VERY wide, but she gained courage as she went on. Her listeners were perfectly quiet till she got to the part about her repeating ‘YOU ARE OLD, FATHER WILLIAM,’ to the Caterpillar, and the words all coming different, and then the Mock Turtle drew a long breath, and said ‘That’s very curious.’

‘It’s all about as curious as it can be,’ said the Gryphon.

‘It all came different!’ the Mock Turtle repeated thoughtfully. ‘I should like to hear her try and repeat something now. Tell her to begin.’ He looked at the Gryphon as if he thought it had some kind of authority over Alice.

‘Stand up and repeat “‘TIS THE VOICE OF THE SLUGGARD,”’ said the Gryphon.

‘How the creatures order one about, and make one repeat lessons!’ thought Alice; ‘I might as well be at school at once.’ However, she got up, and began to repeat it, but her head was so full of the Lobster Quadrille, that she hardly knew what she was saying, and the words came very queer indeed:--

‘’Tis the voice of the Lobster; I heard him declare,
“You have baked me too brown, I must sugar my hair.” As a duck with its eyelids, so he with his nose
Trims his belt and his buttons, and turns out his toes.’

When the sands are all dry, he is gay as a lark,
And will talk in contemptuous tones of the Shark, But, when the tide rises and sharks are around,
His voice has a timid and tremulous sound.

‘That’s different from what I used to say when I was a child,’ said the Gryphon.

‘Well, I never heard it before,’ said the Mock Turtle; ‘but it sounds uncommon nonsense.’

Alice said nothing; she had sat down with her face in her hands, wondering if anything would EVER happen in a natural way again.

‘I should like to have it explained,’ said the Mock Turtle.

‘She can’t explain it,’ said the Gryphon hastily. ‘Go on with the next verse.’

‘But about his toes?’ the Mock Turtle persisted. ‘How COULD he turn them out with his nose, you know?’

‘It’s the first position in dancing.’ Alice said; but was dreadfully puzzled by the whole thing, and longed to change the subject.

‘Go on with the next verse,’ the Gryphon repeated impatiently: ‘it begins “I passed by his garden.”’

Alice did not dare to disobey, though she felt sure it would all come wrong, and she went on in a trembling voice:--

‘I passed by his garden, and marked, with one eye,
How the Owl and the Panther were sharing a pie--’

The Panther took pie-crust, and gravy, and meat,
While the Owl had the dish as its share of the treat. When the pie was all finished, the Owl, as a boon,
Was kindly permitted to pocket the spoon: While the Panther received knife and fork with a growl,
And concluded the banquet--

‘What IS the use of repeating all that stuff,’ the Mock Turtle interrupted, ‘if you don’t explain it as you go on? It’s by far the most confusing thing I ever heard!’

‘Yes, I think you’d better leave off,’ said the Gryphon: and Alice was only too glad to do so.

‘Shall we try another figure of the Lobster Quadrille?’ the Gryphon went on. ‘Or would you like the Mock Turtle to sing you a song?’

‘Oh, a song, please, if the Mock Turtle would be so kind,’ Alice replied, so eagerly that the Gryphon said, in a rather offended tone, ‘Hm! No accounting for tastes! Sing her “Turtle Soup,” will you, old fellow?’

The Mock Turtle sighed deeply, and began, in a voice sometimes choked with sobs, to sing this:--

‘Beautiful Soup, so rich and green,
Waiting in a hot tureen! Who for such dainties would not stoop?
Soup of the evening, beautiful Soup! Soup of the evening, beautiful Soup!
Beau--ootiful Soo--oop! Beau--ootiful Soo--oop!
Soo--oop of the e--e--evening, Beautiful, beautiful Soup!

‘Beautiful Soup! Who cares for fish, Game, or any other dish?
Who would not give all else for two Pennyworth only of beautiful Soup?
Pennyworth only of beautiful Soup?
Beau--ootiful Soo--oop! Beau--ootiful Soo--oop!
Soo--oop of the e--e--evening, Beautiful, beauti--FUL SOUP!’

‘Chorus again!’ cried the Gryphon, and the Mock Turtle had just begun to repeat it, when a cry of ‘The trial’s beginning!’ was heard in the distance.

‘Come on!’ cried the Gryphon, and, taking Alice by the hand, it hurried off, without waiting for the end of the song.

‘What trial is it?’ Alice panted as she ran; but the Gryphon only answered ‘Come on!’ and ran the faster, while more and more faintly came, carried on the breeze that followed them, the melancholy words:--

‘Soo--oop of the e--e--evening, Beautiful, beautiful Soup!’

　ロブスターのカドリール

ウミガメフーミは深々ため息、ひれのうらで目元をぬぐってね。アリスを見すえて話そうとするんだけど、ものの数分、声をつまらせながらさめざめ。「のどにほねがつかえたみてえなざまだ。」とグリフォン、さっそくゆすぶって、背中をどんどんたたいて。とうとう声が出せるようになったウミガメフーミ、あいかわらずほおになみだをたらしながら話の続き。

「もしやおめえさんは海の底でくらしたことがなくて――」（「なくてよ。」とアリス。）――「するってえとまさかロブスターにも顔合わせたことがねえ――」（「食べたことはあ……」と言いかけたけどあわてて口をつぐんでから、「ない、ぜんっぜん。」）「……なら、ごぞんじねえわけですな、うっきうきのロブスターのカドリールは！」

「ええ初耳。」とアリス、「どういうダンスなの？」

「そりゃあ、」とグリフォン、「海辺ぞいに１列になってな……」

「２列でい！」と声を上げるウミガメフーミ、「アザラシにウミガメにシャケにいっぺえよ。で、じゃまなクラゲをみんな追っぱらったら……」

「それにいつもひまがかかりやがる！」と口をはさむグリフォン。

「――２歩前ん出て……」

「てめえごとで相手にロブスターをだな！」と声をはるグリフォン。

「そうともさ。」とウミガメフーミ、「２歩出て相手につらを向けてな……」

「――ロブスターを取りかえ、元の列にもどる。」と先を続けるグリフォン。

「それからほら、」と引きつぐウミガメフーミ、「投げんだよ……」

「ロブスターを！」とさけぶグリフォン、ぴょーんとおどり上がる。

「――できるだけ海の遠くへ……」

「で追っかけて泳ぐ！」とグリフォンのおたけび。

「海んなかでとんぼ返りよ！」と大声のウミガメフーミはやたらはね回る。

「またロブスターの取っかえ！」とあらんかぎりにわめくグリフォン。

「 陸 にもどって――それでひと回りよ。」とウミガメフーミはとたんに声をひそめて、ふたりはそれまでずっと頭おかしいくらいにぴょんぴょんしていたのに、またもの悲しそうにすわりこんで、アリスに目をやる。

「それなりにすてきなダンスじゃなくて？」とアリスはぎこちない。

「ちっとばかし見たかあねえですか？」とウミガメフーミ。

「ええぜひ。」とアリス。

「さあ、ひと回りやってみやしょうぜ！」ウミガメフーミからグリフォンへ、「まあロブスターなしでもできましょうて。どっちが歌いやす？」

「よし、てめえが歌え、」とグリフォン、「文句をわすれちまってな。」

と、もったいぶりつつ始めると、アリスのまわりをぐるぐる、たびたびふみこみすぎては毎回つま先をふんづけていきつつ、ふしを取ろうと前足ふりふり、そのあいだ歌うのはウミガメフーミ、こんなふうにしみじみと。

マイマイ、マダラにうしろをつかれて
サメがせまってる　そこまで来てる
みんな先まで泳いでる
ぼくらを待ってる――おどりにゆこう

行こうよ、どうかな、おどりにさ
行こうよ、どうかな、おどるのは

だって楽しく海へと投げられて
ロブスターと浜から　ぶんぶんざぶん
でもマイマイ言うには　遠すぎる
うれしいけれど　おどりに行けない

いやいや、無理だよ、おどりはさ
いやいや、無理だよ、おどるのは

そこでマダラはせっつく　遠くても
向こうに行けば　陸地はあるよ
遠い近いは気持ち次第
やる気を出して　おどりに混ざろう

行こうよ、どうかな、おどりにさ
行こうよ、どうかな、おどるのは

「ご苦労さま、とてもゆかいなダンスね。」とアリスは、ようやくダンスが終わってほっとした気分。「それにへんてこなマダラの歌もまあ気に入ってよ。」

「おお、マダラと言やあ、」とウミガメフーミ、「そりゃあ――見たこたあありやすね？」

「ええ、」とアリス、「何度も、お 食 ……で。」とあわてて口をつぐむ。

「まあ、オショクてな場所がどこかは知りやせんが、」とウミガメフーミ、「よく見るんでしたらそりゃどんなふうか知ってやすね？」

「たぶんね。」とアリスはよくよく考えた上でお返事。「尾っぽを口にくわえてて――全身にパン粉こがまぶしてあってよ。」

「パン粉は何かのまちがいですぜ。」とウミガメフーミ。「海んなかじゃあパン粉なんかみんな流れちめえます。でも口に尾っぽをくわえたあいるな。そのわけあ――」とここでウミガメフーミはあくびをして目をつむってね。「その子にわけやら何やらを教えてつかあさい。」とグリフォンにあずける。

「まあつまりは、」とグリフォン、「マダラはロブスターといっしょにおどりに行くもんだからよ。で、海へ放り投げられて。で、落ちるまでに暇があって。で、口に尾っぽをくわえるて。で、二度と口から出なくなったってえことよ。おしめえ。」

「ご苦労さま。」とアリス、「とってもゆかいね。マダラのことなんて今までぜんぜん知らなかった。」

「おのぞみならもっと教えてやんでい。」とグリフォン。「マダラって名前の由来は知ってるか？」

「考えてもみなくてよ。」とアリス。「何なの？」

「皮ぐつをまだらにみがくからよ。」と答えるグリフォンはしごく真面目。

アリスの頭はハテナだらけ。「皮ぐつをまだらにみがく？」とふしぎそうにくり返してね。

「そうよ、皮ぐつをみがいたらどうなる？」とグリフォン。「つまりきゅっきゅってみがいたらだぜ。」

アリスは自分のくつを見つめてから、ちょっとばかし考えて答えを出す。「 ぴかぴかのまっ黒になってよ、ふつうは。」

「海んなかで皮ぐつをみがきゃあ、」と野太い声で続けるグリフォン、「はげてまだらになるんよ。おぼえときな。」

「その、海の皮ぐつってどうなってて？」そのへんてこぶりにわくわくしてきたアリス。

「そりゃ下はくつジャコで、くつハモを結ぶのさ。」と返すグリフォンはいらただしげ。「そんなのカレイでも知ってるぜ。」

「あたくしがマダラだったら、」と言うアリスはまださっきの歌のことがずっと頭にあってね、「サメにはこう言ってやってよ、『ついてこないでちょうだい！　いっしょにいたくないの！』」

「連れなきゃなんねえのです。」とウミガメフーミ。「ズサメなきゃ魚ってな、どこにも行けねえんで。」

「そんなまさか？」とかなりびっくりした口ぶりのアリス。

「そのまさかよ。」とウミガメフーミ。「まあ、あっしのとこに魚が来て、これから旅に出るなんて言やあ、こう言うね、『どこをズサメんだ？』」

「それって『目指す』じゃなくって？」とアリス。

「てやんでえ。」とウミガメフーミはむっとしたお返事。するとグリフォンが口をはさんでね、「まあてめえの身の上でも聞かせてくれやい。」

「なら教えてあげてよ、あたくしの身の上――そもそもは今朝のこと。」とアリスはちょっとおそるおそる、「でも昨日をふりかえるのはおことわり、だってそのときはあたくし別人だったんだもの。」

「そっちを語っておくんなせい。」とウミガメフーミ。

「ダメだ、ダメだ！　先に身の上でい。」とじれったそうに言うグリフォン、「そんなの語ってたら、すさまじくひまがかかる。」

そこでアリスは今までの身の上を語り始めてね、はじまりはまず白ウサギを目にしたところから。はじめのうちはちょっと気おくれしてたんだけど、２ひきの生き物は 右左 にと間近にすりよってきてね、聞き手はずっとだまってたんだけど、青虫に「ウィリアムじいさん」をそらでうたって、まったくちがうかえ歌になったくだりに入ると、そこでウミガメフーミが長々とため息をついてね、言うんだ、「そりゃへんてこなこって。」

「こりゃ何もかもへんてここの上ねえ。」とグリフォン。

「全部ちがっちまうとは！」としみじみくり返すウミガメフーミ。「ちょいと何か聞いてみてえな。さいそくしてくだせえ。」と、アリスに言うこときかせるのはそっちと言わんばかりにグリフォンを見つめてね。

「ほれ立って、歌は『グズのうた』で。」とグリフォン。

「ほんとここの生き物は、ひとに何か言いつけたり、いちいちそらでやらせたりばっかり！」と思うアリス。「学校に行ってる方がまだましね。」とはいえ立ち上がってそらでやってみるわけなんだけど、頭はロブスターのカドリールでいっぱいだったので、自分が何を口走っているかほとんどわかっていなくてね、歌の文句もこんなひどくけったいになってしまって――

エビの声が　聞こえてくる
焼きすぎだ　砂糖をまぶせ
アヒルみたく　鼻を使って
おしゃれして　外またで立つ
引きしおでは　はしゃぎだし
サメをバカに　したけれど
満ちしおでは　サメが来る
声はふるえ　ぶるぶる
声はふるえ　ちぢこまる

「ガキんころによく歌ったのたあちげえな。」とグリフォン。

「うーん、聞いたこともありゃしやせんが、」とウミガメフーミ、「じんじょうでねえほどすっからかんな歌で。」

アリスは何も言えなくって。両手で顔をおおったまままたへたりこんでね、また元通りになることがはたしてあるのかどうかとなやましく。

「どういうことなのか、ときほぐしてくだせえ。」とウミガメフーミ。

「できるわけあるか。」とうろたえるグリフォン。「その続きをやってみようや。」

「でも外またってのは？」としつこいウミガメフーミ。「鼻でどうやって外に広げるってんですかい、ほれ？」

「ダンスのとき、まず足をそう置くの。」とアリス。だけど何やかやにもうひどく頭がぐちゃくちゃで、話を変えたくてしかたなく。

「その続きをやってみようや。」とじれったそうにまた言うグリフォン、「『庭先にて』からいってみよう。」またまちがうに決まってるとは思いつつも、とりあえずアリスは言うことを聞くことにして、声をふるわせながらも続きを歌ってね――

庭先にて　パイをわける
フクロウとヒョウの２ひき
パイとお肉　食べるヒョウ
フクロウは　残りのお皿
パイがすっかりなくなると
フクロウ　スプーンいただくが
せまり来るは　ヒョウのやつ
ナイフかまえ　がるるる
〆に　……

「そんなもの歌って何のねうちがあるってんだ？」と横入りするウミガメフーミ、「しかもそのまま自分ではときほぐせねえってんだ。こんなややこしさきわまるもん聞いたこともねえ！」

「そうさな、たぶんもうやめなきゃどうしようもねえな。」とグリフォン、アリスもやめられてほっとすることしきり。

「もうひと回りとしゃれこむか？」とグリフォン、「それよかお歌が好みか？」

「ええ、お歌をお願い！」とアリスの返事があまり本気なので、グリフォンもちょっときずついたみたいで、「へえ！　人も好き好きか！　『ウミガメスープ』を歌ってやれ、こんにゃろめい？」

深くため息をついたウミガメフーミは、なみだにむせびながらも歌い出す――

こくまろすうぷ　すうぷ
おなべで　ほかほか！
がまんできない　もう！
よるのすうぷ　すてきなすうぷ！
よるのすうぷ　すてきなすうぷ！
すう～うてきな　すう～ううぷ！
すう～うてきな　すう～ううぷ！
よお～おるの　す～ううぷ！
すてきな　すてきな　すううぷ！

おさかな　いらない
おにくも　ばいばい！
みんなほくほくだよ！
これでおーけぇ　すてきなすうぷ！
これでおーけぇ　すてきなすうぷ！
すう～うてきな　すう～ううぷ！
すう～うてきな　すう～ううぷ！
よお～おるの　すう～ううぷ！
すてきな　すう～うてきな　すううぷ！

「※くり返し！」とグリフォンが声をはって、ウミガメフーミがふたたび歌い始めたまさにそのとき、「おさばきの始まり！」というさけび声が遠くから聞こえてきて。

「こっちでい！」とグリフォンはアリスの手を取ってかけ出していく、歌の終わるのもまたずに。

「何？　おさばきって？」とアリスが走りながら声をふりしぼったのに、グリフォンは「こっちだ！」って返すだけでどんどん早足、追い風がふいてるせいか、そのうちますますかすかになっていくうらぶらげな声――

よお～おるの　す～ううぷ！

すてきな　すてきな　すううぷ！

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1
Chapter 2
Chapter 3
Chapter 4
Chapter 5
Chapter 6
Chapter 7
Chapter 8
Chapter 9
Chapter 10
Chapter 11
Chapter 12

Chapter 11

Click a checkbox to toggle a feature on or off in the text.

Cultural

Incorrect Word Usage

Nonsense Words

Onomatopoeia

Play on Words

Repetition

Who Stole the Tarts?

The King and Queen of Hearts were seated on their throne when they arrived, with a great crowd assembled about them--all sorts of little birds and beasts, as well as the whole pack of cards: the Knave was standing before them, in chains, with a soldier on each side to guard him; and near the King was the White Rabbit, with a trumpet in one hand, and a scroll of parchment in the other. In the very middle of the court was a table, with a large dish of tarts upon it: they looked so good, that it made Alice quite hungry to look at them--‘I wish they’d get the trial done,’ she thought, ‘and hand round the refreshments!’ But there seemed to be no chance of this, so she began looking at everything about her, to pass away the time.

Alice had never been in a court of justice before, but she had read about them in books, and she was quite pleased to find that she knew the name of nearly everything there. ‘That’s the judge,’ she said to herself, ‘because of his great wig.’

The judge, by the way, was the King; and as he wore his crown over the wig, (look at the frontispiece if you want to see how he did it,) he did not look at all comfortable, and it was certainly not becoming.

‘And that’s the jury-box,’ thought Alice, ‘and those twelve creatures,’ (she was obliged to say ‘creatures,’ you see, because some of them were animals, and some were birds,) ‘I suppose they are the jurors.’ She said this last word two or three times over to herself, being rather proud of it: for she thought, and rightly too, that very few little girls of her age knew the meaning of it at all. However, ‘jury-men’ would have done just as well.

The twelve jurors were all writing very busily on slates. ‘What are they doing?’ Alice whispered to the Gryphon. ‘They can’t have anything to put down yet, before the trial’s begun.’

‘They’re putting down their names,’ the Gryphon whispered in reply, ‘for fear they should forget them before the end of the trial.’

‘Stupid things!’ Alice began in a loud, indignant voice, but she stopped hastily, for the White Rabbit cried out, ‘Silence in the court!’ and the King put on his spectacles and looked anxiously round, to make out who was talking.

Alice could see, as well as if she were looking over their shoulders, that all the jurors were writing down ‘stupid things!’ on their slates, and she could even make out that one of them didn’t know how to spell ‘stupid,’ and that he had to ask his neighbour to tell him. ‘A nice muddle their slates’ll be in before the trial’s over!’ thought Alice.

One of the jurors had a pencil that squeaked. This of course, Alice could not stand, and she went round the court and got behind him, and very soon found an opportunity of taking it away. She did it so quickly that the poor little juror (it was Bill, the Lizard) could not make out at all what had become of it; so, after hunting all about for it, he was obliged to write with one finger for the rest of the day; and this was of very little use, as it left no mark on the slate.

‘Herald, read the accusation!’ said the King.

On this the White Rabbit blew three blasts on the trumpet, and then unrolled the parchment scroll, and read as follows:--

‘The Queen of Hearts, she made some tarts, All on a summer day: The Knave of Hearts, he stole those tarts, And took them quite away!’

‘Consider your verdict,’ the King said to the jury.

‘Not yet, not yet!’ the Rabbit hastily interrupted. ‘There’s a great deal to come before that!’

‘Call the first witness,’ said the King; and the White Rabbit blew three blasts on the trumpet, and called out, ‘First witness!’

The first witness was the Hatter. He came in with a teacup in one hand and a piece of bread-and-butter in the other. ‘I beg pardon, your Majesty,’ he began, ‘for bringing these in: but I hadn’t quite finished my tea when I was sent for.’

‘You ought to have finished,’ said the King. ‘When did you begin?’

The Hatter looked at the March Hare, who had followed him into the court, arm-in-arm with the Dormouse. ‘Fourteenth of March, I think it was,’ he said.

‘Fifteenth,’ said the March Hare.

‘Sixteenth,’ added the Dormouse.

‘Write that down,’ the King said to the jury, and the jury eagerly wrote down all three dates on their slates, and then added them up, and reduced the answer to shillings and pence.

‘Take off your hat,’ the King said to the Hatter.

‘It isn’t mine,’ said the Hatter.

‘Stolen!’ the King exclaimed, turning to the jury, who instantly made a memorandum of the fact.

‘I keep them to sell,’ the Hatter added as an explanation; ‘I’ve none of my own. I’m a hatter.’

Here the Queen put on her spectacles, and began staring at the Hatter, who turned pale and fidgeted.

‘Give your evidence,’ said the King; ‘and don’t be nervous, or I’ll have you executed on the spot.’

This did not seem to encourage the witness at all: he kept shifting from one foot to the other, looking uneasily at the Queen, and in his confusion he bit a large piece out of his teacup instead of the bread-and-butter.

Just at this moment Alice felt a very curious sensation, which puzzled her a good deal until she made out what it was: she was beginning to grow larger again, and she thought at first she would get up and leave the court; but on second thoughts she decided to remain where she was as long as there was room for her.

‘I wish you wouldn’t squeeze so.’ said the Dormouse, who was sitting next to her. ‘I can hardly breathe.’

‘I can’t help it,’ said Alice very meekly: ‘I’m growing.’

‘You’ve no right to grow here,’ said the Dormouse.

‘Don’t talk nonsense,’ said Alice more boldly: ‘you know you’re growing too.’

‘Yes, but I grow at a reasonable pace,’ said the Dormouse: ‘not in that ridiculous fashion.’ And he got up very sulkily and crossed over to the other side of the court.

All this time the Queen had never left off staring at the Hatter, and, just as the Dormouse crossed the court, she said to one of the officers of the court, ‘Bring me the list of the singers in the last concert!’ on which the wretched Hatter trembled so, that he shook both his shoes off.

‘Give your evidence,’ the King repeated angrily, ‘or I’ll have you executed, whether you’re nervous or not.’

‘I’m a poor man, your Majesty,’ the Hatter began, in a trembling voice, ‘--and I hadn’t begun my tea--not above a week or so--and what with the bread-and-butter getting so thin--and the twinkling of the tea--’

‘The twinkling of the what?’ said the King.

‘It began with the tea,’ the Hatter replied.

‘Of course twinkling begins with a T!’ said the King sharply. ‘Do you take me for a dunce? Go on!’

‘I’m a poor man,’ the Hatter went on, ‘and most things twinkled after that--only the March Hare said--’

‘I didn’t!’ the March Hare interrupted in a great hurry.

‘You did!’ said the Hatter.

‘I deny it!’ said the March Hare.

‘He denies it,’ said the King: ‘leave out that part.’

‘Well, at any rate, the Dormouse said--’ the Hatter went on, looking anxiously round to see if he would deny it too: but the Dormouse denied nothing, being fast asleep.

‘After that,’ continued the Hatter, ‘I cut some more bread-and-butter--’

‘But what did the Dormouse say?’ one of the jury asked.

‘That I can’t remember,’ said the Hatter.

‘You MUST remember,’ remarked the King, ‘or I’ll have you executed.’

The miserable Hatter dropped his teacup and bread-and-butter, and went down on one knee. ‘I’m a poor man, your Majesty,’ he began.

‘You’re a very poor speaker,’ said the King.

Here one of the guinea-pigs cheered, and was immediately suppressed by the officers of the court. (As that is rather a hard word, I will just explain to you how it was done. They had a large canvas bag, which tied up at the mouth with strings: into this they slipped the guinea-pig, head first, and then sat upon it.)

‘I’m glad I’ve seen that done,’ thought Alice. ‘I’ve so often read in the newspapers, at the end of trials, “There was some attempts at applause, which was immediately suppressed by the officers of the court,” and I never understood what it meant till now.’

‘If that’s all you know about it, you may stand down,’ continued the King.

‘I can’t go no lower,’ said the Hatter: ‘I’m on the floor, as it is.’

‘Then you may SIT down,’ the King replied.

Here the other guinea-pig cheered, and was suppressed.

‘Come, that finished the guinea-pigs!’ thought Alice. ‘Now we shall get on better.’

‘I’d rather finish my tea,’ said the Hatter, with an anxious look at the Queen, who was reading the list of singers.

‘You may go,’ said the King, and the Hatter hurriedly left the court, without even waiting to put his shoes on.

‘--and just take his head off outside,’ the Queen added to one of the officers: but the Hatter was out of sight before the officer could get to the door.

‘Call the next witness!’ said the King.

The next witness was the Duchess’s cook. She carried the pepper-box in her hand, and Alice guessed who it was, even before she got into the court, by the way the people near the door began sneezing all at once.

‘Give your evidence,’ said the King.

‘Shan’t,’ said the cook.

The King looked anxiously at the White Rabbit, who said in a low voice, ‘Your Majesty must cross-examine THIS witness.’

‘Well, if I must, I must,’ the King said, with a melancholy air, and, after folding his arms and frowning at the cook till his eyes were nearly out of sight, he said in a deep voice, ‘What are tarts made of?’

‘Pepper, mostly,’ said the cook.

‘Treacle,’ said a sleepy voice behind her.

‘Collar that Dormouse,’ the Queen shrieked out. ‘Behead that Dormouse! Turn that Dormouse out of court! Suppress him! Pinch him! Off with his whiskers!’

For some minutes the whole court was in confusion, getting the Dormouse turned out, and, by the time they had settled down again, the cook had disappeared.

‘Never mind!’ said the King, with an air of great relief. ‘Call the next witness.’ And he added in an undertone to the Queen, ‘Really, my dear, YOU must cross-examine the next witness. It quite makes my forehead ache!’

Alice watched the White Rabbit as he fumbled over the list, feeling very curious to see what the next witness would be like, ‘--for they haven’t got much evidence YET,’ she said to herself. Imagine her surprise, when the White Rabbit read out, at the top of his shrill little voice, the name ‘Alice!’

　だあれがタルトをぬすんだの

着くと、キングとクイーンが高いところにすわっていて、そのまわりにはおおぜいがお集まり――ありとある鳥さんけものさん、それにもちろんひとそろいのトランプも。ジャックがその前に立たされて、くさりにつながれたままで、左右を強者にかためられていてね。それにキングのわきにはあの白ウサギ、片手にトランペット、もう片手に羊の皮のまき紙。おさばきの場のどまんなかにあるテーブル、その上にタルトをのせた大皿が１まい。見ばえがすごくよかったのでアリスは見るなりはらぺこになっちゃってね――「おさばきなんてとうに終わって、」とか思う、「おやつでも配ってくれたらいいのに！」ところがそんな段取りはどうにもないみたいで、そこでとりあえずまわりをしらみつぶしにながめてひまつぶし。

アリスもおさばきの場自体、ものの本では読んだことがあるだけで、来たのは初めてだったけど、そこにいただいたいのやつらが顔見知りとわかってたいへんほっとしてね。「あれがさばきを下すひと、」とひとりごと、「だって大きなカツラだし。」

ところでそのさばきを下すひとこそキングそのひと。カツラの上に王さまのかんむりをちょこん（どんな具合かたしかめたいひとははじめにある大きな絵を見てね）、どう見てもすわりが悪く、明らかに 似合 ってなくて。

「それとあれが、話し合うひとの 座席 ね。」と思うアリス、「それに、生き物が１２ひき。」（やむをえず「生き物」と口にしたんだけど、ほら、何せけものもいれば鳥もいるからね、）「つまり 裁判員 。」この言葉を２度３度自分に言い聞かせては、ちょっぴりほこらしげ。だって、無理もないのだけれど、ふつう同い年の女の子たちにはそんなことわかる子なんていないと思ってたからね。どんなおさばきを下すか話し合う人たちのことなんだけど。

１２ひきの裁判員はみんなせわしなく手持ち黒板に何か書き付けていて。「何をしてるの？」とアリスがグリフォンにひそひそ。「何も書きとめることなんてないはずなのに、おさばきが始まるまで。」

「自分の名前を書き付けてんだ、」と返事するグリフォンもひそひそ、「お開きになるより先にわすれちまうとこまるからな。」

「バッカみたい！」アリスの声にもいらいらがこもりだしたんだけど、あわててこらえてね、だって白ウサギが声をはりあげて「お 静 かに！」って、それからキングもメガネをかけて、そわそわながめまわして、声の主をつきとめようとしたものだから。

アリスの目からは、そいつらのかたごしに見える感じなんだけど、裁判員はみんな「バカみたい！」と手持ち黒板に書きとめていてね、そのうちひとりが「バカみたい」をどういう字で書くのかわかっていないのもこっちに見て取れて、どうもとなりに教えてとたのみこむ羽目になったみたいで。「お開きうんぬんの前にあの黒板がめためたになりそう！」と思うアリス。

それに裁判員のひとりが、チョークをきぃきぃ言わせていたんだ。これにはもちろんアリスはたえきれなくって、おさばきの場をぐるっと回り、そいつの背後に立って、すきをねらってさっと取り上げてしまってね。あまりのすばやい手ぎわに、かわいそうに裁判員（トカゲのビル）さんには何が何だかさっぱりわからず、そこであたりを探し回ったあげく、しかたなく最後まで指１本で書くことにしたのに、まったく役に立たずで黒板には何のあともつかない。

「しきり役！　おかされた罪を読み上げよ！」とキング。

これを受けて、白ウサギはトランペットを３ふき、それからまき紙を広げて、こう読み上げる――

ハートのクインがタルトを作る
夏のさなか１日かけて
ハートのジャックがタルトをぬすむ
かくれてこっそりひとりじめ！

「さあ、おさばきを話し合え。」と裁判員へつげるキング。

「まだ、まだで！」と、あわてて止める白ウサギ。「その前にやることがたっくさんおじゃりまする！」

「ひとりめにわけを聞くぞえ。」とキング。すると白ウサギはトランペットを３ふき、声をはりあげる。「ひとりめ！」

はじめにわけを話すのは、ぼうし屋。入ってくると手にはティーカップ、もう片手にはバターのぬられたパン。「失礼をば、キングさま。」と切り出してね、「このようなものを持ちこみ。ですが、よばれたさいは、お茶会のまっ最中でしたもので。」

「すませておくべきであるぞ。」とキング。「いつ始めた？」

ぼうし屋がヤヨイウサギに目をやると、あとから入ってきたそいつはヤマネとうでを組んでいてね。「３月１４日です、おそらくは。」とぼうし屋。

「１５日。」とヤヨイウサギ。

「１６日。」とヤマネ。

「書きとめよ。」と裁判員へつげるキング。すると裁判員は 熱心 にその３つの日付を手持ち黒板に書きとめ、そのあと足し算して、その和をお金の単位たんいに直したんだ。

「それを取れ、その 方 の帽子じゃ！」とキングはぼうし屋へ言いつけてね。

「わがものではなく。」とぼうし屋。

「ぬすみおったか！」とさけぶキング、裁判員の方を向くと、すぐさま一同はこのことをひかえる。

「これは売り物で。」と言いわけをあとからするぼうし屋。「わがものではなく、ぼうし屋でありますゆえ。」

ここでクイーンはメガネをかけ、ぼうし屋をじぃとにらみつけるたので、ぼうし屋も心おだやかでなく、顔もまっ 青 。

「はよう次第をのべよ、」とキング、「びくびくするでない、さもなくばただちに処すぞ。」

これで相手に先をうながせるわけもなくてね。足の重心を左右に行ったり来たりさせつつ、そわそわとクイーンを見やるんだけど、取りみだすあまり本当ならパンをかじるところを、ティーカップをがりっといっちゃって。

ちょうどこのときなんだけど、アリスはひどくぞくぞくして、へんてこな気分になってね、自分でもしばらくなぜだかちっともわからなかったんだけど、どういうことなのかとうとうわかった。また身体が大きくなりだしていてね、ひとまず立ち上がって 席 を外そうかと思ったんだけど考え直して、ぎりぎりすわれるまではそこにいすわることにしたんだ。

「そんなにつめないでくださいな。」と、となりにすわっていたヤマネが言ってね。「息苦しい。」

「どうしようもないの。」と、とてもすなおなアリス。「育ちざかりなんだもん。」

「だからって、ここで勝手に大きくなるなです。」とヤマネ。

「すっからかんな言い分。」と今度はアリスもふてぶてしい。「ほら、あなただって育つんだから。」

「そうですけど大きくなるかげんはわきまえてますよ。」とヤマネ。「そんなふざけた育ち方なんてしません。」そうしてひどくむっとして席を立つと、さばきの場の向かいがわへまたいでいってしまって。

このあいだずっとクイーンはたえずぼうし屋をにらみつけていてね、ちょうどヤマネがおさばきの場をまたいだときに、その場にひかえていたやつへこう申しつける、「先の音楽会の歌い手の名ぼを持って参れ！」するととたんに、あわれにもぼうし屋はぶるぶるふるえだして、両足ともくつがぬげてしまう始末。

「次第をのべよ。」とくり返すキングはかんかん、「さもなくばびくびくのいかんを問わず処すぞ。」

「わがはいはつまらぬものです、キングさま。」と話し出したぼうし屋はふるえ声、「それにお茶を始めてより――まだ１週間もございません――パンは次第にかっぴかぴとなり――てぇかてかのお茶……」

「てぇかの、何とな。」とキング。

「お茶のことにございますか。」と答えるぼうし屋。

「ふむ、そりゃお茶は『てぇ』とも言うわい！」とキングの声はとげとげしい。「わしをバカにしておるのか？　続けよ！」

「わがはいはつまらぬものですが、」と続けるぼうし屋、「そのあとあちこちがてかてかと――ただヤヨイウサギが申すには……」

「言わねえ！」と大あわてで口をはさむヤヨイウサギ。

「言った！」とぼうし屋。

「まちがいだ！」とヤヨイウサギ。

「まちがいか。」とキング。「ではその部分を消すがよい。」

「ではとにかくヤマネが申すには……」と続けたぼうし屋が気づかわしげにあたりを見て、まちがいと申し立てられないかとたしかめるも、ヤマネは何も申し立てずぐっすりすやすや。

「そのあと、」とそのまま話し出すぼうし屋、「わがはいはバターのぬられたパンをもう少しとちぎりまして……」

「あの、ヤマネは何と言ったんで？」と裁判員のひとりがたずねる。

「それが思い出せず。」とぼうし屋。

「思い出さねば、」と言い出すキング、「処すぞ！」

あわれにもぼうし屋はティーカップとパンを落として、片ひざをついてね。「わがはいはつまらぬものでございます、キングさま。」と言い出すんだけど。

「 たしかにその 方 の話はつまらん！」とキング。

ここでモルモットが１ぴき手をぱちぱちとたたいたんだけど、ひかえていたやつらにたちまち取りおさえられてね。（っていうのはちょっとややこしい言い方かな、どうなったのかちゃんと話すね。大きくしっかりした布のふくろ、口のところをひもでしばるやつをもってきて、そのなかにモルモットを頭から取り入れて、その上からすわっておさえたんだ。）

「うれしい、こんなの見られるなんて。」と思うアリス。「新聞では読んだことあったけど、おさばきの終わりに『ざわめくもたちまちひかえていた役人によって取り押さえられた』って、今ようやくなるほどとなってよ。」

「それだけしか知らんのなら、もう下がるがよい。」と先を続けるキング。

「これより下へは行けません。」とぼうし屋。「ゆかをつきぬけろとおっしゃる？」

「ならば、しりをゆかにつけい。」と答えるキング。

ここでもう１ぴきのモルモットが手をたたいたが、また取りおさえられる。

「ふうん、これでモルモットはみんな片づいたってわけ！」と思うアリス。「ようやくおさばきもはかどってよ。」

「よろしければお茶の方をすませても。」と言うぼうし屋は、気づかわしげにクイーンを見やったけれど、歌い手の名ぼを読みふっていて。

「かまわん行け。」とキングが言うので、ぼうし屋はかけ足でおさばきの場をあとにしたんだけど、くつをはき直すのをどわすれしちゃった。

「……そして外でやつの首をはねよ！」と追ってクイーンはひかえている者に言いつけたんだけど、ひかえの者がドアにたどりつくより先にもう、ぼうし屋のすがたはどこへやら。

「次のもの入れ！」とキング。

その次にわけを聞くのは御前さまのコック。手にコショウびんを持っていてね、アリスはそのひとが入ってくる前からだれだか当てがついたんだけど、それというのもドア付近のひとたちがみんないっせいにくしゃみをしたから。

「そこなもの、わけを話せ。」とキング。

「まっぴらだね！」とコック。

キングの気づかわしげな目にさらされて、白ウサギが小声で、「やむをえませぬ、反対にご自身からこの者に次第をたずねてみては。」

「ふむ、やむをえぬならやむをえぬ。」とだるそうなキングはうで組みをして、コックにまゆをしかめるんだけど、そのせいで目はほとんど皮にうもれてしまってね、重々しい声で言うんだ、「タルトは何でできておる？」

「だいたいコショウさ。」とコック。

「シロップです。」とその後ろからねむたげな声。

「そのヤマネを首ねっこじゃ！」と声をしぼり上げるクイーン。「そのヤマネは打ち首じゃ！　そのヤマネをつまみ出せ！　取りおさえよ！　しょっぴけ！　ヒゲをちょん切れええ！」

しばらくのあいだ、おさばきの場はしっちゃかめっちゃか、ヤマネは外へつまみ出され、みんながもとの場所にもどったころには、コックもすがたを消していて。

「かまうな！」とキングは大きくほっと息をついてね。「次のものをよべい。」それから、そのあとクイーンに向かって、おさえた声音で、「やむをえん、実はの、次はおまえがたずねる役をやってくれんか。ひどくしかめっ痛つうがするのでな！」

アリスが様子をうかがっていると、白ウサギが名ぼをいじいじしていたので、次によばれるのがどんなひとなのかとってもわくわくしてきてね、「――だって事と次第があんまりはっきりしてないもん、まだ。」とひとりごと。どんなにその子がびっくりしたことか、そのとき白ウサギが読み上げた、ふりしぼって声高にさけんだ名前はなんと、「アリス！」

Home
About
Texts
Conclusions

Chapter 1 | Chapter 2 | Chapter 3 | Chapter 4 | Chapter 5 | Chapter 6 | Chapter 7 | Chapter 8 | Chapter 9 | Chapter 10 | Chapter 11 | Chapter 12

Chapter 12

Alice’s Evidence

‘Here!’ cried Alice, quite forgetting in the flurry of the moment how large she had grown in the last few minutes, and she jumped up in such a hurry that she tipped over the jury-box with the edge of her skirt, upsetting all the jurymen on to the heads of the crowd below, and there they lay sprawling about, reminding her very much of a globe of goldfish she had accidentally upset the week before.

‘Oh, I BEG your pardon!’ she exclaimed in a tone of great dismay, and began picking them up again as quickly as she could, for the accident of the goldfish kept running in her head, and she had a vague sort of idea that they must be collected at once and put back into the jury-box, or they would die.

‘The trial cannot proceed,’ said the King in a very grave voice, ‘until all the jurymen are back in their proper places--ALL,’ he repeated with great emphasis, looking hard at Alice as he said do.

Alice looked at the jury-box, and saw that, in her haste, she had put the Lizard in head downwards, and the poor little thing was waving its tail about in a melancholy way, being quite unable to move. She soon got it out again, and put it right; ‘not that it signifies much,’ she said to herself; ‘I should think it would be QUITE as much use in the trial one way up as the other.’

As soon as the jury had a little recovered from the shock of being upset, and their slates and pencils had been found and handed back to them, they set to work very diligently to write out a history of the accident, all except the Lizard, who seemed too much overcome to do anything but sit with its mouth open, gazing up into the roof of the court.

‘What do you know about this business?’ the King said to Alice.

‘Nothing,’ said Alice.

‘Nothing WHATEVER?’ persisted the King.

‘Nothing whatever,’ said Alice.

‘That’s very important,’ the King said, turning to the jury. They were just beginning to write this down on their slates, when the White Rabbit interrupted: ‘UNimportant, your Majesty means, of course,’ he said in a very respectful tone, but frowning and making faces at him as he spoke.

‘UNimportant, of course, I meant,’ the King hastily said, and went on to himself in an undertone,‘important--unimportant--unimportant--important--’ as if he were trying which word sounded best.

Some of the jury wrote it down ‘important,’ and some ‘unimportant.’ Alice could see this, as she was near enough to look over their slates; ‘but it doesn’t matter a bit,’ she thought to herself.

At this moment the King, who had been for some time busily writing in his note-book, cackled out ‘Silence!’ and read out from his book, ‘Rule Forty-two. ALL PERSONS MORE THAN A MILE HIGH TO LEAVE THE COURT.’

Everybody looked at Alice.

‘I’M not a mile high,’ said Alice.

‘You are,’ said the King.

‘Nearly two miles high,’ added the Queen.

‘Well, I shan’t go, at any rate,’ said Alice: ‘besides, that’s not a regular rule: you invented it just now.’

‘It’s the oldest rule in the book,’ said the King.

‘Then it ought to be Number One,’ said Alice.

The King turned pale, and shut his note-book hastily. ‘Consider your verdict,’ he said to the jury, in a low, trembling voice.

‘There’s more evidence to come yet, please your Majesty,’ said the White Rabbit, jumping up in a great hurry; ‘this paper has just been picked up.’

‘What’s in it?’ said the Queen.

‘I haven’t opened it yet,’ said the White Rabbit, ‘but it seems to be a letter, written by the prisoner to--to somebody.’

‘It must have been that,’ said the King, ‘unless it was written to nobody, which isn’t usual, you know.’

‘Who is it directed to?’ said one of the jurymen.

‘It isn’t directed at all,’ said the White Rabbit; ‘in fact, there’s nothing written on the OUTSIDE.’ He unfolded the paper as he spoke, and added ‘It isn’t a letter, after all: it’s a set of verses.’

‘Are they in the prisoner’s handwriting?’ asked another of the jurymen.

‘No, they’re not,’ said the White Rabbit, ‘and that’s the queerest thing about it.’ (The jury all looked puzzled.)

‘He must have imitated somebody else’s hand,’ said the King. (The jury all brightened up again.)

‘Please your Majesty,’ said the Knave, ‘I didn’t write it, and they can’t prove I did: there’s no name signed at the end.’

‘If you didn’t sign it,’ said the King, ‘that only makes the matter worse. You MUST have meant some mischief, or else you’d have signed your name like an honest man.’

There was a general clapping of hands at this: it was the first really clever thing the King had said that day.

‘That PROVES his guilt,’ said the Queen.

‘It proves nothing of the sort!’ said Alice. ‘Why, you don’t even know what they’re about!’

‘Read them,’ said the King.

The White Rabbit put on his spectacles. ‘Where shall I begin, please your Majesty?’ he asked.

‘Begin at the beginning,’ the King said gravely, ‘and go on till you come to the end: then stop.’

These were the verses the White Rabbit read:--

‘They told me you had been to her,
And mentioned me to him:
She gave me a good character,
But said I could not swim.

He sent them word I had not gone
(We know it to be true):
If she should push the matter on,
What would become of you?

I gave her one, they gave him two,
You gave us three or more;
They all returned from him to you,
Though they were mine before.

If I or she should chance to be
Involved in this affair,
He trusts to you to set them free,
Exactly as we were.

My notion was that you had been
(Before she had this fit)
An obstacle that came between Him,
and ourselves, and it.

Don’t let him know she liked them best,
For this must ever be
A secret, kept from all the rest,
Between yourself and me.’

‘That’s the most important piece of evidence we’ve heard yet,’ said the King, rubbing his hands; ‘so now let the jury--’

‘If any one of them can explain it,’ said Alice, (she had grown so large in the last few minutes that she wasn’t a bit afraid of interrupting him,) ‘I’ll give him sixpence. I don’t believe there’s an atom of meaning in it.’

The jury all wrote down on their slates, ‘SHE doesn’t believe there’s an atom of meaning in it,’ but none of them attempted to explain the paper.

‘If there’s no meaning in it,’ said the King, ‘that saves a world of trouble, you know, as we needn’t try to find any. And yet I don’t know,’ he went on, spreading out the verses on his knee, and looking at them with one eye; ‘I seem to see some meaning in them, after all. “--SAID I COULD NOT SWIM--” you can’t swim, can you?’ he added, turning to the Knave.

The Knave shook his head sadly. ‘Do I look like it?’ he said. (Which he certainly did NOT, being made entirely of cardboard.)

‘All right, so far,’ said the King, and he went on muttering over the verses to himself: ‘“ WE KNOW IT TO BE TRUE-- ” that’s the jury, of course--“ I GAVE HER ONE, THEY GAVE HIM TWO-- ” why, that must be what he did with the tarts, you know--’

‘But, it goes on “ THEY ALL RETURNED FROM HIM TO YOU, ”’ said Alice.

‘Why, there they are!’ said the King triumphantly, pointing to the tarts on the table. ‘Nothing can be clearer than THAT. Then again--“BEFORE SHE HAD THIS FIT--” you never had fits, my dear, I think?’ he said to the Queen.

‘Never!’ said the Queen furiously, throwing an inkstand at the Lizard as she spoke. (The unfortunate little Bill had left off writing on his slate with one finger, as he found it made no mark; but he now hastily began again, using the ink, that was trickling down his face, as long as it lasted.)

‘Then the words don’t FIT you,’ said the King, looking round the court with a smile. There was a dead silence.

‘It’s a pun!’ the King added in an offended tone, and everybody laughed, ‘Let the jury consider their verdict,’ the King said, for about the twentieth time that day.

‘No, no!’ said the Queen. ‘Sentence first--verdict afterwards.’

‘Stuff and nonsense!’ said Alice loudly. ‘The idea of having the sentence first!’

‘Hold your tongue!’ said the Queen, turning purple.

‘I won’t!’ said Alice.

‘Off with her head!’ the Queen shouted at the top of her voice. Nobody moved.

‘Who cares for you?’ said Alice, (she had grown to her full size by this time.) ‘You’re nothing but a pack of cards!’

At this the whole pack rose up into the air, and came flying down upon her: she gave a little scream, half of fright and half of anger, and tried to beat them off, and found herself lying on the bank, with her head in the lap of her sister, who was gently brushing away some dead leaves that had fluttered down from the trees upon her face.

‘Wake up, Alice dear!’ said her sister; ‘Why, what a long sleep you’ve had!’

‘Oh, I’ve had such a curious dream!’ said Alice, and she told her sister, as well as she could remember them, all these strange Adventures of hers that you have just been reading about; and when she had finished, her sister kissed her, and said, ‘It WAS a curious dream, dear, certainly: but now run in to your tea; it’s getting late.’ So Alice got up and ran off, thinking while she ran, as well she might, what a wonderful dream it had been.

But her sister sat still just as she left her, leaning her head on her hand, watching the setting sun, and thinking of little Alice and all her wonderful Adventures, till she too began dreaming after a fashion, and this was her dream:--

First, she dreamed of little Alice herself, and once again the tiny hands were clasped upon her knee, and the bright eager eyes were looking up into hers--she could hear the very tones of her voice, and see that queer little toss of her head to keep back the wandering hair that WOULD always get into her eyes--and still as she listened, or seemed to listen, the whole place around her became alive with the strange creatures of her little sister’s dream.

The long grass rustled at her feet as the White Rabbit hurried by--the frightened Mouse splashed his way through the neighbouring pool--she could hear the rattle of the teacups as the March Hare and his friends shared their never-ending meal, and the shrill voice of the Queen ordering off her unfortunate guests to execution--once more the pig-baby was sneezing on the Duchess’s knee, while plates and dishes crashed around it--once more the shriek of the Gryphon, the squeaking of the Lizard’s slate-pencil, and the choking of the suppressed guinea-pigs, filled the air, mixed up with the distant sobs of the miserable Mock Turtle.

So she sat on, with closed eyes, and half believed herself in Wonderland, though she knew she had but to open them again, and all would change to dull reality--the grass would be only rustling in the wind, and the pool rippling to the waving of the reeds--the rattling teacups would change to tinkling sheep-bells, and the Queen’s shrill cries to the voice of the shepherd boy--and the sneeze of the baby, the shriek of the Gryphon, and all the other queer noises, would change (she knew) to the confused clamour of the busy farm-yard--while the lowing of the cattle in the distance would take the place of the Mock Turtle’s heavy sobs.

Lastly, she pictured to herself how this same little sister of hers would, in the after-time, be herself a grown woman; and how she would keep, through all her riper years, the simple and loving heart of her childhood: and how she would gather about her other little children, and make THEIR eyes bright and eager with many a strange tale, perhaps even with the dream of Wonderland of long ago: and how she would feel with all their simple sorrows, and find a pleasure in all their simple joys, remembering her own child-life, and the happy summer days.

　アリスがわけを語る

「ここです！」と声を上げるアリス、とっさのことであたふた、この数分で自分の図体がどれだけでっかく育っていたかどわすれしちゃっててね、あんまりあわてて立ち上がったものだから、スカートのすそがひっかかっちゃって裁判員のいる箱形の 座席 が 横転 、裁判員全員が下でおさばきを聞いているひとたちの頭上にすってんころりん、そのときのみんなは手足をじたばたさせていたので、思わず先週うっかりひっくりかえした金魚ばちのことがものすごく重なってね。

「あら、ごめんあそばせ！」と口をついて出るもののどうにもあたふた、大急ぎでひろい上げはじめてね、だって金魚でのうっかりがずっと頭にあったから、なんとなくそう思えたんだ、すぐにひろい集めて座席にもどさないと死んじゃうって。

「おさばきが進められんな。」と言うキングの声はものものしい、「裁判員みなをおのおのの持ち場にちゃあんともどすまで――みなをな。」と最後のところを力強くねんおししつつ、アリスをじろり。

アリスが座席に目をやると、見えたのは、あわてていたからか、頭から 逆 さにつきささったトカゲ、このかわいそうなやつは、しおしおとしっぽをふりふり、身動きがまったく取れてなくって。もう１度ぬき出してからちゃんと入れ直す。「さして大した差でもないのに。」とひとりごと。「たぶんそもそもおさばきの役に立ちようがないし、どっちが上でも。」

ひっくり返されたどきどきからいささか立ち直った裁判員一同、見つかった手持ち黒板とチョークを手元に置いたとたん、せっせと仕事に取りかかってね、みんなしてこの 事故 のいきさつを書き出したんだけど、トカゲだけは別、すっかり参ってしまったのか、できることといえば、こしを下ろして口をあんぐり、おさばきの場の天井をぼんやり見上げるばかり。

「事と次第について何を知っておる？」とキングからアリスへ。

「なんっにも。」とアリス。

「これっぽちもないか？」としつこいキング。

「これっぽちも。」とアリス。

「なんとよしありげな。」とキングは裁判員へと顔を向けてね。みんなそのことを黒板に書き出したところへ、白ウサギが口をはさむ。「よしなし、とのつもりでおじゃりましたか。」と言葉こそうやうやしいけど、話すあいだもみけんにしわでしかめっ面。

「よしなし、とのつもりであったぞよ。」とあわてて口にするキング、ぼそぼそと続けるひとりごと、「よしあり――よしなし――よしなし――よしあり……」どっちが聞こえがいいのか品定めしてるみたいに。

裁判員には「よしあり」と書きとめた者もあれば「よしなし」とした者もいて。かろうじて黒板をのぞけるところにいたアリスは、これを見て、「どのみち大差なくてよ。」とひとり思う。

このときのキング、しばらくいそいそと手元のメモに何かをしたためてたんだけど、いきなり声を出してね、「静まれ！」って、それからそのメモを読み上げたんだ、「決まりその４２。『背たけが１．６キロをこえた者は何ぴともおさばきから 退場 とする。』」

みんながアリスに目をやる。

「あたくし、１．６キロもなくってよ。」とアリス。

「ある。」とキング。

「３キロ近くはある。」と後おしするクイーン。

「ふん、出て行かないもん、ぜったい。」とアリス。「それにちゃんとした決まりでなくてよ。たった今でっち上げたんだから。」

「ここに記されたものでもいちばん古い決まりじゃ。」とキング。

「なら、決まりその１のはずじゃなくって。」とアリス。

顔を青くしたキングは、あわててメモ帳をとじる。「では、おさばきを話し合え。」とふるふる小声で裁判員に。

「まだまだやることがおじゃりまする、キングさま。」と白ウサギはとび上がって大あわて。「このような紙が今しがたとどいておじゃります。」

「中には何と？」とクイーン。

「まだ開けておじゃりませんが、」と白ウサギ、「おそらくは手紙かと、とがびとの手になる――だれかしらあての。」

「そうにちがいなかろう、」とキング、「あて名がないのでないかぎりは。まあまずあるがな、ほれ。」

「だれにあてたものなんです？」と裁判員のひとり。

「あて先が何もないでおじゃる。」と白ウサギ。「むしろ、そとみには字は何もおじゃりません。」と言いながら紙を広げると言葉をついで、「つまるところ手紙でないでおじゃる、これはひと続きのポエム。」

「字の書き方はとがびとのものですか？」と裁判員がもうひとり。

「いえ、ちがうでおじゃる、」と白ウサギ、「そこがたいそうけったいで。」（裁判員はみなハテナだらけのお顔。）

「だれかしらの字の書き方をまねたにちがいない。」とキング。（裁判員みな顔がまたぱっと明るくなる。）

「申し上げます、キングさま、」とジャック、「わたくしめは書いてません、そうだと言い切れるだけのものもないでしょう？　終わりに名前もそえられてないんですから。」

「名前がないならば、」とキング、「よけいに事はまずくなるぞよ。つまりおぬしはお痛いたをしたことになる。でなければ、いい子としてちゃんと自分の名をそえるはずだからな。」

これにはその場一同の手からぱちぱちぱち、キングがこの日初めてほんとにうまいことを言ったもんでね。

「はっきりした、やったのはおまえぞ、もちろん。」とクイーン。「では首をちょ……」

「そんなの何もはっきりしてなくってよ！」とアリス。「ふん、何が書かれてあるかもわかってないのに！」

「読み上げよ。」とキング。

白ウサギはメガネをかけてね。「キングさま、どこからお始めに？」とたずねる。

「はじめから始めよ。」とのべるキングはものものしい。「そして続けて、とうとう終わりに来たら、そこでやめよ。」

静まりかえるおさばきの場、そのなかで白ウサギが読み上げたのは次のポエム――

あいつらの話じゃ　あの女のところで
おれのことを　あの男にしゃべったそうだな
あの女はおれを　いいやつと言ったが
おれは泳げないと　言いくさる

あの男があいつらに、　おまえはでかけて
ないと伝えたぞ（おれたちにもたしかなことだ）
あの女がことを　おし進めたら
おまえはいったい　どうなるやら

おれ→あの女は１　やつら→あの男は２
おまえ→おれたちは３　いやもっとだ
あいつらみんなもどる　あの男→おれへ
もともとそいつらは　おれのものだったがな

まんがいち　おれとあの女が
この 件 に　まきこまれでもしたら
あの男はおまえに　やつらのあつかいをまかす
おれたちのときと　まったく同じだ

おれが思うに　それまでおまえは
（あの女が　かっかするまでは）
出しゃばって　じゃまするつもりだったんだろ
あの男と　おれらとそれのあいだを

あの男にはもらすなよ　あの女の１番びいきが
あいつらだって　だってそりゃあ
ひみつに決まってる　だれにも言うなよ
おまえとおれ　ふたりだけのないしょだ

「今まで聞いたなかでも、いちばんのよしありげなわけじゃぞ。」とキングは手をもみもみ、「では今こそ裁判員よ……」

「そこのだれかがこのポエムを読みとけたら、」とアリス（このほんの数分でたいへん大きくなっていたので、まったく物おじもせず口をはさんでね）、「 銀貨 １まいあげてもよくてよ。こんなのこれっぽちの意味もないと思うけれど。」

裁判員もみんな手持ちの黒板に書きとめてね、「こんなのこれっぽちの意味もないと思うと女。」ところがそのうちのだれもその紙を読みとこうとはしない。

「もし意味がないのだとすれば、」とキング、「すさまじく手間がはぶけるぞ、ほれ、何も探らんでよくなるからの。とはいえどうなのかの。」と続けて、ひざ上にそのポエムを広げ、片目でじっと見てみるも、「どうにも何かしらの意味はありそうじゃ、やはり。『……おれは泳げないと言いくさる……』おまえは泳げないのだったな。」と言葉をついで、ジャックに顔を向ける。

ジャックは悲しげにかぶりをふって。「見ての通りですよ。」と返事。（たしかにできそうにない、まったくの 厚紙 だからね。）

「ここまではよろしい。」とキング、そしてひとりごとみたくぶつぶつそのポエムを読んでいく。「『おれたちにもたしかなことだ』――これはもちろん裁判員のことじゃな――『あの女がことをおし進めたら』――これはクイーンのことにちがいない――『おまえはいったいどうなるやら』――おお、まったくだ！――『おれ→あの女は１　やつら→あの男は２』――ほほう、こうしてやつはパイをよろしくしたわけか、ほれ……」

「でも続きに『あいつらみんなもどる　あの男→おれへ』って。」とアリス。

「うむ、だからそこにある！」とキングはしたり顔でテーブルのタルトを指さす。「これほど明らかなことはないとも。そののちまた――『あの女がかっかするまでは』――おまえや、 かっか したことなどないじゃろ？」と言葉をクイーンへ向ける。

「ない！」と言いながらもクイーンはとちくるってインクびんをトカゲに投げつけてね。（とんだ目にあったビルくん、黒板から指で書くのをやめていてね、何も書けないと気づいたからなんだけど、でもこうなってあわててまた取りかかって、顔からしたたるインクを使ってとうとう使い切った。）

「まあ『かっか』というよりは『へいか』じゃしのう。」とキングはおさばきの場を見回しつつ、にやり。あたりは死んだようにしーん。

「だじゃれじゃ！」と続けてキングはむすっとすると、みんな大笑い。

「さて裁判員よ、おさばきの話し合いだ。」とキングは言うんだけど、これこの日でもう２０回目くらいにはなるかな。

「いいえっ！」とクイーン、「言いわたすのが先――話し合いは後あと！」

「がらくたのすっからかん！」とアリスの大声、「言いわたすのが先だなんて！」

「だまらっしゃい！」と 血相 を変えるクイーン。

「だまらない！」とアリス。

「このむすめの首をちょん切れ！」とクイーンがありったけの裏声をはる。ひとりも動かない。

「だれが言うこと聞いて？」とアリス（このときまでに元々の背たけになっていてね）。「あんたたちみたいなただのトランプ！」

せつな、トランプがいっせいにおどり上がり、空からふりそそいでくる。きゃッと、びくつき半分、むかつき半分で打ちはらおうとしたら、気づけばもとの木かげ、お姉さまにひざまくら、木から頭にひらひら落ちかかっていたかれ葉をやさしく取りはらってくれていて。

「起きて、アリスちゃん。」とお姉さま、「もう、長々としたお昼ねだこと。」

「ねえ、あたくしもう、へんってこなゆめ見てたの！」とアリスはお姉さまに自分がおぼえているかぎりのことを、自分のとっぴなめぐり歩きを、ここまで読んできた通りぜんぶおしゃべり、終わるとお姉さまはキスをしてくれてね、こう言うんだ。「へんてこなゆめだったのね、ほんと。でもすぐにお茶へかけ足しないと、このままだとちこくよ。」というわけで、アリスは起き上がってかけ足、走りながら心のなかは、そりゃやっぱり、これまでのふしぎなゆめのことでいっぱい。

ところがお姉さまは妹がはなれていったあともじっとすわったまま、ほおづえをついて夕ぐれをながめながら、小さなアリスとふしぎめぐりの道行きを考えているうち、今度は自分もうつらうつらゆめを見始めてね、そのゆめっていうのはこう――

はじめにゆめ見るのは、その小さなアリスのこと。何度となく小さなお手々をこちらのひざの上でにぎりながら、さらにきらきら わくわく上目づかいでのぞきこんでくる――聞こえるのはあのいつもの声音、目に入るのは頭をつんと上げるあのけったいなくせ、いつも毛がちらかってどうしても目に入ってしまうからってそうやって元にもどそうとするんだ――そしてじっと耳をかたむける、たぶんかたむけるうちに、そのまわりのあちこちが、小さな妹のゆめのなかのとっぴな生き物でにぎやかになってくる。

長い草が足下でがさごそ、白ウサギがあわててかけてゆく――びくびくネズミがばしゃばしゃ、そばの池を進んでいて――聞こえてくるティーカップのかちゃかちゃ、ヤヨイウサギとなかまたちは、いっしょにいつまでも終わらないお茶会中、そのあとクイーンがきぃきぃ声でかわいそうに来たひとみんなを処すとか言いだして――またもやブタの赤ちゃんが御前さまのおひざでくしゅん、そこへ大皿小皿ががちゃんばりん――ふたたびグリフォンの鳴き声、トカゲの黒板チョークのきーきー、さらに取りおさえられたモルモットのもがく声があたりにひびき、そこへかなたからまじり合うあわれなウミガメフーミのさめざめ。

だからじっとしたまま、ひとみをとじていると、もう 半 ばふしぎの国にいるようで、目をいまひとたび開けてしまえば、つまらない 現実 にみんな変わってしまうとわかっているのに――草はきっと風でかさかさしてるだけで、池がそよぐ草に波を立てているだけで――ティーカップのかちゃかちゃは羊につけられた鈴の音に、クイーンのきぃきぃ声も羊かいの男の子のさけび声に――さらに赤ちゃんのくしゃみ、グリフォンの鳴き声、そのほかけったいな物音だってみんな（わかってる）、きっとせわしない 牧場 のごちゃごちゃ がやがやに――それから、遠くから聞こえる牛のモーモーに、ウミガメフーミのなみだ声も入れ変わってしまうだけなのに。

最後にひとり思いえがくのは、この当の小さい妹がこれから先、ひとりの女に育っていくさま。大人にふくらんでいくなかでもずっと、子どものころの、すなおなあたたかい心を持ち続けていくのか。そして、だれかの子どもをそばに集め、たくさんとっぴな話をしては、その子たちの目をきらきらかがやかせるのだろうか。その話は、遠い昔のふしぎの国のゆめそのものだったり？　すなおに悲しむその子たちのそばで、自分もと、すなおにはしゃぐその子たちにかこまれ、楽しかったと気づくのかな、自分の子ども時代の思い出、あの幸せな夏の日々に。